<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Topicks in the laws of England, containing media apt for argument, and resolution of law cases ...</title>
            <author>Clayton, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20402</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11687743</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205088</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240873880</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11687743</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20402)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1482:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Topicks in the laws of England, containing media apt for argument, and resolution of law cases ...</title>
                  <author>Clayton, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 138 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.L. for William Leake and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Clayton.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: J.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Law School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:1"/>
            <p>TOPICKS In the Laws of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing <hi>Media,</hi> apt for Argument, and resolution of <hi>Law</hi> Cases: also an Exposition of severall words, not touched by former <hi>Glossaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Non omne Argumentum undique venit ideoque non passim quaerendum est, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus alioquin error est exhaustoque labore quod non ratione scrutabimus non poteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus invenire nisi casu.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Quintil.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>R. L.</hi> for <hi>William Leake,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the signe of the Crown in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> betweene the two Temple Gates. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:2"/>
            <head>To the HONORABLE OLIVER Saint JOHN Esquire Solicitor Generall, AND OLIVER CRUMWEL Esquire, the Honourable, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Valiant Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be matter of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, that any thing of Law should now be heard but to whisper amidst the noyse of lowd Instrument of Warre, this may Apologize, that both sides professe the mayntenance of Laws. If
<pb facs="tcp:205088:3"/> again it seeme strange to any that I joyne for Patrons of a Lawbooke a Sword-man, and one of the long Robe together: let this suffice, that the last is well known to have bin longer time a <hi>Mecoenas</hi> of Schollers, then a Commander of Souldiers and men are also well perswaded that the points of these swords are bent onely against the adversaries of those Laws which are written upon their hilts. These Laws are now in danger, and the Common-wealth with them who can sit still and do nothing like old <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> when his house was on fire em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing his only daughter, but helped nothing till himselfe and shee were consumed in the flame. With my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state I cannot helpe, that was long since taken from mee by the injustice &amp; oppression of the Popish Northern Army and our own malignant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen who called in that Army, and assisted them. With my body I can do little being somewhat in yeers and
<pb facs="tcp:205088:3"/> more unfitted by a sedentary life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides uncalled upon for such services. I both approve and somwhat resemble the <hi>Spaniards</hi> posture, who when he is bleeding his last, and so weake hee cannot stand to fight, yet while any life is in him hee will be brodding at, and pottering upon the ground, every way with his Rapier or Dagger point as if hee would doe somthing, wound his enemie, &amp;c. if he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. These weake essayes shews a minde to doe good to the publike; In them little new Law can be found, they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shew how to use the old, the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of the Laws which is to be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to all other Sciences, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Philosopher <hi>Organon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gánon.</hi> If these observations shall have any use that way or any else, I have my ends: Your honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to me who are so much one for the publike hath been reason enough to me to joyne you in this Dedication, <hi>Eadem sentitis, eadem agitis, in foro
<pb facs="tcp:205088:4"/> &amp; in campo.</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> called some of their Worthies <hi>Gladii Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum,</hi> so <hi>Marcellus,</hi> other <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pei,</hi> so <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> both goe together, both usefull now. I shall not need much to implore your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections who cherish every sparke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears for the publike. The Lord make you ride on with good luck for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynting again his Majesty, and the great Councel of <hi>England,</hi> the Head and the Members, and that the Laws, one part (whereof is priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) may be maintained and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed, for as <hi>Bracton</hi> saith, <hi>Parum est jus in Civitate esse, nisi sint qui possint jura gerere,</hi> which if I mistake not, is a main ground of this bloudie Quarrell, which God end in due time, and in the accomplishment of Peace and Truth, which shall be the continued prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant, J. C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my chamber in the Inner Temple.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>MAn by his defection from his Maker, lost Truth as well as good, and is fain to gather up the one as well as the other by peecemeale, as a Bee that goes from flower to flower to get up any reasonable quantity of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: How many <hi>minutula frustu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> are there found and left from one Age to another by such as have been wittie and industrious in each Science, and altogether will not make up halfe that the first man had in the bulke <hi>unto intuitu,</hi> as it were. The Philosophers have left some <hi>Principles, Axioms,</hi> and <hi>Topikes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:5"/> the Humanists, Physitians, and Moralists <hi>Aphorismes:</hi> Musitians their <hi>Systemata,</hi> for to that Science I take that word properly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, though usurped by the later Logicians. The Lawyers their <hi>Maximes, Brocardica, Grounds,</hi> and <hi>Placita:</hi> Others their <hi>Paradigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Loca Media,</hi> fit for invention and argumentation, some of these by experience are demonstrative, and more immediately, certainly, and resolvedly bring <hi>Scientiam,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are of a lower ranke, and are called <hi>Dialectica,</hi> or <hi>Probabilia,</hi> which helpe to resolve questions and cases with a more trembling judgement, and some fears, as they say, least the truth may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and is termed opinion, as that other knowledge; of this kinde are these few Observations of mine, and I call them TOPICKS, in which one may finde matter of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for cases shall be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb facs="tcp:205088:5"/> and raise Majors in which the chiefe vigour of argument lies: I dare not call them grounds of Law, as hee did who once made an essay in this kinde, yet I finde a great <hi>Rabbin</hi> in our Law cals them <hi>Rules</hi> of Law.<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 152.</note> I have put them down in the most familiar way of our Books expression, which is in various lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which will prove most use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Law of <hi>England</hi> intending matter, not words, and it brings what we have read in our books quickest to our apprehensions, whereas the turning of those terms into fine Latine, or civill Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, as some of late makes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth to the English Lawyer, and far lesse usefull: There be 400 ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and terms of Law in our books, and yet if you have present use of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of these Topicks, you cannot finde them there, in this you may, which will serve not onely to grace argument, but resolve some doubts,
<pb facs="tcp:205088:6"/> I haue made each place good by Book Cases, and some few Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, you may add more in your daily reading without such obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, the Student will be put far to seeke for such Rules and Cases upon a suddain, I have put them in an alphabeticall order, the more easie to finde them and make use of them, other method to dream of in Law learning as some have done is vaine, sithence it consists of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite particulars, of which the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian determines thus. <hi>Individua non recipiuntur in methodum propter infinitatem.</hi> Vale.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:6"/>
            <head>Contenta.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ACt of God shall preiudice no man, <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act of a Court shall preiudice no man &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act the first who shall do where it is doubtfull, <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act implicit where not sufficient but shall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act of an Enemy shall turn to my benefit, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act subsequent shall be guided by agreement pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act imperfect of the part of one party shall be of both parties, <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act executed where it shall be defeasible and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One Act may inure to two intents, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Actori incumbit onus, <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Act to himself, where a man may do and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where part of an Act cannot be performed, yet the rest shall, <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One shall not have benefit of his own Act, preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice he may, <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One shall be punished for the Act of another, <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One shall not defeat his own Act, &amp; è contra, <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Agens &amp; consentiens pari poena plectuntur, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A posse ad esse non est bona argumentatio, sic à non essè ad non posse, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A posse ad esse bona fit argumentatio, <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A non posse ad non esse bona fit argumentatio, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Act me invito made is not my act, <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Argumentum à minori ad maius tenet affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:7"/>
               <item>Bonum publicum privato preferendum, <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Causa qualis tale causatum, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Causatum non excedit suam causam, <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Causans damnum equalis facienti, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coniunctive, and collective, words taken scorsim and discretive, <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Causa cessante cessat effectus. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coliquintidae parum totum ius vitiat, <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A coniunctis ad devisa male arguitur, <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coniunctorum utrumque oportet esse verum, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Damnum absque iniuria, not punishable. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Deus &amp; natura ferenda, <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dictum partis, is not exclusive taciti dicti legit, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Disiunctorum sufficit alterum esse verum, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Distructio facti, shall be eodem modo quo creatio.</item>
               <item>Dictum partis, which is no more then dictum legis operates nothing at all. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dominus &amp; servus, Iudge and Minister, Subiect and Sovereigne, Idem non erit, so Iudge and party, <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dignior dat nomen rei, &amp; regulabit eam, <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duty once discharged is always discharged, <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>De non existentibus &amp; aliter exisentibus, quam lex vult eadem ratio, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aequipollentia habent eundem in lege vigorem, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Eadem ratio, idemius. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Expressum &amp; particulare facit cessare tacitum &amp; generale, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Exceptio firmat regulam, concessionem, &amp;c. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aetymologia verborum non praebet firmum argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Exitus acta probat, <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Expositio verborum, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:205088:7"/>
                     <item>Averia</item>
                     <item>Aut</item>
                     <item>A, ab, abs</item>
                     <item>Abathia</item>
                     <item>Antchac</item>
                     <item>Competent</item>
                     <item>Consueta</item>
                     <item>Circiter</item>
                     <item>Citra</item>
                     <item>Infra Circa</item>
                     <item>Discretion</item>
                     <item>Donque, then, tunc</item>
                     <item>Demise</item>
                     <item>Et</item>
                     <item>Expiration</item>
                     <item>Esteant, being</item>
                     <item>Exactionibus</item>
                     <item>Est, suit</item>
                     <item>Eviction</item>
                     <item>House</item>
                     <item>Horrible, enormous</item>
                     <item>Incontinenter &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</item>
                     <item>Infra <hi>4</hi> Maria</item>
                     <item>Inhabitant</item>
                     <item>Resiant, commorant</item>
                     <item>In, apud, ad, de</item>
                     <item>Interest</item>
                     <item>In manibus</item>
                     <item>Inde</item>
                     <item>In rerum natura</item>
                     <item>Ipso facto</item>
                     <item>Iuxta</item>
                     <item>Infra</item>
                     <item>Maeremium</item>
                     <item>Meniall</item>
                     <item>Nuper</item>
                     <item>Pacatione</item>
                     <item>Praetextu</item>
                     <item>Prima, Proxima</item>
                     <item>Pacifice</item>
                     <item>Pro</item>
                     <item>Forfeiture</item>
                     <item>Puer</item>
                     <item>Nos, vos</item>
                     <item>Permittere</item>
                     <item>Res</item>
                     <item>Sufficienter</item>
                     <item>Sure, estate</item>
                     <item>Similiter</item>
                     <item>Praedict.</item>
                     <item>Paratus</item>
                     <item>Et caetera</item>
                     <item>Comodities</item>
                     <item>Sovereigne</item>
                     <item>Subditus</item>
                     <item>Miniments</item>
                     <item>Expositio verborum in Wills.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Fixio iuris neminem ledere debet, <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fortior est obligatio partis quam legis, <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fortior est dispositio legis quam hominis, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fortior &amp; melior est provisio legis quā hominis, <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fundamento distructio cadit opus, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:8"/>
               <item>Generale nihil certum ponit, <hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Generall words where they will help particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Generall words in grants where they shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained by particular words in the same clause, and contrary, <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Generale discendens in particulare sive speciale, shall be ruled by that speciall. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He that needs most let him blow the cole, <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Integra lex separat &amp; individua, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Idem taken pro simile, <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Inconvenience, See <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Indefinitum supplet locum universalis, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ignorantia non excusat, <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Inter aequales melior est conditio possidentis, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Interation of a small offence will make it amount to a great one, <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iniuria propria non cadit in beneficium facientis, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In praesentia maioris cessat potestas minoris, <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Laches may preiudice but shall not ayd any man, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law avoids circuit of action, <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law yeilds to necessity, <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law will suffer a mischief rather then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience. <hi>63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex non cogit ad impossibilia, <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex iudicat de impossibiliter faciendis quasi fractis <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex accepit voluntatem &amp; diligentiam pro facto, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex iudicat de rebus necessario faciendis quafire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipsa sactis, <hi>67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law iudgeth of that may be done as actually done, <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:8"/>
               <item>The Law iudgeth of some things actually done as not done &amp; e converso. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law adiudgeth the same thing in esse, &amp; non esse to divers purposes. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quod lex dicit factum, est sic acsi, by the party himself. <hi>71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law iudges that it is illegally done, as not done at all. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leges priores per posteriores abroguntur, &amp; contra. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex non cogit ad vana peragenda. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex non haeret in syllabis vel literis modo de sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantia constat. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law is sometimes stricter then the words of the party in force. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex non est curiosa. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>De minimis non curat lex. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Law presumes more then the party himself says. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex intendit optima perfecta &amp; effectualia &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex omnia suaviter, &amp; ad melius disponit. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex semper dabit remedium. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lex iudicat de insufficienter vel vane factis quasi omnino insectis. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law will accept of that is good in grants or pleadings, and reiect the surplus. <hi>84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law is more agile in working then the act of the paty. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law where it enioyns an Act to be done will provide be shall not be burt, à latere that doth it. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law regards the principall thing, and not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionals. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law adiudges the deniall to do a thing is not
<pb facs="tcp:205088:9"/> doing it or breach of covenant. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law-is not satisfied with shadows but sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Law hath an eye to the beginning of Acts. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Loquendum ut vulgus. <hi>87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A lawfull act by matter, ex post facto, may become unlawfull. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Malitia mutat legem. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Melior dabit nomen rei. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Magis dignum trahit ad se minus. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Magis continet in se minus. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Modus &amp; conventio vincant legem &amp; Regem &amp; contra. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nihil dat, quod non habet. <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nemo bis punietur pro uno delicto. <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Negativum nihil implicat, in a precipe quod red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nemo tenetur seipsum prodere. <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Negatio duplex est affirmatio. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ou une est a defetur chose ceo ne serra obiect alui <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ou chose fait per implication serra bone, &amp; contra. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ou chose serra, rule per le greinder part de le state. <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ouvne serra sou iudg, demesne, paymaster, carver, &amp;c. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Parols ou voilent amount al act &amp; contra. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Parols subsequent bounded or qualified by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, &amp; è converso. <hi>104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Parolx font plea. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poena aptabitur damno. <hi>105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poena sine culpa. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poena delictum superabit. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Particeps criminis &amp; non poenae. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:9"/>
               <item>Poena tollitur cum culpa, vel sequitur culpam. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Propositio hypothetica taken Categorice. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Principio non valens tractu temporis non conva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lescit. <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Principio valens tractu temporis non devalescit. <hi>109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Principio dato sequitur concomitans, &amp; sit sublato. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Praesumptioni stabitur donec probetur in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. <hi>110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui tacet consentire videtur. <hi>111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui sentit commodum sentire debet &amp; onus. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui sentit onus sentire debet &amp; commodum. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui per aliud facit per seipsum facere videtur. <hi>112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui remedio destituitur reipsa valet, si culpa absit. <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Qui magis scit &amp; potest de eo magis requiritur. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quicquid solo superstruitur solo cedet. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quicquid remittitur fieri aequat facto. <hi>114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quae non prosunt singula iuncta iuvant. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quod necessario intelligitur non d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est. <hi>ibi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Quod non capit discus rapit fiscus. <hi>115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ratio dicti minus valet quàm dictum ubi differunt. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relations. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relatio &amp; non ad ultimum. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation will rectifie incertainties in place, time, measure, &amp;c. <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation shall make things have beene, as if they had never beene. <hi>118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation to defeat a thing, shall be intenta ad u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. <hi>119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation will yeild to necessity. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation shall not be to take away things collaterall, &amp;c. <hi>120</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:205088:10"/>
               <item>Relatio ad principium, &amp;c. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ralation to time, place, &amp;c. <hi>121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relatio sit ad accommodatiorae. <hi>122</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation to avoid thing or a vain thing will destroy that was good in the premises. <hi>123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Semel malus semper presumitur malus &amp; contra, <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Similitudo non currit quatuor pedibus <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sic utere tuo, ut non laedas alieno. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Singulare distributive sumpta aequa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plurali. <hi>125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Synonyma will not serve in our Law. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Surplusse, what power and influence this shall have in Grants, <hi>126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Totum continet suas partes &amp; è converso. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Totius &amp; partis eadem ratio. <hi>127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Totum qui concedit partes negare non potest. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tort of his own wrong, a man shall take advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vtile per inutile non vitiatur, nec emendatur. <hi>129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Void, in a Statute where it is said what sense it hath, &amp;c. <hi>131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Void, where a thing shall be for part, or for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time onely. <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Void act as to that was intended, may yet be good and effectuall to a colaterall purpose. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Volenti non fit iniuria. <hi>134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Verba discretiva, shall not extend to ioynt words &amp; contra. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Verba coniuncta non capiantus discretive &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. <hi>135</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vna hirundo non facit ver. <hi>136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vniversale non comprehendit omne particulare. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vbi duo iuria in una concurrunt persona aeque est ac in diversis. <hi>137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vigilantibus non dormientibus subveniunt leges. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205088:10"/>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He act of God shall preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice no man.</hi> Upon this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it is if the heire at full age tender Livery, and dye within three moneths,<note place="margin">8 Report <hi>Halls</hi> Case.</note> which is the time given by law to finish his Livery, he shall have no prejudice, but as much benefit as if he had actually sued it forth, and the interest of the King is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Lessee for the life of I.S. is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seised, now to recover the mean profit the Law requires an entry, if I.S. dye, which is the act of God, by which his entry is taken away, he shall mayntain an action of trespasse without entry,<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 28.</note> and recover the mean profits. Lessee Covenant to leave a wood in such plight as it was in time of the lease, it is subverted by tempest, he is excused of his Covenant.<note place="margin">1 Report. 98.</note> The <hi>same Law</hi> is of <hi>impossibility,</hi> as if it be impossible to gain actuall seisin, in such case tenancy by the courtesie shall be without it, as in case of Rent and Advowson, and the wife dye before the rent day, &amp;c.<note place="margin">2 H. 3.</note>
               <hi>Exception out of this rule is,</hi> if the act of God is not so meerly, but the folly of the party inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed, as where after battle joined, one of the parties becomes blind by his own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205088:11"/> it shall not excuse him which otherwise would. A River changeth his course and runs upon my ground,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 93.</note> the common road shall be upon this as formerly, because it is not meerly the act of God, but my negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. In like manner, the rule of Impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility fails where it was known to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">4 H. 6. 3.</note> and therefore if I am bound to go to <hi>Rome</hi> and return in one day the bonds good. So if the matter was not meerly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible, as if I. S. assume to carry goods safe by water, and they are overthrowne by tempest, this shall not excuse him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he might have carried them another way,<note place="margin">32 Eliz.</note> &amp;c. but if the carriage was to be by Sea otherwise it had been. Lastly, impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility shal not excuse where no person is in being at the time to receive hurt by the im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>possibility, as tenant for life is the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the right heires of I. S. Tenant for life is disseised,<note place="margin">1 Report Case <hi>Archer.</hi>
               </note> and disseisor levies a fine at the Common Law, I. S. dyes, his right heire shall be bound, &amp;c. though it was impossible he should make claime, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for to avoid it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Act of a Court shall prejudice no man &amp; contra.</hi> In assize a verdict is given for the Plantiffe and at this time Corne was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205088:11"/> growing upon the land, the assize is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed into the Common Place and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judgment given the corne is severed and taken away,<note place="margin">41 E. 3. 19.</note> he which recovered shall lose the Corne by this adjournment. A man ought to have the priviledge of the Chancery, as servant,<note place="margin">35 H. 6. 3.</note> the Court advises upon it, and in the mean time the master is dicharged of his office, yet the servant shall have his priviledge. The Court inlargeth him that is in execution contrary to the Law,<note place="margin">2 E. 4. 8.</note> its said the party is without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, <hi>utlagarie</hi> after judgment is pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Chancellor, the debt not satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied which is a wrong,<note place="margin">2 Eliz. <hi>Dyer</hi> 172.</note> Its left doubtfull whether the party can have any remedy, yet for the most part the party shall not be prejudiced, as if the Court advise upon a protection and before the day, in Bench the protection is repealed,<note place="margin">10 H. 6. 6.</note> or a Writ of Errour cast in upon the first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, upon which this in question depends, yet the Court will give judgment. After Counsance of plea prayed,<note place="margin">35 H. 6. 54.</note> the Court gives a continuance, this shall not hinder the party to have Conusance of plea. See <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutes</hi> 3. <hi>title Appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Who shall do the first Act, where it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205088:12"/> doubtfull.</hi> Hee that shall have advantage by it shall do it,<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 18.</note> the condition of a bond is if the obligor resigne his Benefice for a pension to be granted to him as they can agree, then the bond to be void. It is not sufficient to agree of the pension, but the obliegee shal tender a deed for the assuring of it to the obligor. So where a Covenant is to assure the Mannor of D. to I. S. before <hi>Michael.</hi> next, as Counsell shall advise the Counsell of I.S. shall give the advise, and also tender the assurance. Note where the thing is certain to be done, hee which is bound in assumpsit, or a bond shall do it to to save an action, and damage to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered against him. Assumpsit to make a feoffment to I. S. is, and an action is brought without request or tendor of any deed of feoffment, and well mayntainable because the other may make it without deed and request is not agreed upon. Condition of a bond is that the obligee shall bring three ells of cloth to the shop of the obligor which shall be measured,<note place="margin">Old book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, 5.</note> the obligor shall do it to save his bond, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter est,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>E. 3.</hi> Car. per Noy. in Casu &amp; Brown Stroude.</note> if the obligor is the tailor. An obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is to build a house, as I.S. shal devise the obligor ought to procure this advise to save his bond</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205088:12"/>4 <hi>Act implicit where not sufficient but shall be explicit.</hi> Two Garnishers are in a reall action, and a stranger in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence doth speak the words of garnish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this is not sufficient,<note place="margin">43 E. 3. 32.</note> but they in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per person ought to do it themselves.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Act of an Enemy shall turn to my benefit.</hi> As where severall <hi>Nisi prius</hi> are sued by the Plantiffe &amp; Defendant by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso, and they have severall <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Eliz. <hi>Dyer</hi> 217.</note> the Plaintiffe faile <hi>in Jurata Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuanda,</hi> but the Defendant doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it, the Plantiffe shall take avail by it, as if he himself had done it.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Act subsequent shall be guided by agreement precedent.</hi> I.S. pays a hundred pounds at the day in the condition limited,<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 109.</note> if agreement was before that hee should have part of that hundred pound againe, this is no performance of the condition. A. brings goods into the Market to sell and there was an agreement before out of the Market for these same goods,<note place="margin">1 Mar. <hi>Dyer</hi> 99</note> if I. S. had the true property of these, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is altered by this sale. <hi>Sic è converso.</hi> Act precedent by act subsequent, as where the Lord distreins his tenant, and after kils the distresse, this in Law is a Declaration
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205088:13"/> of his intent from the beginning,<note place="margin">12 E. 4. 8.</note> and makes him a trespesser. Land discends to two daughters, the eldest enters into the whole, and makes a feoffment with War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty,<note place="margin">9 Report Case <hi>Dowman.</hi>
               </note> this declares the generall entre to be for her self, and not for them both, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently it is no Warranty by disseisin.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Act imperfect of the part of the one party shall be so of both.</hi> As a woman with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the age of 12 yeers is married to a man of above 14 yeers,<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 79</note> in this case though hee may consent to marriage, yet because shee cannot, he is at liberty to dis gree to this marriage as well as the woman.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">P. 42 Eliz. Case <hi>Costerd.</hi>
               </note>8 <hi>Act executed where it shall be defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and contrary.</hi> The husband and wife joyn in a Lease of the Lands of the wife, or grant her goods, and after they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced this shall stand. So when an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrator doth necessary acts, and then the Executor proves the Will, yet those acts shall stand firme; so where a Parson makes a Lease,<note place="margin">Institute 1. 138. &amp; Kell. 126.</note> and after is deprived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause a Layman, the Lease shall stand.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>One Act may inure to two intents.</hi> The tenant infests the Lord and a stranger, and makes livery to the stranger,<note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>B.</hi> &amp; <hi>Bac.</hi>
               </note> in name of both the Lord enters and distreins, this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205088:13"/> is a disagreement to the feoffment, and a devesting of the Freehold. Tenant for life impleaded,<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 37.</note> prayeth in ayde of the Grantee of the Reversion▪ this shall amount to an Attournament. Lessee Surrenders to the Grantee of the Reversion, this amounts also to an Atourment.<note place="margin">12 H. 7. 15. Plo. 87. 5 Report 15.</note> A Parson demiseth to his Patron who assignes this over to I. S. this is a good grant of the tearme, and also a Confirmation,<note place="margin">6 Report Case <hi>Fitzwilliams.</hi>
               </note> the same Indenture may revoke the old uses, and declare new uses.</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Actori incumbit onus.</hi> A partition is sued of the Mannor of D. one defendant alledges that part of the land was purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, &amp; is not parcel of the Mannor,<note place="margin">Dyer 266.</note> he ought shew the certainty of that parcell, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Jury are not bound to find it, if they do that, <hi>est veresimile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>An Act to himself,</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 H. 7. 4. Institutes 2. 139. 14 H 6. 2. 5 H. 7. 2.</note>
               <hi>a man may doe and contrary.</hi> A Sheriffe is Plantiffe, hee may take pledges to himselfe, and hee may execute a <hi>Replevin</hi> against himself as I.S. tenant in tayle, vouch himselfe to save the tayle, hee may have Processe against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.<note place="margin">8 E. 3. 21.</note> The Sheriffe is in seisin of a Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, of a Liberty by seisure, he himselfe as Sheriffe shall command himself as Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205088:14"/> of that Liberty, to execute that Processe. There is a Writ in the Register directed to the Sheriff, to inhibit himself, that hee proceed not in a Writ of right,<note place="margin">F.n.b. 4. e.</note> a Bishop is defendant in a Writ of Dower, he himself shall certifie the loyalty of the marriage in his own Case.<note place="margin">10 E. 2. ff. Triall 100.</note> The old books differ whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Sheriff may summon himself or no, but later authorities have resolved it, that he cannot, but where two Sheriffs are, the one may summon the other,<note place="margin">Michel 14. &amp; 15 Eliz. Case, Vic. <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </note> but then note a speciall mention shall be of that in the Writ, and direction that the other shall summon him. It is holden, the Sheriff who is demandant may execute all processe till it come at the <hi>Venire facias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 E. 4. 7.</note> otherwise where he is tenant. The Archb. of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> is made executor to one, who hath <hi>bona notabilia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 E. 4. 33.</note> if he wil refuse the executor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship hee shall make this before his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missary and not by himselfe; a Sheriffe is conusee of a statute,<note place="margin">Trin. 43. Eliz. Case. Sir <hi>Thomas Gerrerd.</hi>
               </note> he cannot execute a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate himselfe. It is doubted whether a steward may admit himself to a Copyhold or no. See more of this title, 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8.31. <hi>Plo. casu, Plat. vicesimo primo</hi> 6.16. <hi>Coke Jurisdiction of Court.</hi> 105.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Where part of an Act cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205088:14"/> yet the rest shall.</hi> The condition of a bond is that I.S. shall be assured at <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">40 E. 3. 12. Case <hi>Io. de Pech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> of the Remaynder of the Mannour of D. after the death of I.S. and that H. shall be present at this assurance, H. dyes before <hi>Michael.</hi> yet the assurance shall be made, the same Law is if the words were that R. himself should be present, though he comes not then and there, yet the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance shall not stay of that, because his presence is not necessary, For the Remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be limited to him absent.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>One shall not have benefit of his own Act; prejudice he may.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 E. 4. 4.</note> A man is <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage</hi> of felony, or condemned in debt, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution shal be done notwithstanding. And this holds against the King himselfe. Q. <hi>Mary</hi> who had an estate <hi>dum sola fuerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Mar. Dyer, 141.</note> granted a Rent, the Reversion discends to her, and then shee marries, it seems shee shall not avoid this Rent by her mariage, <hi>contra est aliquando,</hi> by the folly of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as one enters a bond to A. that he and A. shall stand to the arbitrement of I. S. or that A. shal take a Feoffment of him. A.<note place="margin">33 H. 6. ff. barr. 165.</note> refuses, he himself shall take the forfeiture of this bond for the folly of the other to undertake this. If one that hath Collation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205088:15"/> to a Benefice, do present to it hee hath lost his Collation, and subjected the Church to a lapse,<note place="margin">F.n.b. 35 E. 2.</note> &amp;c. so if a Parson impropriate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the Church, it makes it disappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate. A Lord holds land for the value of the mariage by two yeeres, and the tenant enters before all is levied, the Lord shall recover the whole value. An heire who held by homage and fealty takes his land of the King upon office found,<note place="margin">44 Ass. 35.</note> that hee held by forty pound <hi>per annum,</hi> he shall be bound all his life time to pay that Rent so prejudiced by his act.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>One shall be punished for the Act of another.</hi> A disseisor ceaseth, the dissei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see enters,<note place="margin">44 E. 34.</note> he shall be charged in a <hi>Cessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> Accompt is brought against two, the one enters into the accompt,<note place="margin">44 E. 3. 13.</note> and it is found against him, it shall bind both: One is imprisoned in the Marshalses, a stranger breaks the prison, the Marshall shall bee charged for the whole debt. I have a way over the lands of twenty men,<note place="margin">33 H. 6. 26. <hi>per Prisot.</hi>
               </note> one of them stops the way in his land, I shall have an action against all those over whose lands the way was. A rate is put upon a towne for the fees of a Knight of the Parliament, the beasts of him hath payd his part,<note place="margin">11 H. 4. 2.</note> are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205088:15"/> taken for the residue, hee shall not have a replevin, but the beasts shall be sold to pay this dutie.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>One shall not defeate his own Act: &amp; è contra.</hi> Lessee for years grants the next avoydance, and then surrender,<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Davenport.</hi>
               </note> this shall not destroy his own grant. A grant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to B. for a horse, and after grant a Rent charge, the horse of B. shall not bee destrained.<note place="margin">20 H. 7. 10. 5 Mar. Dyer 151.</note>
               <hi>Brook</hi> the chiefe Justice did put out an Officer which he himselfe had admitted before: And so an Ordinary may admit the same partie able, whom he hath returned disable before.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Agens &amp; consentiens pari poena plectuntur.</hi> If one takes a horse by wrong,<note place="margin">43 E. 3. 43.</note> by my consent, trespasse lies against mee, A. mayme, B. by assent of C. appeal lies against A. and C.<note place="margin">22 Ass. 82.</note> and damages equally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst both, otherwise it is where interest is to be bound, as Dean and Chapter, sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in <hi>simul,</hi> the Dean leaseth the Land with consent of the Chapter:<note place="margin">Dyer 40.</note> This is not good.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>A Posse adesse non est bona argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatio, sic à non esse ad non posse.</hi> A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise is of Land in fee, so of goods, if the Devisee dye before the Devisor his heire,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205088:16"/> nor Executor shall gaine any thing by this Will.<note place="margin">Plo. 345. Case <hi>Brett.</hi>
               </note> A. is indebted to B. 200 pound, and delivers goods to him to sell, <hi>meliori mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quo poterit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18 E. 4. 5.</note> to pay himselfe hee is prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered 200 pound for the goods, and refuses it, and after hee sels them for 12 pence, A. shall answer the residue of the debt not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this proffer and possibility was,<note place="margin">5 E. 3. 64.</note> &amp;c. Lands have never been departed betwixt males, therefore cannot be is a <hi>non sequitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>A posse ad esse bona fit argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</hi> Condition of a bond is to save harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse without damage, if he may be damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, though he is not <hi>in facto,</hi> the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is broken.<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Broughton.</hi>
               </note> If an Eschetor may seise goods for a forfeiture, it is all one as if hee did, when he will he may. A husband hath a terme in the right of his wife,<note place="margin">18 E. 4. 28. 50 Ass. 5.</note> and is a debtor to the King though hee dye, this term shall be charged to the King, the same law of one joynt tenant debtor. Tenant in tayle, because it is in his power to dock the remainder upon this,<note place="margin">6 Report, Sir <hi>Anthony Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais</hi> Case.</note> the law takes this as done, and for this reason puts no value upon it, as Assets to an heire, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>A non posse ad non esse bona est ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentatio.</hi> The condition is, if a rent is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205088:16"/> behind and no distresse, he may re-enter, he demands at the day, and the doore is shut against him,<note place="margin">Pasch. 23. Eliz</note> albeit a distresse is in the house, because hee cannot come to it, the condition is broken as if no distresse were there, see if request shall be to open the doore.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Act me invito fait nest mon act.</hi> I chase Deer out of my land with a dog, and after I recall the dog,<note place="margin">43 E. 3. 8.</note> but hee notwithstanding pursues him and kils him within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, I shall not be <hi>punished for this within</hi> the statute. An assize of Common is brought and hanging this the Plaintiffs cattle escape thither,<note place="margin">F.n.b. 180. 33 Ass. 9.</note> this shall not abate his Action.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Argumentum à minori ad majus tenet affirmative.</hi> Upon this reason a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso in the statute of ordinaries extends to the High Commission,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Cawdry.</hi>
               </note> which is above them, and the <hi>contrary is also true,</hi> as a sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute which speaks of Deanes doth not extend to Bishops. So the Statute of 8 <hi>H.</hi> 6. which speaks of Clerks raising Records, a Judge is not within it.<note place="margin">Institutes 3. 72. &amp; 20.</note> So in expsition of Treasons this argument doth not hold the lesse is made treason. <hi>Ergo</hi> the greater, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:205088:17"/>22 <hi>Bonum publicum privato preferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> Upon this reason a man may dig in my soyle to make Bulwarks against ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the King.<note place="margin">36 H. 8. Dyer 60. 8. E. 4. 19. 13 E. 4. 9. Lynius 35. Plo. 322. 21 E. 4 47.</note> So fishers in the sea may come upon my land, &amp;c. Its lawfull to break a doore to finde a Felon if felony is done. Upon this reason the Civillians say, <hi>Si piscator ligat navem ad arborem domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus arboris eam incidere non potest:</hi> upon this reason it was that the King might cut my trees for repayre of his Castles before <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> And if the King grant to a County or Hundred, that they shal not be Jurors in Enquests, it is void, because pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique prejudiced.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Causa qualis tale Causatum.</hi> I cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with one, &amp; his executors make a lease of B. Acre before <hi>Michael.</hi> and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venantee dyes before <hi>Michael,</hi> and I make the Lease to his Executor, this Lease shall be in the same degree as the Covenant was,<note place="margin">Plo. 292. Case <hi>Chapman.</hi>
               </note> and so shall be to the use of the testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and Assets in the Executor, the same Law is if an Executor have a villaine who purchaseth land, hee shall have this as he held the villaine, &amp;c. <hi>fallit regula,</hi> In case assise is brought oyntly against fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his daughter, and the father sayes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205088:17"/> he is villein to I. S. howbeit shee is of the like quality,<note place="margin">10 Ass. 7.</note> yet this plea shall not be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall to her.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Causatum non excedit suam cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam.</hi> Tenant for years grants a Rent for life of the Grantee. He shall not have fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hold in this Rent, but if he die within the terme, the Rent shall cease, and shall be as if granted for so many years as the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath, if the Grantee so long live,<note place="margin">Plo. 524. 15 E. 4. 8. Plo. 555.</note> but see <hi>ibid.</hi> that for necessity of reason, and by fiction in Law, it may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Causans damnum equalis faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti.</hi> If one breake down a gap in my hedge,<note place="margin">9 E. 4. 4.</note> by which beasts escape into my Close, from the Common adjoyning, now the trespasse which at the first was onely 4. d. may bee 20. lib. by the insuing da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. Two combat,<note place="margin">Stamford 17.</note> and the one kils the other, &amp; this was by reason of the words of a woman; shee was arraigned for this felonie. Trespasse for burning the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs house,<note place="margin">48 E. 3. 25.</note> &amp; declares that it was burnt by negligence of the defendant and holden, a good count to maintain their writ. If the partie shews other goods then he ought to do in a Replevin,<note place="margin">11 H. 4. 91.</note> or in a <hi>Cap. sa.</hi> shews a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205088:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:205088:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:205088:19"/> man to the Officer, he shall be charged in trespasse, and false imprisonment, and so shall the other too. Somtime the Law more punishes the causor then the actor of an injury as a <hi>Capias</hi> issueth where it ought not,<note place="margin">Michel. 23. H. 7. Kell. Pla. 5.</note> he that took it out shall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, but the sheriffe excused.</p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>Conjunctive, and collective, words taken seorsim and discretive.</hi> Three men submit themselves to arbittrement of all matters betwixt them and A, this shall be not onely of matters they have joyntly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst A,<note place="margin">2 R. 3. 18.</note> but what either of them hath against him. An estate is limited to two. &amp; if they die without issue, the remainder to another in this case, upon the death of either of them, the estate as to his part shall go to the remainder man. Severall demises and rents are in one Indenture of lease and lessee Covenants,<note place="margin">16 Eliz. Dyer Case, <hi>Clatches.</hi>
               </note> to pay <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum praedictum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">No. lib. d' En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries 115.</note> this Covenant extends to all the severall rents: Two grant <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia bona,</hi> so A. releases to B. and C. all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,<note place="margin">19 H. 6. 6.</note> this extends to their severall goods and actions, as well as joynt. Three se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall men make three severall Covenants, and in conclusion of the Indenture one is bound to performe the Covenants made<note place="margin">11 H. 7. 6.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205088:19"/> betwixt A. I. and S. This doth extend to the Covenants <hi>separatim. A scire facias</hi> is against the successor of a Prior of D.<note place="margin">17 E. 4. 2.</note> and shews a recovery against his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessour and part behinde in his owne time. <hi>Et quod non redierunt, &amp;c.</hi> and this ruled good. See <hi>Dyer</hi> 150,</p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>Causa cessante cessat effectus.</hi> If the offence is pardoned,<note place="margin">37 H. 621. 5 Report Case <hi>Vaughan.</hi> 36 H. 624. 15 E. 4. 17.</note> for which the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe ought to be amerced, no amercement shall be. The husband and wife lease by deed, he dyes shee accepts the rent, if the Lessee lose the Deed of lease, she shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the lease, for this was the sole cause she was estopped, &amp;c. The Feoffor shall have and hold the Charter of the land a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Feoffee, by reason of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty,<note place="margin">1 Report 2. 4 Report. Case <hi>Acto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> but if this determine he shall hold them no longer, but note it is cause exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutory is intended, as Annuity granted <hi>pro consilio.</hi> I grant to I. S. that I will clayme nothing in the Mannour D. of which the Grantee is seised, and for this he grants me an Annuity,<note place="margin">15 E. 4. 3.</note> in this Case the entry of the Grantee wil not cause the annuity to cease, and see <hi>ibid.</hi> A good Case of an Advowson granted for an annuity.<note place="margin">24 E. 3. 53. 4 <hi>Abbot</hi> and <hi>Lewes</hi> Case.</note> And note it is not in the power of the Grantor to cease his own
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205088:20"/> grant, as if hee will say to the Grantee hee will not have his Counsell, the Annuity shal continue, though <hi>Richel</hi> in 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4. 16 thought otherwise. A man grants to make a new pale for the old one, if hee cannot have the old one, he is discharged to make a new one, yet in <hi>Pigots</hi> case, if he can have an Action for the old pale, he is bound to make the new one.<note place="margin">15. E. 43. 5 E. 4. &amp;</note> Note another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, where the Office determines for which the Annuity was granted, that shall cease also. see 12 <hi>Ass.</hi> 41. 20 <hi>Ass.</hi> 27 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 10. 49 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 45. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>ultimo.</hi> Note another difference.<note place="margin">Plo. 381.</note> It must be <hi>causa</hi> not <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantia,</hi> which causes this Cesser, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where Covenant is to make Divine Service in the house of the Grantee every Sabboath day, though the Grantee depart with the house, yet the service shall be done.<note place="margin">6 H. 41.</note> But if the cause cease but in part, the whole Annuity shall be lost. The King grants the office of a Keeper to two, and the one fails in discharge of his duty, the the whole fee shall determine. So if An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity is for Counsell to two,<note place="margin">Plo. Case. <hi>Nevill.</hi>
               </note> and the one refuse, <hi>fallit haec regula,</hi> as where a Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian in Chivalry hath the body in ward, and there be other lands in Soccage, the next of kin shall not have this land in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205088:20"/> Ward,<note place="margin">Plo. Case. <hi>Carrell.</hi>
               </note> though the body of the Ward is to another (which is the cause) but the next of kin to whom it cannot discend shall have it. Arbitrement is to pay ten pounds for sixe yeeres, to educate B, B. dyes, yet the payment shall continue during the terme,<note place="margin">Dyer 329.</note> Processe agard to the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for Cosinage to the Sheriffe, who after becomes out of office, and another put in,<note place="margin">14 H. 731. 18 E. 4. 3.</note> yet the Processe shall continue to the Coroners. <hi>Vide</hi> more of this matter and title, 4 <hi>Mar. Dyer</hi> 141. <hi>Kell.</hi> 124. <hi>Davis Reports</hi> 3. and <hi>Case Lutterell</hi> 4 <hi>Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Coliquintidae parum totum Jus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat.</hi> A suit is in the spirituall Court for wood, tithable, if any part is free from tithes, a prohibition lyes for the whole: if for part of the action, though the lesse part,<note place="margin">11 H. 489.</note> jurisdiction ought not to be to the Court where it is begun. It shall be outed for all. A bond is made upon a usurious contract for part, all shall be avoyded.<note place="margin">In 33 Eliz. Case <hi>Paramor</hi> and <hi>Robinson.</hi> 22 H. 6. 6.</note> If my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell labour jurors, hee is a mayntainer <hi>ab initio,</hi> even for his Counsell. Husband and wife do vary in the declaration of uses for the particular estate as for life, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, as to the fee it is void for all.<note place="margin">2 Report Case <hi>Beckwith.</hi>
               </note> Divers Covenants in an Indenture are void, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205088:21"/> it is concerning a grant of an office contrary to the statute 5 <hi>E.</hi> 6. and one Covenant therein is good yet the bond to performe Covenants is void for all.<note place="margin">1 Report. 82. <hi>Cal. Colshill.</hi>
               </note> Superstitious use intermixed infects all the good,<note place="margin">2 Report 113.</note> so covine.</p>
            <p n="28">28 <hi>A Conjunctis ad devisa male argui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> as the Ordinary may take a refusall by all the executors,<note place="margin">9 Report Case <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enlose.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H. 7. 19.</note>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> of any is false. One is heire to husband and wife, <hi>Ergo,</hi> to the husband is a <hi>non sequitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Conjunctorum utrumque oportet esse verum,</hi> and performed, as where the condition of a bond is double, so the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of assumpsit both shal be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.<note place="margin">44 E. 4 21. 4 Report Case <hi>Digbie.</hi>
               </note> A license <hi>recipere &amp; retinere,</hi> both shal be done, leafe is &amp; bond to pay 10 <hi>li.</hi> rent if no restreint be of sowing &amp; making woad, and after a Proclamation is to prohibit sowing of Woad, he shall pay his rent in this case.<note place="margin">T. 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liz. Rot. 431. Case <hi>Shervvod.</hi>
               </note> Rent is granted out of land in the tenure and occupation of I. S. though he had it all in Lease, if hee have it not in occupation, the land is not charged.</p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnum asque injuria, is not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 H. 447. 22 his 14. 7 E. 3. 65.</note> As if a Schoole-master erect a new Schoole to the hurt of the former Master; so if a new M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll is set up to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205088:21"/> prejudice of the ancient one to which all within the Town resorted before, no acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lies, so where arable is laid down to pasture, by which my ancient pastures give not such a rate as formerly, or agis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not so much. 31 <hi>Sic è conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uria absque damno is not actiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> A man is affied to a woman, and when the bains are published in the Church, another forbids them, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that hee hath another wife, which is false, this is <hi>Injuria absque damno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trin. 5. Car. Case <hi>Ap. Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he may compell her to marry him being affied. I may enter into your close, and put out Savages,<note place="margin">Michel. 12. H. 7. Kell. 2.</note> or your own cattle out of your corne, which have escaped in by your own fence.</p>
            <p n="32">32 <hi>Deus &amp; natura ferenda.</hi> If the water change his course, and run upon my Land,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 93.</note> the common road shall be there as before.</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Dictum partis, is not exclusive taciti dicti legit,</hi> Lessor Covenant Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see shall have fewell by his assignement, he may take it without assignement.<note place="margin">Dyer 19. 44 E. 3. 18. 40 E. 3. 10.</note> A rent is granted to distrein for this by the Baily of the King, yet he may without him.</p>
            <p n="34">34 <hi>Disjunctorum sufficit alterum
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205088:22"/> esse verum.</hi> It is pleaded the Bishop &amp; his predecessors have used to grant such an office,<note place="margin">10 Report 59 Case <hi>Evesque-Sarum.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Tali persone, sine personis</hi> as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth; this is no affirmation that hee had granted it to more then one, so that issue can be taken upon that, but the plea is true, if he had granted it to one onely.</p>
            <p n="35">35 <hi>Distructio facti, shall be eodem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quo creatio.</hi> A specialty must be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by deed,<note place="margin">7 E. 4. 15. 5 Report Case, Com. <hi>Rutland.</hi>
               </note> an use declared by Indenture shall not be altered but by indenture, yea, though but in abatement as resceit of parcell upon a deed shall, not bee admited without deed of it,<note place="margin">15 H. 7. 10.</note> otherwise it is where matter of fact intervenes, as in covenant before he can have an action: so in case of a rent because of distresse is to be pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a good plea without deed,<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 33. 6 Report Case <hi>Blake.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H. 7. 33.</note> and so is it there, though he bring a Writ of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, <hi>quod nota.</hi> A man is bound he shall not occupy my land in D, I after let it unto him, this is not to purpose to save his bond without writing: and yet matter in fact wil aid an imperfect writing to make it good, as where an Acquittance was pleaded to a bond, and upon sight of it, it reherses it was money due upon Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase of Land now by an Averment that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205088:22"/> this bond was taken after the money due for the purchase, and agree in the summe,<note place="margin">3 H. 7. 14.</note> by this the Acquittance is helpt.</p>
            <p n="36">36 <hi>Dictum partis, which is no more then dictum Legis operates nothing at all.</hi> Lease is for life, and the Lessor grants the Rent to A. for life,<note place="margin">26 Ass. 38.</note> in whose hands so ere the Land shall come, this is no more then for the life of the Lessor. A gift is to two of land, and <hi>uni eorum diutius, viventi,</hi> they make partition and the one dyes, the survivour shall not have his part by these words, and <hi>uni eorum, &amp;c.</hi> which is no more then the law would have said. A bond is to do such an Act (if the law per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) its all one,<note place="margin">30 Ass. 8.</note> as if it had been to doe it absolutely: see 9 <hi>Report, Flowers Case.</hi> 4 <hi>Report Case Burrow.</hi> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>aliter ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su.</hi>
               <note place="margin">12 H. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> As a man charges his executor to pay his debts, by his Will by these words, the debtor may sue a man in Court Christian, <hi>quod quere,</hi> by the allower of this book. A bond to infeoffe A. if be please, though the law says as much that he cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feoffed against his will, yet it hath this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, to alter the law in this, that the obligor is not bound to make this feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till A, signifie his minde, &amp;c. The
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205088:23"/> Statute 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. says, that he who takes a second Benefice, the first shall be void, which the Ecclesiasticall law said before, yet this operation is by this expresse saying of that Act, that it shall be void without notice, where value is above eight pounds. <hi>Vide</hi> 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Dyer</hi> 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 264. <hi>Perkins</hi> 105.</p>
            <p n="38">38 <hi>Dominus &amp; Servus, Judge and Minister, Subject and Sovereigne, Idem non erit, so Judge and party.</hi> A woman is Guardian of the Fleet,<note place="margin">Plo. <hi>Plats</hi> case</note> and takes one of the prisoners to husband, this is an escape. If one hath a Benefice and is made Bishop of the said Diocesse,<note place="margin">5 E. 3.</note> the Benefice is void. He which is Justice of the Peace is made Sheriffe, the Patent of Justice determines. A man hath an Annuity for service to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> he is made King, the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice shall cease he is no longer Prince.<note place="margin">Plo. Sir <hi>Tho. Wroths</hi> Case. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eliz. Dyer 197.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Baron of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, this causes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Office to cease. So one shal not be Judge of the Kings Bench and Common Pleas. <hi>Persey arraigned an assise,</hi> with other Plantiffes, and after hee was joyned in Commission of assise, and ruled that no proceeding can be upon this Commission.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5 Aff. 3.</note> A Charter to hold,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205088:23"/> Plea, <hi>licet ipsemet sit pars, &amp;c.</hi> Is not good if there be not words to make another Judge when such a Case happens.<note place="margin">8 H. 6. 20.</note> A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable may apprehend him that breaks the peace upon himself,<note place="margin">5 H. 7. 6.</note> but that is because it is an offence to the Crowne more then to himselfe.</p>
            <p>Sheriffe is Judge in redisseisin yet hee himselfe returnes the pannell, so Judge and Minister, but the reason is because he is made Judge by statute,<note place="margin">Kell. 85.</note> not as the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, but a person described by this name. By the Civill Law a Judge may punish an injury to himselfe imprisonment or mulct,<note place="margin">Boden 309.</note>
               <hi>Sed si pars verberibus aut capite mulct anda est propter in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriae atrocit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem abstinendum est.</hi> A Writ of Error in the Exchequer is directed to the Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Barons,<note place="margin">Institutes 4. 105.</note> comanding them to have the Record before the Treasuror and Chancellor, and good.</p>
            <p n="38">38 <hi>Dignior dat nomen rei, &amp; regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit eam.</hi> A grant is of the Office of the Kings Tennis Court, &amp;c.<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Iohn Webb.</hi>
               </note> The play of the Houshold is included, and that onely gives the name. Where speech is of I.S. it shall be taken the father and not the son. Where speech is of a Will, it shall be intended
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205088:24"/> the last Will where more Wils are,<note place="margin">Dyer 314.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="40">40 <hi>Duty once discharged is alwayes discharged.</hi> The Ordinary once refuses a Clerke for insufficiency,<note place="margin">10 E. 3. 26.</note> he is not bound to take a second examination of him.</p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>De non existentibus &amp; aliter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istentibus, quam lex vult eadem ratio.</hi> If a Record is removed into a Court,<note place="margin">44 Ass. 6.</note> but not by due processe and course of law, its all one as not removed.</p>
            <p n="42">42 <hi>Aequipollentia habent eundem in lege vigorem.</hi> A Writ comes to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe to arrest A. which was in his custody before,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Frost.</hi>
               </note> and upon the escape of him an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the Case is brought, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that hee was arrested, &amp;c. <hi>&amp; bene.</hi> A Writ is to the Sheriffe, and hee returns that <hi>virtute precepti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">16 H. 7. 16.</note> he hath done so and so, and bene and equipoll, <hi>virtute brevis, &amp;c.</hi> In a Writ it is said, <hi>quam clamat esse, jus,</hi> this equipoll fee-simple, and therefore if in the following part of the Writ he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance in a lesser estate,<note place="margin">39 H. 6. 58.</note> as <hi>ex dono</hi> for life, or, &amp;c. The Writ shall abate, <hi>Vide Plo.</hi> 542 555. <hi>Dyer</hi> 171. 203. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 31. But note this <hi>exception to this generall rule,</hi> that words of art shall not be supplyed by equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent words, as voluntarie, <hi>&amp; ex mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205088:24"/> praecogitata interfecit,</hi> is not sufficient in Indictment of murder, but the word <hi>murder avit,</hi> must be.<note place="margin">9 Eliz. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. 2 H. 6. 11.</note> A Writ against M. late wife of <hi>Thomas Com.</hi> A is all one as if he had called her Countesse of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rondell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="43">43 <hi>Eadem ratio, Idem jus. So Bracton de similibus à similia eadem ratione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendum.</hi> The stat. which outs <hi>non clayme in fines,</hi> by reason of wars, takes away also <hi>non claime</hi> in a Writ of right,<note place="margin">Plo. 59, &amp; 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for the same reason is &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="44">44 <hi>Expressum &amp; particulare facit ces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sare tacitum &amp; generale,</hi>
               <note place="margin">28 H. 8. 15.</note> In this notion its said a deed is a private law amongst par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to it. By the word demise assignee of a lessee for yeers shall have an action of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant if he is disturbed, but if there is an expresse covenant in the deed, that the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see shall enjoy the house demised, &amp;c. without eviction of the lessor,<note place="margin">4 Report <hi>Nokes</hi> Case.</note> this shall restreine the covenant to the lessee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. An Abbot brings trespasse against the Parson of C. and declares of cutting trees, <hi>ad deteriorationem Ecclesiae praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae,</hi> though every Abbey is a Church, yet because it is not named before,<note place="margin">18 E. 2. ff. 6 Report 828.</note> this refers to the Parson which was named, and so
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205088:25"/> makes the Writ insensible &amp; abate. A man devises land to his eldest son, the remainder to his yonger son,<note place="margin">Hill in Iac. c. <hi>9.</hi> Casu Porriman <hi>by</hi> Bridgman.</note> the remainder <hi>proximo de sanguine</hi> of the devisor, the eldest shall not take by these generall words, but any other not named before. <hi>A.</hi> hath two messuages, and demises that in D. and all his land in S. to I. S, the messuages in S. shall not passe.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               <hi>Exception.</hi> Note, where that the expresse is against the nature of the estate, as a gift in tayle, and an express clause is, he shall not do waste, or suffer a recovery,<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 14. <hi>Perkins</hi> 660. 6 Report Case Sir <hi>Anthony Mildmay.</hi> 2 E. 4. 5.</note> or that he shall hold of the Lord Paramount, these shall not crosse the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit <hi>dictum legis,</hi> in those severall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and it is also in things insepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. As Warranty by dedi is not destroyed by expresse Warrantie. <hi>Sic regula fallit in casu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Report Case <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes.</hi>
               </note> the thing is inherent to the estate, as covenant expresse is the lessee and his executors shall repaire the house demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, &amp;c. This shall not excuse the assignee who by implyed covenant in law adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to his estate,<note place="margin">5 Redort case 23 <hi>Broughton.</hi>
               </note> is tyed to repaires, <hi>except also</hi> in case of matter of record this, though implicit will controll the expresse act <hi>in facto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Report Cap. <hi>Vernon.</hi>
               </note> as a woman enters into her joynture, &amp; then brings a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit of Dower.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205088:25"/> So where the expresse act is vaine it shall have no such operation. <hi>See Dyer</hi> 376. <hi>Kell.</hi> 123. <hi>Doctor and Student</hi> 94. And so it is also where the expresse act or word is additionall, and not contradictory of the first,<note place="margin">18 Eliz. Dyer 348.</note> as a devise is to pay ten pound rent to <hi>A.</hi> and if it is behinde six weeks, &amp;c. that <hi>A.</hi> may distreine, this shall not avoid the entry upon the condition if bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but it is variety of security for this rent. So where that which is but secret is dehors, there both may stand without the one outing the other, as bloud may be averred to have beene the consideration to rayse an use mentioned in an Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">1 Report Case <hi>Mildmay.</hi>
               </note> though money only expressed within the deed.</p>
            <p n="46">46 <hi>Exceptio firmat Regulam, conces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionem, &amp;c.</hi> A man holds by homage, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuage and rent, the Lord grants the rent <hi>cum pertinentiis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">29 Ass. 20. 23 Incidents 24.</note> the <hi>Seignio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> doth not passe by this grant, but if he h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> said (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting reliefe and escheate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doubted. Common is granted for all c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> excepting hogs, this exception inlarges this to goats, &amp;c. <hi>A</hi> man grants all his trees excepting payr-trees, apple-trees, now passe,<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 1. 2 .2. R. 2.</note> which otherwise would not. The statute of 23
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205088:26"/>
               <hi>H.</hi> 6. speaks only of Sheriffs, yet because in the end of the statute there is an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Guardian of the Fleet. It is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den all other Guardians are included as well as Sheriffs.<note place="margin">22 Eliz. Case <hi>Yastley.</hi> 11 Report 74.</note> But note, <hi>fallit haec regula,</hi> where the exception is idle. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though the statute 5 <hi>E.</hi> 6. hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception that ingrossing of salt shall not be within that statute, any ingrossing of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, yet, <hi>non sequitur,</hi> it is victuall within any statute, for it is <hi>condimentum</hi> onely.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Michael. 7.</hi> Car. in <hi>b.</hi> Roy. Information.</note> And such clauses are put in to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ignorant Burgesses; rather then for necessity, so in the statute 43 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. there is an exception in that statute, which provides against alienations to the King, in case of Ecclesiasticall persons it follows not, therefore that other persons upon whom a disability was by law before to alien as infants mad men, &amp;c. May now give away their estates, because Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticks are onely excepted.</p>
            <p n="47">47 <hi>Aetymologia verborum non praebet firmum argumentum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 340. Institutes 177. 7 Report 27.</note> And therefore to argue from the word joynture of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that therefore it must be a joynt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state with her husband is a fallacy, for its a good joynture though the estate be to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205088:26"/> her selfe sole, yet such arguments exhibits ornament in the discourse, where it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the law.</p>
            <p n="48">48 <hi>Exitus acta probat.</hi> The copying out of a Libell proves as evidence that he did publish it.<note place="margin">8 Report Case Lamb. 7 E. 4. 4. 9 Report 11.</note> The tenant is distreined without the mesnes fault, yet if hee after does not what the law requires, as putting his own beasts into the pownd, for to free the tenants beasts, the distresse shall now be said in his default. <hi>See</hi> 9 <hi>Report, Case Meriell Tressam.</hi> And <hi>vide,</hi> the Case of Estray, and how it shal be demeaned that it prove not tortious.<note place="margin">8 Report 146.</note> So in those cases of liberty given by law, as to come into a Tavern to drink, and he take away a piece of plate, this shews the act of comming in tortious <hi>ab initio, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="49">49 <hi>Expositio verborum. Averia</hi> is any live thing as fish, hens, capon, &amp;c. <hi>Aut,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. lib. entryes 138. 21 H. 6. 39.</note> albeit it is a disjunctive adverbe, yet in the Kings case it leaves his genuine sense, as where he grants land, &amp;c. <hi>Quae quidem terra concelata, aut reditus substracta, &amp;c.</hi> If the land is not concealed, though the rent is substracted,<note place="margin">11 Report 113 Case <hi>Hugh Vaughan.</hi>
               </note> and so the disjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, <hi>aut,</hi> is performed, yet the land passes not. <hi>A, ab, abs. Ab octabis Trin.</hi> is the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205088:27"/> last day of the foure,<note place="margin">21 E. 4. 37.</note>
               <hi>à festo Paschae,</hi> must be ruled by the Canons, <hi>Abathia.</hi> In <hi>Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> this extends onely to the Precincts of the Close of the Abbey, and not to all the possessions of it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 Ass. 55.</note>
               <hi>Charge. A</hi> man cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to free a purchasor of all charges up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land, this extends to a possibility of a term, which yet is no title or right, <hi>ante hac usitate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 Eliz. <hi>Dyer</hi> 362. no. lib. entrey 384.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Note in a subjects case these words, Will reach higher then in the Kings Case.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Circiter.</hi> Is an incertaine time, and therefore in case where certainty is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Pas. 28. Eliz. Case <hi>Farrer.</hi>
               </note> it is ill in pleadings, &amp;c. and therefore <hi>Circiter</hi> 21 of <hi>Feb.</hi> may be as well be afore the day as after.<note place="margin">21 E. 4. 52. lib. entrys 152.</note>
               <hi>Citra, infra. Circa fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum, sic ante festum.</hi> These are all before the <hi>Vigils</hi> of the Feast, or in the Vigils at the least.<note place="margin">Mich. 13. Eliz. b. 207. rot. 1330.</note>
               <hi>A</hi> bond is made to stand to the arbitrement of I. S. to be made <hi>ante no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum diem</hi> of <hi>October, &amp;c.</hi> The arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is well made any time before mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night of the 8 day. <hi>Citra,</hi> 50 yeers last past,<note place="margin">9 Eliz. upon <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endolf.</hi>
               </note> was rejected because unusuall, for the pleading is <hi>infra</hi> 50 yeers, &amp;c. Condition of a bond is to pay so much mony by <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> next it shall be before the day.<note place="margin">9 Eliz. per <hi>Gavvdy</hi> and Dyer.</note>
               <hi>Competent.</hi> as a competent Benefice, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205088:27"/> meaning of this word is to be found out by the annuity is to cease when such a Benefice is provided, and not in reference to the persons quality to be provided for, as if the annuity was forty shillings <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> to the Chaplain of the King, till pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, &amp;c. Of a competent Benefice ten marks <hi>per annum est,</hi> adjudged compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this case. <hi>Consueta.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 Report Case <hi>Molins.</hi>
               </note> It is taken for a thing anciently, used albeit now at the present it is discontinued &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Discretion</hi> comes of <hi>upir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judico,</hi> so Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors put themselves in discretion of the Court, that is,<note place="margin">8 H. 4. 12. 5 Report Case <hi>Rooks.</hi>
               </note> upon the judgement of the Court in point of Law, it is taken for that act of the Judge arises in case of extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Law, and amounts to as much as if he had said that the Judge shall doe according to the Law and right reason,<note place="margin">Vide Plo. 83.</note> when it's said in Statutes, &amp;c. that hee shall doe according to his discretion, See 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8, 25. <hi>Fitz James</hi> discretion menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, see 10. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 29. where it's taken <hi>pro concilio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Donque, then tunc</hi> a license is made to goe over sea, proviso if he resort to fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, <hi>then</hi> to cease he breaks the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>then</hi> here is expounded, for thence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205088:28"/> forth and not <hi>ab innitio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Eliz. Dyer 177. P. 5. <hi>Car.</hi> Case <hi>Mason.</hi>
               </note> action upon the case, consideration is <hi>quod tunc</hi> he deliver a horse, &amp;c. It's well done any time of the day after.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plo. 192. F.n.b. 194.</note>
               <hi>Demise</hi> signifies not onely the originall Lease which is made to the Lessee, but the relinquishment, grant or assignement of any thing, as in the Writ, in the <hi>per,</hi> it is said, <hi>cui</hi> A, this demise in case of fee sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple granted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et,</hi> This conjunction in our Law, hath somtimes the sence of <hi>vel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Pexall.</hi> Register 125.</note>
               <hi>&amp; sic è converse</hi> horrible <hi>and</hi> enormous taken for <hi>or</hi> enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. A bond is upon condition, if he pay part it shall be void, and also upon condition, that if hee suffer the Obligee to enjoy such a Mannour that the bond shall be void, the performance of either of these causes will avoid the bond,<note place="margin">9 Eliz.</note> which prove <hi>and</hi> or <hi>&amp;</hi> is taken in the sense of or, A rent is reserved to the Lessor, or his heirs, this rent is good to himselfe, and or is not disjunctive here.<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Mallery.</hi>
               </note> A man devises Land to G. S. and if hee die before 21 yeers of age, or without issue, to remain to a stranger,<note place="margin">Eliz. 20. Iac. in b.R. cited. per Dod. I.</note> he dies before 21. but hath issue, adjudge this word <hi>or,</hi> shall be taken for <hi>and,</hi> and both must fail, otherwise he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205088:28"/> shall have no benefit of the remainder in this case, See <hi>Plo. Manxels</hi> case, <hi>fol.</hi> 5. <hi>Bene</hi> 4 <hi>Report, Ogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls</hi> case, and 10 <hi>Report, Vaughans</hi> case, cited in <hi>Legats</hi> case, <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti.</hi> 96. 8 <hi>Report Pexals</hi> Case.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Expiration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plo. 198.</note> is properly by efflux of time and differs a fine <hi>rei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Esteant,</hi> or being.<note place="margin">27 H. 8. 17. 19.</note> 1 these words will extend to future times, and are not tyed always to the present tense.<note place="margin">16 Eliz. Dyer 333.</note> A man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viseth his land shal go to the next of bloud <hi>(being males)</hi> It shall be construed in the future tense, that shall be males, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exactionibus,</hi> is all things in action,<note place="margin">11 H. 4. 7.</note> and as large as Demands in a manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Est &amp; fuit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 H. 6. 27. 10 H. 7. 27.</note> Sometimes taken in the same sense, as if mayntenance be layed in a plea, <hi>quod fuit,</hi> betwixt such and such, in law its taken for which is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eviction.</hi> A man is bound, the obligee shall enjoy such a house, or, &amp;c.<note place="margin">5 Report <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Eliz.</hi>
               </note> without eviction. Pursuit in Chancery and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree thereupon, &amp;c. is no such eviction to forfet his bond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>House.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16 Eliz. Dyer 333.</note> A remaynder is limited to the house. In law the family, and the chiefe and most worthy or eldest of it, is meant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Horrible</hi> and enormous. <hi>Ietus unus non
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205088:29"/> dicitur</hi> enormous,<note place="margin">Register 125. F.n.b. 185.</note> if mayme, &amp;c. is not by it. <hi>Vide Stat. W.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 29. hath the word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Incontinenter &amp; in mediate, is as much as eodem tempore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">F.n.b. 198. Institutes 1. 369.</note> And therefore <hi>lit.</hi> 702. says if disseis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n be and a feoff made <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenter garr.</hi> created upon that is <hi>garr.</hi> by disseisin. See 6 <hi>Report</hi> 11, there its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by reasonable time. A bond is conditioned to pay plantiffe,<note place="margin">39 H 6. 10. Institute 1. 208.</note> and no time limited, the law says it shall be inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently payed, now this in legall constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is inconvenient time, and so it seems shall it be, though the party himself sayes in expresse words, hee will pay the money incontinently or presently. If no heire be at the time of discent of land, but one is born with in an houre after, this is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently as to make a discent to take away an entry and yet hee shall have it as heire. A man takes base money in payment and discovers this immediatly,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Wade.</hi> 30 Ass. 11.</note> yet he cannot refuse this, having once accepted of it. It is said where a deed is absolute, and a defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sans is delivered immediate, it is good and all one as if it were within the deed it self. Covē is to deliver cloth &amp; that immediatly upon the delivery of such cloth to pay him 10 pound,<note place="margin">18 E. 4 20. 21 E. 4. 53. <hi>per Sylyard.</hi>
               </note> the cloth is delivered at noon, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205088:29"/> other hath all the day remayning to pay the money. Immediatly sometime is by good construction, observing all incidents to such an act &amp;c. to be done. See <hi>Stat. Winchest. &amp;</hi> 27. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Report <hi>Kens</hi> Case.</note> of immediate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and action <hi>Burnel</hi> the same sence <hi>ut hic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infra quatuor Maria.</hi> is taken to be within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and doth not fetch in or intend <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 107.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inhabitant. Resiant, Commorant, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant,</hi> the genuine sense of these words are very necessary to be known, by reason they are frequently used in severall statutes, as in that of election of Burgesses to the Parliament, 1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>H.</hi> 6. and in the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Rogues,</hi> &amp;c. The originall in the Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is, <hi>properan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Commorari, apud aliquem morari,</hi> and in <hi>Buckleys Case, Plo.</hi> the word in the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <hi>Resident</hi> is in the Record and pleading of it in Latin, translated <hi>Commorans, vel Conversans,</hi> the first comes of <hi>morando,</hi> which signifies dwelling for a time, or to sojourne, and it is rather loytering then habitation. <hi>Conversans</hi> is to haunt much in a place, the originall imports to abide for a time <hi>versari in acie,</hi> and yet note the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205088:30"/> word there <hi>Resident</hi> is in the record <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morans</hi> and <hi>Conversans.</hi> The word Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>resideo,</hi> and imports as much as to light or to sit down as a bird after her flight, which may aptly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Rogues, but what time will make resident is darke yet by these expositions, but it seemes a small time will do it, in <hi>French</hi> its neerer our law sence, <hi>assis lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur idem cum assiduitas,</hi> which inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that such a one will continue in such a place for the time to come, then that he hath been long there before. The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a lease is, that the lessee shall inhabit and be resident upon the land during the terme, if these words during the terme had not been in,<note place="margin">Plo. Case. <hi>Colthirst.</hi>
               </note> it is adjudged that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding a small time there will serve to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the condition of abiding and resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. A man hath his family upon a house or no family, but occupies lands in Dale, the first is said a Resiant,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> the second an Inhabitant in our Law. Suit reall which was better <hi>royall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Iefferey.</hi>
               </note> is said due of the body of a man, because <hi>resiant</hi> there within the Hundred, and note no certain time is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in such case,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5 E. 3. 23.</note> for if he have been there three dayes he shall attend. A Charter is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205088:30"/> granted that Inhabitants shall have fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, it shall not be extended to fugitiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as this book saith, &amp;c. See <hi>Fitz-Herbert N.B.</hi> 160. A faith that a man shall not be distreined to come to a leet where he is not demurrant and conversant, if a house is in two Leets,<note place="margin">Institut. 2. 122.</note> he shall attend that where his bed is, for there hee shall be deemed most conversant. <hi>Vide Fitz. N.B. ibid.</hi> in the Writ for discharging a man to come to a Leet it is, <hi>illi qui moram non fecerint,</hi> shall not be put <hi>in juratis, &amp;c.</hi> by these reasons and authorities you shall better conceive the right sence of these kinde of words, about which such various opinions have been in Courts of Record and Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Country, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In apud ad, de, &amp;c.</hi> all these have the same sence in severall cases. Trespasse upon the statute of 6 <hi>R.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">9 E. 4. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for intrusion into the Mannor of D. <hi>apud D;</hi> it is as much as in <hi>D.</hi> and the <hi>venire facias</hi> shall be of the Town of <hi>D.</hi> yet the Indictment was for an affray <hi>apud Ecclesiam de</hi> D. and it was doubted if good, but it should be <hi>in Ecclesia,</hi> otherwise by the word <hi>apud</hi> it may be without the walls,<note place="margin">P. 36. Eliz. <hi>Capt. Knevit.</hi>
               </note> and the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is penall and the word <hi>in</hi> the Church,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205088:31"/> &amp;c. A grant of a rent charg <hi>percipiendum in Manerio de Dale,</hi> and <hi>apud Manerium</hi> and both good.<note place="margin">10 E. 4. 8. 41 E. 3. 16.</note>
               <hi>Assumpsit</hi> was to deliver goods in such a Port, and in pleading hee says,<note place="margin">Hill. 33. Eliz. <hi>Keisers</hi> case.</note>
               <hi>adtale portum,</hi> its sufficient, so where its said such a thing shall be done <hi>in festo,</hi> its as much as the first day of this feast, and shall not be deferred till the <hi>utas</hi> of it.<note place="margin">21 E. 4. 52.</note> A Writ is directed <hi>Coronatoribus in Com.</hi> It is as good as <hi>de Com.</hi>
               <note place="margin">F. n. b. 245. Vid. lib. entrys fol. 1.</note> And so abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pleaded <hi>coram Coronatoribus in Com.</hi> was holden good contrary to the opinion which <hi>ex subito</hi> hath beene taken by some.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 185.</note>Interest, any profit as Common &amp;c. is interest.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In manibus,</hi> a man devise all his tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>in manibus suis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">34 H. 67. 8.</note> and hath a reversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon an estate for life, this shall passe for the word denotes onely a thing in my subjection and power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 291.</note>
               <hi>Inde</hi> imports all things spoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as thus, <hi>Si judicium jude redditum sit, &amp;c.</hi> this is to be taken upon the whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,<note place="margin">18 Eliz. Dyer 349.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In rerum natura,</hi> hee which is dead in law, as Monk, &amp;c. so he which is out of the Country where, &amp;c. is in law said, not <hi>in rerum natura.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:205088:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ipso facto.</hi> Such a thing shall be,<note place="margin">Stat. E. 3.</note> as hee which draws a dagger, &amp;c. shall be excomenge <hi>ipso facto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 275.</note> it is doubted if it shall be without sentence or proof, but the statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, which sayes, hee that takes a second Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, &amp;c. shall be <hi>ipso facto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Report 79. 75.</note> or <hi>ipso jure privatus</hi> of the first, this is without sentence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juxta.</hi> The thing may be twenty foot remote from the place to which its said <hi>Juxta. Juxta Hull.</hi>
               <note place="margin">19 Ass. 6. 14 Ass. 8. 45 E. 3. 3.</note> This imports the place is another then <hi>Hull,</hi> and remote from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infra,</hi> is all one with <hi>Ante.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 E. 4. 63.</note> As to pay money <hi>infra Festum Nativitatis Domini,</hi> is before it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maereneum.</hi> Is this timber which hath bin part of a house, or els <hi>aptum ad domum,</hi> seems framed for such a purpose yet see <hi>ib.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Register 94.</note> 96. It is used for timber in other building. In the Dictionaries it is written <hi>merene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, &amp; est idem quod tignus,</hi> timber to build with.<note place="margin">Institute 3 97. Institute 4. 307</note> In old French <hi>Mareme</hi> Latin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneum lignum aedificatorium,,</hi> and its said a Norman word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meniall</hi> servant.<note place="margin">22 H. 6. 19.</note> Is hee which is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the house for to serve the person
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205088:32"/> of a man. So old book entries, <hi>fol,</hi> 434. of <hi>servus familiaris</hi> for meniall servant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">F. n. b. 197.</note>
               <hi>Nuper est expound le jour aute le mort de Auntestor quod nota,</hi> no long time is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17 E. 3. 16.</note>
               <hi>Pacatione.</hi> An old word used for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease, as where its said ten pound was payed <hi>in Pacatione</hi> of a hundred pound, <hi>Vide</hi> old <hi>Magna Charta</hi> 153. the word for payed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">F. n. b. 93. no. entrys 2. &amp; 109. 9 Report 56. 21 H. 7 38.</note>
               <hi>Praetextu.</hi> Is used in law for reall and good matter and of equall force with <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute cujus,</hi> or <hi>ratione cujus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prima &amp; proxima.</hi> Where it is said the jurour who hath lands neerest to twenty pound, &amp;c. Is not intended nineteen pound, but the neerest to twenty pound till it dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to forty shillings. I grant one twenty pound at the birth of my first son, and I have a son at the time of this grant hee shall not have the twenty pound till the birth of another son.<note place="margin">12 Eliz. <hi>per Harperum.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pacifice.</hi> I am bound you shall enjoy acre <hi>B.</hi>
               <note place="margin">30 H. 8. Dyer 43.</note>
               <hi>pacifico, &amp;c.</hi> albeit hee be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streined for issues lost, this is no breach of this bond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pro.</hi> The sense of this word is not to have one thing for another, but the thing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205088:32"/> it self sometimes, as if I promise to content you, <hi>pro granagio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 352.</note> this is taken that I shall pay the very granage it selfe, and not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forfeiture</hi> of all a man may,<note place="margin">Institutes 391.</note> this in law is land, goods, and body to be imprisoned, when such expression is in a statute, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Puer.</hi> Comprize female as well as <hi>male, maxime</hi> in the Dative case plurall,<note place="margin">Dyer 337.</note> 30 <hi>Ass.</hi> 47. 9 <hi>Report</hi> 72.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nos. Vos.</hi> Is <hi>stylus aulicus, sed non an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquus,</hi> and intimares, <hi>quando Princeps lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur ex curiae consilio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parens in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesin, <hi>272.</hi>
               </note> and it is not to be found in all the Scripture given to any Prince or single man, and upon like reason it seems, Bishops used it, and the Chief Justice of the Bench, <hi>coram vobis &amp; sociis,</hi> but because it was given to a Sheriffe in a Writ, thus <hi>praecipite I. S. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">29. E. 4. 44.</note> the Writ was abated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Permittere.</hi> Imports meer passive,<note place="margin">Dyer 255. 35 H. 6. Fitz barr. 261.</note> and he that is bound <hi>permittere</hi> onely need do nothing, and violence by him is to have advantage of a condition by which a breach is, will excuse as if the bond is that hee shall not permit A to inhabit in such a house, and the Obligee him put in, &amp;c. he who is so bound becomes a bankrupt, by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205088:33"/> with the house is sold, and another is put in, see whether this breaks the covenant when hee hath done an act by which in law the breach follows,<note place="margin">12 H. 8. 6. 17 E. 4. 2.</note> that the other can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dwell there. <hi>Si lex pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mittat,</hi> is if by any licence the thing can be done, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensation after then it shall be done, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">F. n. b. 41. 3 Institut. 182.</note>
               <hi>Res</hi> is a good word for goods and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and goes to corporate and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">15 E. 4. 15.</note>
               <hi>Sufficienter,</hi> a man is bound to serve in <hi>Normandy, Sufficienter,</hi> is with armour, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sure</hi> estate, a man is bound to make a sure estate by force of this word hee shall free it of dower,<note place="margin">11 H. 7. 7.</note> and yet the estate may be sure without it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Similiter pro ut, &amp;c.</hi> Where Jury findes the homage did <hi>similiter</hi> or <hi>pro ut,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 Ass. 14. 21 E. 3. 56.</note> the Defendant hath pleaded, &amp;c. that goes to time and place and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances as well as to the matter it selfe. <hi>Trin.</hi> 33. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Case, <hi>Barnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Predict.</hi> This word hath various, effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all operations in our Law, by some books it is said of as great force and efficacie, as if the words themselves to which it refers had been expressed at large. A <hi>Cessavit</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:205088:33"/> is brought and declares of a tenour by homage, Rent, &amp;c.<note place="margin">35 H. 6. 31.</note>
               <hi>Et quod de praedictis serviciis Cessavit, &amp;c.</hi> This refers onely to that service,<note place="margin">6 H. 7.</note> of which in Law properly cesser may be. <hi>Praedict</hi> is not necessary where the matter appears, though it would have made it more cleer. It will supply an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment to reconcile differences in the Record as <hi>Codred</hi> is in the beginning of the Plea, and after it is <hi>Cotreid praedict,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 H. 7. 5. 8. Report 57.</note> this helpes the varience. An Indenture is said, dated 23, <hi>December,</hi> and after it is said, <hi>per</hi> indentured <hi>praedict. datum.</hi> 23. <hi>November,</hi> the mistake is helped by the word <hi>praedict.</hi> The quality of a thing shall be well helpt by this, and inforced, as where it is mentioned that land was conveyed which he had by discent from his father, mention after,<note place="margin">Trin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Case <hi>Graye.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>de terris praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis</hi> will include all this. I surrenders copihold to the use of A. for life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to I. S. for life, the remainer to the heirs <hi>praedicti Johan.</hi> &amp; resolved it shall be the heirs of the later I. S. the purchasor,<note place="margin">Pasch. 23. <hi>Eliz</hi>
               </note> and not of himselfe, Assisse is against M. the Abbot <hi>de</hi> H. and the pone was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted <hi>Abatissam,</hi> with one more, and the opinion that it shall abate, <hi>vid.</hi> 8. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 64.<note place="margin">26 Ass. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:205088:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Paratus, paratus, respondere,</hi> within the Statute <hi>W.</hi> 2. &amp;c. he shall be said <hi>paratus</hi> who comes at the time appointed by the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2 H. 6. 2.</note> and not presently, as where a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder depends upon a remainder for life, here he is in Law said <hi>paratus,</hi> if hee come after the others which are meane and have made default.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Expositio quorundam verborum &amp; sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiarum in devises</hi> of Land. I. S. hath Lands in D. and also Rents, Court-Leets, dismes and common, and doth devise to his eldest Son divers <hi>Lands</hi> by <hi>name,</hi> and then devises to his yongest Son all his other Lands purchased free hold and copy-hold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trin. 9.</hi> Eliz. per Dyer. Walsh &amp; Gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and it was ruled because in the forepart of the will, all his Lands were devised to the eldest, the rents, tithes, leets, &amp;c. shall by those words passe to the youngest son.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 20 Iac. <hi>in</hi> b. <hi>Roy</hi> case, <hi>Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good.</hi> 22 Iac. Case <hi>Fox.</hi>
               </note> A man devises all his living to I. S. and and judge his reversion shall passe. <hi>Item,</hi> I will and intend to devise my Land to A, this is a present devise of the Land <hi>per opem curiae.</hi> A man devises the fee simple of his Land to his wife, and after her decease to his son <hi>Thomas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Eliz.</note> &amp;c. shee takes for life the remainder to the son for life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in fee to the wife, but it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205088:34"/> to make a title, her husband to be Tenant by the courtesie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et Cetera, &amp;c.</hi> This will help in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cases in Law. In an action of trespasse, <hi>quare bona, &amp;c.</hi> and declare of a bale of wood, and ruled it is not good because in the singular number,<note place="margin">Hill. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. 1. <hi>Keble.</hi>
               </note> and the writ in the plurall, but if this expression, &amp;c. had been added, it would have made it good. A Recognizance <hi>in atteint</hi> is, that if hee doe such and such things, <hi>quod tunc, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer.</note>
               <hi>per, &amp;c.</hi> by these particles, the condition of the Recognizance shall be perfected, which otherwise is not. Indictment is certified up to be <hi>capta,</hi> before such Justices <hi>ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, nec non ud diversas fellonias &amp; alia malafacta, &amp;c.</hi> &amp;c. supplies the other particulars of the commission,<note place="margin">Trin. 11. <hi>Car.</hi> b. <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
               </note> but in the the same case it was ruled, that such an Indictment certified <hi>capta coram, Justicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ad pacem,</hi> &amp;c. was not good, and doubted if it were certified to be presented <hi>per sacramentum proborum &amp; legalium hominum, &amp;c.</hi> and doth not put down the names of the Grand Jurie if it shall be good. When a record is sent up in a Writ of errour, out of an inferiour Court, shews the <hi>venire facias</hi> was awarded, <hi>ad recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noscendum,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205088:35"/> &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trin. 11. <hi>Car.</hi> Case. <hi>Hambleton in</hi> b. <hi>Roy.</hi> At the Assize <hi>Ebor.</hi> 9. <hi>Car.</hi> by <hi>Davenport</hi> Chiefe Baron.</note> and sufficient without shewing the particular issue, an &amp;c. added to a prescription made it ill, and the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe <hi>non suted, super inde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Commodities, profits, emoluments,</hi> these words in a deed added to the land or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor sold extend to such things which yield naturall profit, which an advouson doth not,<note place="margin">Trin. 18. Iac. <hi>in</hi> Comm. b. Case <hi>Loudor. Vide</hi> Chapter of <hi>Southwell.</hi>
               </note> and therefore it was resolved it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to an Advow appendant, &amp;c. to passe that without expresse words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sovereigne,</hi> In Law it is no more but the supreme of a house, or a Town, &amp;c. So an Abbot is Sovereigne of the house, and <hi>Claydon</hi> the Marshall of the house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,<note place="margin">7 E. 3. 24.</note> is termed there <hi>Sovereigne,</hi> in respect of the Gaoler and the command of such an one obeyed, shall excuse the subject or inferiour.<note place="margin">28 E. 3. 11.</note> Sovereigne of the Town shall pursue fellons, &amp;c. this is the chiefe officer be it Constable, or &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subditus</hi> is one who is subject to the ordinary jurisdiction of another,<note place="margin">Register 44.</note> as those under the Diocesan are said <hi>Subditi</hi> in the writ of consultation,<note place="margin">Britton 19. W. 2 cap. 40.</note> and the word is used also for any neighbour or inferiour, within the distresse of such a Court, but in a strict sense it refers to the Prince, so <hi>Boden, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205088:35"/> plurium principum quisque esse non potest.</hi> See <hi>Dyer</hi> 360. Its said that one of <hi>Ireland</hi> is subject of <hi>Irelaend,</hi> and not of <hi>England, quod nota:</hi> and see <hi>Calvins</hi> case, 7 <hi>Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miniments.</hi> A word used in Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances,<note place="margin">35 H. 6. 37.</note> it includes all manner of Evidences whatsoever, <hi>quasi Muniments.</hi> Old <hi>lib. Entryes</hi> 335. There it is said forger of false deed and Muniments.</p>
            <p n="49">49 <hi>Fictio juris neminem ledere debet. But ayde much it may, and this is seen in all matters where the Law works by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and division of an instant, which are fictions in law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 H. 4. 12.</note> A Constable takes one which had struck another, and then sets him at liberty, the party stricken dyes of this stroake, this is felony <hi>ab initio,</hi> but not to the prejudice of the Constable who suffered this escape. A feoffment is upon condition that he shall re-infeoff him, he grants a rent-charge, and the Grantee brings a Writ of annuity, now it is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity by relation <hi>ab initio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> 30 E. 3. 17.</note> betwixt the Grantor and Grantee, but not to defeat the condition broken, <hi>quoad</hi> the Feoffor. A fine is levied, <hi>sur render</hi> the Conusee by fiction in law hath seisin in an instant to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205088:36"/> make this renderback good, but to no other purpose to the prejudice of the conusor, for his wife shall have no Dower,<note place="margin">2 Report Case Lord <hi>Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
               </note> nor shall this land be subject to any statute, &amp;c. in which this Conusee was bound.</p>
            <p n="50">50 <hi>Fortior est obligatio partis quàm le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</hi> A man is bound by obligation to pay his rent, he ought to seek the Lessor to pay him.<note place="margin">22 H. 6. Dyer 33. 33 Eliz.</note> A man is bound in a bond to repaire a house, hee shall do this against tempest, &amp;c. and so also though it be ruinous at the time of the lease, which otherwise hee is not bound to doe. If the Lessor Covenant the Lessee shall enjoy the land demised pacifice, this extends to those, do interrupt him by wrong,<note place="margin">Dyer 328. 40 E. 3. 6.</note> whereby the word demise he is not bound.</p>
            <p n="51">51 <hi>Fortior est provisio legis quàm par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> The statute of <hi>Glocester</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits a man do no waste, it is expounded that he shall not permit wast,<note place="margin">11 Eliz. Dyer 281. Doct. &amp; Stud.</note> but if I be bound that I shall not do waste, my bond is not forfeited by waste permissive.</p>
            <p n="52">52 <hi>Fortior est dispositio legis quàm ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis.</hi> A man hath <hi>interesse termini,</hi> hee cannot this surrender, but if he take a new Lease <hi>in praesenti,</hi> this is a surrender of the old <hi>interesse termini.</hi> And upon this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205088:36"/> it is that conditions in law are so strong, as expresse conditions.<note place="margin">10 Report 67. Litt. 378.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="53">53 <hi>Fortior &amp; melior est provisio Legis quàm hominis. Parceners,</hi> by the law are to have equall portions of lands tayle and fee, now if one of them agree to take all her part of the tayled lands, she may suffer by this partition. A man is seized of three manners, of equall value, and takes a wife, and shee takes one entire mannour for her dower, which is charged with the rent shee shall hold it charged,<note place="margin">1 Institu. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> otherwise is it if she had recovered her dower, and had had a third part of each assigned to her.</p>
            <p n="54">54 <hi>Fundamento distructo cadit opus, à quare non admisit,</hi> is awarded, and afterward the originall record is removed by a writ of Errour, now the other fails though it be disadvantage to the King, who cannot now proceed for the contempt but by Green, if hee is attainted once for the contempt, the reversall of the first judgement afterward shall not aid him to avoid the contempt <hi>ut supra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. 26 E. 3. placito 25. fol. 75. 43 E. 3. 18.</note> an exigent goes out for felonie, and after a pardon of ancient date to the exigent comes, and all things by the Law required are done, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205088:37"/> chattels are saved, an excommengement is for contempt of a letter missive from the high commission, the contempt is pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">P. 23. Eliz. 6 Report 13.</note> the excommengement is also <hi>excon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequenti:</hi> Execution is sued upon a Statute, and then the Conusee makes a defeasance of the Statute, upon payment of twenty pounds, if it is paid, the execution shall be defeated,<note place="margin">20 Ass. 7.</note> as well as the Statute. <hi>vide.</hi> 43. <hi>E.</hi> 3. 18.</p>
            <p n="55">55 <hi>Generale nihil certum ponit,</hi> and is rejected in Law. A man is bound to devise all his lands in the tennor of I. S. in the Towne of D.<note place="margin">2 Report 33. Case <hi>Doding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> the obliger may say, hee hath no lands there, so a man is bound to be <hi>non suited</hi> in all actions that he hath in the Common-pleas, hee may say he hath none there: otherwise if the condition be particular, as to be nonsuted in a <hi>formdon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22 Ass 73.</note> &amp;c. Inditement is thus, that A. is a malefactor or a common thiefe, it's not good.</p>
            <p n="56">56 <hi>Generall words where they will helpe particular infirmities.</hi> As <hi>Scire facias</hi> is a gainst two severall tenants, the Sheriffe returnes <hi>Scire feci,</hi> the two <hi>modo &amp; forma pro ut breve exigit,</hi> now this which was joynt in the beginning of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205088:37"/> the return is now severall and good by the generell words <hi>modo &amp; forma, &amp;c.</hi> So where a Sheriff returns that <hi>virtute brevis</hi> he hath done such a thing,<note place="margin">2 H. 4. 13.</note> and in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of his return are many imperfections, they shall be helped all by these generall words, <hi>virtute brevis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">34 H. 6.</note> see to this purpose of these words <hi>contra formam Statuti,</hi> &amp; what imperfections will be aided by these words; so by the words <hi>secundum formam Statuti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stamford 8 1.</note> where it's said they shall have the force as if the very words of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute &amp;c. had been punctually expressed. An information is upon the Statute of buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing titles,<note place="margin">5 Report 7. Dyer 13. Eliz. 11 H. 4. 4 Case <hi>Barns</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> Michel. 7. Car. in b. le Roy.</note> and there is a mistake in the record of the day of holding the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or in the ending of it, but because the words <hi>contra formam Statuti</hi> were in the conclusion, that was aided in the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repetition of the date, or day of holding the Parliament, which was vain.</p>
            <p n="57">57 <hi>Generall words in grants where they shall be restrained by particular words in the same clause, &amp; contray.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 Report. 11 Case <hi>Carter.</hi>
               </note> A man hath a mannor in O, and other lands not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the manner, and suffer a Recoverie of all, and declare by Indenture that the use of all his lands in O, shall be to the use
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205088:38"/> of A, this shal not be of the Mannor which was particularly mentioned before. A. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges a fine of the Mannor of D. with an advouson,<note place="margin">Temp. E. 1. F. title grants <hi>per Barkley.</hi> Iudg. 13 <hi>Car.</hi> 19 H. 6. <hi>per Ascue.</hi>
               </note> and regrants the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor <hi>cum pertinentiis,</hi> the advouson shall not passe in this case. A Release to <hi>Jo. S,</hi> executor <hi>I.D.</hi> all actions now by this restri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctive word executor no impedimēt shal be, but that this release shall have an operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon all the capacities of I.S. The Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gee grants to the obligor, that he shall bee discharged of the bond, and if he is sued upon it, that hee shall plead this as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease:<note place="margin">21 H. 7. 32.</note> It is a release presently without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting Suit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="58">58 <hi>Generale discendens in particulare sive Speciale, shall be ruled by that speciall.</hi> A man grants a rent in the Mannor of D.<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Altham.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>percipiendum</hi> in 100 Acres, parcell of the same Mannor, or <hi>distringendum</hi> in 100 Acres, this rent is charged upon this 100 Acres onely,<note place="margin">Dyer 261. 9 Eli.</note> so a man releaseth all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>nec non</hi> title of dower in the Lands of W. this curbs the generall word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and ties it to the Lands of W. one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I. H, grants his Mannor S. in A. and B.<note place="margin">9 Eliz. Dyer 261.</note> where this extends also into C. nothing of the Mannor in C. shall passe.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205088:38"/> A man devises all his Land in D. and the Hamblet of I, this excludes that Lands in other Hamblets then I, shall passe though within the same Town, but note if the speciall is first put down in the deed and generall word after that the Law is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as when one is made Deputy Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard to take a surrender absolute,<note place="margin">Trin. 26. Eliz. <hi>inter Adams</hi> &amp; <hi>Fost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>&amp; ulterius facere omnia qua ad officium ejus in hac parte pertinent facienda,</hi> this enlarges his power, so that this Steward now may take a surrender conditionall, &amp;c. <hi>Vide</hi> 7 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>bene</hi> upon this rule.</p>
            <p n="59">59 <hi>Hee that needs most let him blow the cole.</hi> Upon this reason hee which is to have benefit shall do the first act. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de antea,</hi> title <hi>Act,</hi> so where request is to be made, hee who is to have a vaile shall make it, &amp;c. Detinue is brought of a deed of Release, the defendant garnish <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to whom this was made, &amp;c. and upon shewing the deed, the seale was debrused, and the Plaintiffe would have had dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ruled no,<note place="margin">29 E. 3. 31.</note> for he hath no reason to complain of the debruser, &amp;c. but hee to whom it was made, and let him blow the coal if he will.</p>
            <p n="60">60 <hi>Integra lex separat &amp; individua.</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:205088:39"/> A Charter may be allowed for part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it hath beene allowed in Eyre, and disallowed <hi>pro residuo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 H. 7. 29.</note> In debt upon a bond against two, the one acknowledgeth the deed, the other pleads in abatement, and it was awarded the Plantiffe shall recover a moyty.<note place="margin">4 E. 2. F. Tittle judgment 229.</note> So a judgment may be reversed for part as a fine, for that it was ancient Demesne was reversed for that part and stood good for the rest. And note there is a speciall Writ of Errour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move part of the Record,<note place="margin">21 E. 3. 20. Dyer 291.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="61">61 <hi>Idem taken pro Simile.</hi> So a limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ad eundem usum</hi> was taken <hi>pro tali usu.</hi> Obligation is to pay 20 shillings at <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 13. &amp; 233. Plo. Case. <hi>Browning.</hi> &amp; B.</note> and the yeer following 20 shillings at the same Feast. It is taken for the like feast. <hi>Vide</hi> 5 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 39. 40.</p>
            <p>Inconvenience, see afterward here fol. 63</p>
            <p n="62">62 <hi>Indefinitum supplet locum univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salis.</hi> A man is bound, his Feoffees shall grant a Rent, or make a feoffment, all ought to joyne in this grant.<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 10. Plo. 30.</note> A man gives <hi>bona sua</hi> in D. Its all one as if he had said, <hi>omnia bona dies, datus est partibus praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi> its all one as if he had said <hi>omnibus partibus,</hi> a Writ is directed <hi>Coronatoribus Lincoln.</hi>
               <note place="margin">E. 4. 1.</note> Its all one as if he had said <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:205088:39"/> and is not intended 2 or 3. The sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Winchester</hi> is that the hundred shall answer for the body of the offendors,<note place="margin">11 H. 7. 11. Plo. 75.</note> this is taken for all the offendors, and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of two or more will not serve the turn. See for the pleading of this Case onely foure or five of the Inhabitants are to be named in Certeine, &amp;c.<note place="margin">7 Report 7. Case <hi>Milborn.</hi>
               </note> A tenant pleads that hee is no tenant of the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and issue is joyned upon this, and its found tenant but for part, and of the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due not, this is against the pleador. See 2 <hi>R.</hi> 3. 17. 18. 6 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 15. 1 <hi>E.</hi> 5. 5. 27 <hi>E.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Mich. 10. Car. inter <hi>Lee</hi> &amp; <hi>Smathers. Exceptions.</hi>
               </note> 21. This generall rule hath severall excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and restrictions. As in case the non observance of it makes for advance of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, as a <hi>tales, quales, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 Report <hi>Denbawd</hi> case.</note> shall issue in favour of tryals, though onely one of the principall pannell did appeare. See 12 <hi>H.</hi> 4 <hi>tit:</hi> Certificate of Assiize 4. And <hi>Hobs</hi> Case, <hi>Institute</hi> 1. Upon the same reason, <hi>Vt res magis valeat. R.</hi> 2. granted to the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>W.</hi> that he and his successors shall be Collectors of Dismes granted <hi>per Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Angliae,</hi> this shall be taken for that part of the Clergie use,<note place="margin">8 Report 56. 4 Report Case of <hi>Corporns.</hi>
               </note> to grant such dismes which is the Clergy of the severall
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205088:40"/> Provinces. Prescription is that the Major shall be chosen by the Comminalty, by usage this shall be restreined to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of the Comminalty, &amp;c. A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is claymed to a Mannor, it is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment all times of the yeere, but yet its not so strong as if expressed all times of yeer.<note place="margin">Trin. 8. Car. Case <hi>Bullock.</hi>
               </note> See 30 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 2. 8 <hi>Report</hi> 91. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 44 <hi>Dyer</hi> 186. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 44. 5. 6.</p>
            <p n="59">59 <hi>Ignorantia non excusat,</hi> nor folly, but a man shall have prejudice by this much.<note place="margin">Lit. 261. Briton 62.</note> The Clerk mistakes, <hi>debet pro deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> in a Writ, Ignorance is no excuse. If a man can <hi>read</hi> and <hi>will</hi> accept the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>contents</hi> of a deed by one who declares it in a different manner, from that the truth in the deed is, <hi>This shall not ayde him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22 E. 4. 21. 2 Report Case <hi>Thorowgood.</hi>
               </note> but he is bound by it.</p>
            <p n="60">60 <hi>Inter aequales melior est conditio possidentis.</hi> Upon this reason 'tis that hee that hath an estate by wrong, shall hold against all others who have no title. If ten Mannors are conveyed to severall persons by one and the same Deed which of these happen to get the Deed may deteine it, where two severall persons have each of them power distinct to make a lease of<note place="margin">4 H. 7. 10.</note>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:205088:40"/> such Lands which of them leased it first shall stand. A Lord allows six Chaplains by his Letters Testimoniall all are presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to six severall Benefices, Pluralities the three first promoted shall stand. Two At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourneys reteyned conjunctem &amp; divisem,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Drury.</hi> 12 H. 7 9.</note> the plea of him first pleads shall stand. A Ser eant at Law brings an Action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an officer of the Kings Bench, the Common Place shall have the priviledge. See 48 <hi>E</hi> 3. 20. 21. 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>F. Assize</hi> 91. Where it is said that possession by halfe a day is not sufficient to gaine a freehold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him is a tort fesor, &amp;c. and so titles equall.</p>
            <p n="61">61 <hi>Iteration of a small offence will make it amount to a great one.</hi> As if a Gaoler permit severall negligent escapes, this will grow to be in judgment of law as much and as high a crime as a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry escape.<note place="margin">39 H. 6 33.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="62">62 <hi>Injuria propria non cadet in benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium facientis.</hi> A water runs upon the land of I.S. he stops it, by which my land is surrounded, I may enter his Close and debruse that which stops the water course.<note place="margin">8 E. 4 5.</note> Lessee for yeers puls downe his house, hee shall not have the tymber was in it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifie
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205088:41"/> it, as he shall when its blown down: the same law is if hee cut downe trees hee hath lost his speciall interest in them for shade,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Herlaken.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. A man devises land to A. till a hundred pound levied and dyes, the heir enters &amp; continues by four yeers in which by computation the money might have been levied,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Edw. Corbet.</hi>
               </note> the Devisee shall have foure yeers more against him is heire. In a <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe quod reddat,</hi> the tenant is essoigned at the <hi>Grand Cape,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 E. 428.</note> where he ought not to be this shall not turne to a discontinuance. One takes my goods by wrong and them offers to an Image, my property is gone, but if afterward these goods come again to the possession of the trespassor,<note place="margin">34 H. 6. 11.</note> I may cease them out of his hands.</p>
            <p n="63">63 <hi>In praesentia majoris cessat pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stas minoris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Institutes 4. 13.</note> A Lord of the Parliament makes a proxy, and after comes himselfe into the house of Lords, though hee says nothing, <hi>the power of the Proxy ceaseth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="64">64 <hi>Laches may prejudice but shall not ayde any man.</hi> Tenant in tayle sels a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Oakes for twenty pound, the vendee delayes the taking of them till the vendor die,<note place="margin">18 E. 4. 6.</note> he hath lost them for ever. A man brings a <hi>Formdon</hi> against two, the one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:205088:41"/> pleads, <hi>ne dona pas,</hi> which is found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, the other pleads Basterdy, if the demandant in this case do not pray his judgment against the first,<note place="margin">15 E. 4. 27.</note> till the other issue tryed against him which findes him basterd, he shall by this neglect lose the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moyty which he might have had. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of a Towne is after Corn and Hay, severed and carried away in such a field to put in Hogs, &amp;c. if one will permit his corn to continue there where he had suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient time equall to his neighbours, it is at his owne perill,<note place="margin">21 E. 4. 41. F. b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rr. 205.</note> and the other may put in <hi>their beasts,</hi> &amp;c. as if the Corn had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away. A man hath five load of hay to be taken yeerly in such a Medow, if the grantee do not take their loads of hay one yeere, it is lost <hi>for ever,</hi> and he cannot take it the next yeer, for then perhaps he should take all the hay in that place which was not reasonable,<note place="margin">27 H. 6. 10.</note> and might put the owner without hay for that yeer.</p>
            <p n="65">65 <hi>The Law avoyds Circuit of action.</hi> Upon this reason tis that where a Lessor Covenants to repair and doth not, the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see shall not be put to a suit upon the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,<note place="margin">12 H. 8. 1.</note> but shall deteine so much money out of his Rent, &amp;c. annuity is granted to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205088:42"/> A. for which <hi>he covenants</hi> and grants to be with the Grantor in every place in the County,<note place="margin">8 H <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23.</note> &amp;c. if he fail to be with him &amp;c. he may plead it in barre of the Annuity, and shall not <hi>be enforced to an action</hi> of Covenant.</p>
            <p n="66">66 <hi>The Law yields to necessity.</hi> Upon this reason it is that in a Writ averment that they are the same lands shall not be admitted,<note place="margin">6 E. 3. 41. 5 Report Case of Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 7 Report Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of discont. scilicet. 38 E. 3. 25.</note> because hee may have another Writ, but in a fine upon release, it shall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the land shall be lost, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>fine anuld.</hi> If there be not sufficient to serve of a Jury, the tenant to one of the parties shall be sworne rather then fail of the tryall. The husband discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue an acre parcell, &amp;c. With the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowson, the Alicnee presents and dyes, the heir grants the Advowson now in so much that the wife cannot recover this Advow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,<note place="margin">17 E. 3. 4 5.</note> by recovery of the acre, because of the severance of this from the acre by the grant he shall present without recovery of the advowson, as if it had bin severed at the first.<note place="margin">13 H. 8. 16. 6 E. 4. 7.</note> One cuts an Oke which fals upon the land <hi>of another,</hi> now if he could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this, he shall be excused to enter into this land and take it away. The same law
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:205088:42"/> is if beasts be driven by the high-way, and they run <hi>into</hi> the Corn, he may enter into the Corn to drive them out.<note place="margin">10 E. 4. 7.</note> In a <hi>per quae servitia</hi> against a Prioresse,<note place="margin">22 E. 4. 8.</note> for that she is incloystered shee shall atterne by her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourney.<note place="margin">43 E. 3. 8.</note> A man gives me leave to come to his house, <hi>and after discharges</hi> me again,<note place="margin">20 E. 4. 4.</note> if I continue there <hi>afterward I am a tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passor,</hi> but if the countermand was in time of a tempest, the law alters, and they may stay there untill it be over, <hi>sed nota differentiem inter necesse &amp; necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> though in <hi>Latine</hi> as <hi>Davis</hi> thinks, <hi>fol.</hi> 12. they are used promiscuously, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sentence of a <hi>Roman</hi> Senator,<note place="margin">6 Report Case <hi>Trollop.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil magis justum quàm necessarium, &amp; per Coke, Necessitas est lex temporis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">67 <hi>The Law will suffer a mischief rather then an inconvenience.</hi> This word Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence so much used in our Law hath the force of against reason <hi>scilicet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lit. 231. 138. Institutes 152.</note> artificial rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son perfected by use and experience termed <hi>summa ratio.</hi> And it is in truth when some maxime of the Law is shaken. A man pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged in some Court is sued in <hi>London,</hi> and the matter is actionable no where but there in <hi>London,</hi> yet by his priviledge the cause shall surcease there.<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 30.</note> This the reason
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205088:43"/> that a Fem covert or Infant shall not avoid <hi>their fines</hi> at full age, or after the husbands death.<note place="margin">17 E. 3. 79.</note> See title Voucher in <hi>Fitz.</hi> 81. 13 H. 4. 3. Matter upon like reason.</p>
            <p n="68">68 <hi>Lex non cogit ad impossibilia.</hi> This the reason a Corporation, as Major and Comminalty may do pety ordinary things without writing,<note place="margin">7 H. 7. 18.</note> for the <hi>infinity of</hi> them, so a Sheriffe he shall plead general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ea ratione, &amp;c.</hi> because of the impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to do otherwise in all the severall bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse of his office. The statute appoints that in <hi>redissesin,</hi> the Sheriffe shall go to the place and there shall take the inquest if now the <hi>redissesin</hi> is of a rent which issues out of divers Lands in severall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">40 Ass. 23.</note> so as he cannot be at all at once. Its sufficient to take the inquest at one of them &amp;c. because of the impossibility, &amp;c. lease upon condition he dwell upon the land de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, and he dyes at the end of ten yeers, the lease being for forty yeers, yet his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor shall enjoy this tearm,<note place="margin">Michel. 37. 38 Eliz.</note> because the condition is become impossible, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="69">69 <hi>Lex judicat de impossibiliter faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endis quasi fractis.</hi> So tenant in tayle suffers an usurpation, the issue is bound till the Church become void again, but if hee
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205088:43"/>
               <hi>had</hi> made an appropriation of it. In which case by judgment of law it wil never come void again in this case, hee may bring his action presently as if it were absolutely void.<note place="margin">46 Ass. 4. <hi>I. Neveros</hi> Case.</note> A Covenant is that lessee will leave the trees in as good plight at the end of his terme as he found them, and he cuts them down, an action lies presently for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility to performe, see 5.<note place="margin">Temps E. 1. F. Covenant 29. 7 Report 15.</note> Report Case, Sir <hi>Anthony Maine</hi> ruled upon the same reason. A man submits to arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then repeals the authority of the arbitrator, &amp;c. this makes all impossible to go on, &amp;c. and is as much in doome of law as if he had broke the arbitrement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, and his <hi>bond is</hi> forfeited, but <hi>nota.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 Report ease <hi>Viner.</hi>
               </note> The Impossibility must be absolute, for if the least possibility remayne it alters the law, as where the condition was upon a feoffment to re-infeoff the Feoffor, the Feoffee is disseised, and then acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a statute or takes a wife, &amp;c. in this case at first sight in ordinary reasen it is impossible he cannot make this feoffment, but hee must enter before by which the Land will be charged with these incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, yet because the wife may dye, or he may procure a release of the statute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205088:44"/> the time of entry &amp; refeoffment,<note place="margin">2 Report Case <hi>Iulius Wining<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no such impossibility is in the case to amount to a breach of the covenant. So in case of trees before, if the <hi>Covenant</hi> had been of a <hi>house in as good plight,</hi> &amp;c. which is out of repaire, and the tearm is welnigh ended within three days, in which a kinde of impossibility is to doe it,<note place="margin">12 E. 3. Fitz. Tit. Covet. 2.</note> yet an action doth not lye till the tearm be wholy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxed. <hi>E converso, The Law adjudges sometimes that is impossible to be done as actually performed.</hi> As where it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted that a statute the made should have continuance till the King returned <hi>à partibus transmarinis,</hi> and he dyed there, this statute is now determined, as if hee had returned.<note place="margin">18 H. 6. 12.</note> A lease is for yeers untill A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ccomplish the age of 21, hee dyes at eighteene, this lease is determined as fully, as if he had come to one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.<note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>Borraston.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="70">70 <hi>Lex accepit voluntatem &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam pro facto.</hi> No place is limited where money shall be payed in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a bond, if now the obligor happen in company with the obligee intending to tender him the money,<note place="margin">8 E. 4. 1. per <hi>Catesby.</hi>
               </note> and the other shifts away to prevent him, &amp;c. It seems in this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205088:44"/> case hee shall be excused, because hee hath done his endevour. A man gives a Jurour money to embrace him, though it happen the verdict do pass against this man, yet he shall be punished for this, &amp; the law was that if one assaile me to rob me though he did not, yet he should die for it.<note place="margin">28 H. 6. 12. Dyer 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> See <hi>Frosts Case</hi> 5 <hi>Rep.</hi> &amp; <hi>Ridgways Case</hi> 3 <hi>Rep.</hi> &amp; <hi>Plow.</hi> 22. <hi>Exception</hi> 2. <hi>Nota,</hi> this exceptiō where the Condition, <hi>Act or</hi> &amp;c. is to be done to an estranger there, to do what in him is, will not serve, but it shall be actually done, and its nothing to have done <hi>quantum in se est.</hi> As a covenant is betwixt <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> that if <hi>A.</hi> upon the tender of a hundred pound makes him an estate, then <hi>B.</hi> shall release to <hi>A. A.</hi> is all times ready to make the estate <hi>pro ut, &amp;c.</hi> but the 100 <hi>li.</hi>
               <note place="margin">23 Eliz. Dyer 371.</note> is not tender, &amp;c. <hi>B.</hi> in this case is not bound to make any release.</p>
            <p n="71">71 <hi>Lex judicat de rebus necessario faciendis quasi reipsa factis.</hi> One erects a jetty above my house, by which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity the raine will fall and run upon my house or curtelage.<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Pentuddock.</hi>
               </note> Its lawfull for mee in this case to debruse it and pull it down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any rain have falne, all one as if it had falne upon the house.</p>
            <p n="72">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:205088:45"/>72 <hi>The Law judges of that may be done as actually done.</hi> Upon this reason it is that the attornement by an Infant <hi>in pais</hi> is good,<note place="margin">9 Report Case <hi>Conie.</hi>
               </note> because he might have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by a fine to do it. The Sheriffe may sell goods without any <hi>venditioni expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> because hee might by such a <hi>Writ have been compelled</hi> to it.<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Hoe.</hi>
               </note> A Rent charge is payed twenty yeeres without acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and after a Writ of annuity is brought,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 19.</note> he shall be received to plead pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to a rent because hee might have done so if he had issued for it as rent.<note place="margin">9 Report Case Sir <hi>George Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls.</hi> 1 E. 3. 11.</note> An of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is grāted for <hi>yeers, it is void</hi> because this may come to an executor. Albeit an es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soigne is not cast, yet because it might have <hi>been done,</hi> a Jury shall not be <hi>demanded the first day.</hi> The King discharges all Intrusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. and one hath entred at this time, yet because office was not found it cannot be said Intrusion, but resolved because an office may be found when the King plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth,<note place="margin">11 Eliz. Dyer. 284.</note> it is all one in law as if it were found see 4 <hi>Report Bevils case,</hi> bin to this purpose. <hi>Nota, If a thing is in my Will to have, it is all one as in my possession,</hi> so where it is in the will and power of a prisoner to escape,<note place="margin">10 H. 6. 6. 42 E. 3. 10.</note> it is all one as if hee had escaped in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:205088:45"/> of law.<note place="margin">Fitch. Coron. 432. Exception. 14 H. 7. 2.</note> He which is acquitted upon an <hi>Appeal may</hi> this <hi>shew upon</hi> an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but if hee do not so he shall have <hi>no damages.</hi> See 4 <hi>Report Vernons</hi> Case.</p>
            <p n="73">73 <hi>The Law will iudge of some things actually done as not done, &amp; è converso.</hi> Tithes are set forth <hi>actu,</hi> but re-taken by the owner, it shall be as if they had never been set out at all, so money payed to lose a morgage, and if taken back againe, it is as if not payed at all. One hath a protection,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wades</hi> case. 5 Report.</note>
               <hi>dum moratur, &amp;c.</hi> Comes over to provide victuall, it is in law no comming to break the condition, <hi>D'Itaque non redeat,</hi> which is in it. A demandant enters into the land in question by disseisin to the use of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is no entrie.<note place="margin">Institut. 1. 18. 131. Institut. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Beasts escape out where the Lord comes to distreine as to him they are yet upon the land, and hee may take them, &amp;c. one shall be said in possession of a Ward gone six houres before out of his possession.<note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>Ratcliffe.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="74">74 <hi>The Law adjudges the same thing in esse, &amp; non esse to divers purposes.</hi> An estate in remaynder discends to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar estate,<note place="margin">9 E. 4 18. 40 E. 3. 13.</note> yet if he be an Infant hee shall not have his age, nor be in Ward by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of this remaynder, but shall be said in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:205088:46"/> of his first estate. A particular tenant grants a rent, &amp; after makes a Feofment or surrender which determines his estate,<note place="margin">1 Report Case <hi>Archer,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 E. 3. 6.</note> yet it shall be <hi>in esse</hi> to hold up the rent during the said estate. Two men are bound in an obligation of a hundred pound, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery by judgement is against one of them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Report Case <hi>Higgens.</hi> 9 E. 4. 51.</note> this dammes the bond as to him, but as to the other it is <hi>in esse.</hi> A man is bound in a statute, and is seised of a rent and before the extent he releases the rent, yet it shall be <hi>in esse,</hi> as to the Conusee. He in reversion infeoffs his Lessee for yeers to the use of I.<note place="margin">7 Report Case <hi>Lillington.</hi>
               </note> S. &amp;c. This wil work a surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by the law of the term. Yet by the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Uses it shall be <hi>in esse,</hi> and is saved. The Lord releases to his tenant being an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot, who had purchased in Mortmain the Seigniory is extinct,<note place="margin">F. n. b. 223. 14 Eliz. <hi>per opinionem</hi> Dyer.</note> yet as to the Lord Paramount it is <hi>in esse.</hi> Lessor grants a rent, and then accepts of a surrender, hee shall hold now charged with this rent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently, but if he had granted the reversion to a stranger who accepts of a surrender, hee shall hold discharged of this rent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of the tenant for life. See 9 <hi>E.</hi> 4 18. and 6 <hi>Report,</hi> Sir <hi>Anthony Mildmays</hi> Case of a rent to cease for a time, and to revive for another time. 1 <hi>Report Anne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:205088:46"/> Mayos</hi> Case, <hi>simile</hi> 5 <hi>Report Halls</hi> Case in a sentence after appeal it is <hi>in esse,</hi> as to the costs. <hi>Vide</hi> 6 <hi>Report,</hi> Lord <hi>Aburga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venies</hi> Case, 9 <hi>Report</hi> Case, <hi>Strata Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cella,</hi> where its said those things are <hi>in esse quae jure sunt.</hi> Vouchee is tenant in law, but to some purpose,<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 273.</note> not to have a release to him, so tenant by courtesie who hath granted over his estate.</p>
            <p n="75">75 <hi>Quod lex dicet factum est sic ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si, by the party himselfe.</hi> This is the reason that in all dealing with officers, trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>smen, &amp;c. they will declare that agreement, was to give them <hi>tantum, quantum meruit,</hi> &amp; though no such agreement can be prov'd, it shall passe for them as if such agreement had bin proved as in case of a Taylor, it is good evidence that he put the clothes to make without more the Law says the rest.<note place="margin">8 Report 147.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="76">76 <hi>The Law judges that is illegally done, as not done at all.</hi> One gains the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of a copy-holder by disseisin,<note place="margin">4 Report Case of Copyhold.</note> and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses this for years, this shall not destroy the custom. A man takes beasts for to agist his common,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 84.</note> this gives him no seisin because not legall to use his common so.</p>
            <p n="77">77 <hi>Leges priores per posteriores abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, &amp; contra.</hi> But then the later
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205088:47"/> Statute must be contrary to the former in substance or quality, and so if the later be negative, as <hi>assisse non capiuntur nise in proprio Com.</hi> This of more power then if it had said, <hi>ascise capiuntur in proprio com.</hi> In the first it will warrant a plea to the jurisdiction of a Court,<note place="margin">11 Report 62. 3.</note> in the latter not so, if he be impleaded in any other place then the Countie where the Land lies,<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 18. 8 E. 2. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 240.</note> But a Statute in the affirmative doth not alter a statute formerly made, or a custome. Statute 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. is, that if one who hath a benefice of the value 8 pound takes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is inducted, the first is void, this doth not alter the Law before that the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond benefice doth make void the first, though of lesse value then 8.<note place="margin">4 Report case. <hi>Digby</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> Case.</note> lib. and so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore indiction in such case. A man hath wreck by prescription, and it is inacted, <hi>Quod Rex habebit reckum maris per totum regnum:</hi> This shall not take away my prescription, <hi>aliter</hi> if the prescription had gone <hi>per totum Angliam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Report case Sir <hi>Hen. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable.</hi> 9 <hi>Car.</hi> case. <hi>Bradshavv in</hi> b. <hi>Roy.</hi>
               </note> and so as large as the Statute: As the Statute 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 4. In acts that he who sets up such trade must be apprentice before, &amp;c. alters the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom of the Realm to trade freely before without such service presedent. The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:205088:47"/> that Sheriffs shal deliver Indictments to the Justices of Peace by Indenture, yet if he do not so, they are not void.<note place="margin">4 H. 7. 11.</note> Things of necessity are not altered by generall words of an Act of Parliament.<note place="margin">10 Report 61. 5 Report 71. 7 Report 14.</note> So if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst common reason. <hi>Plo.</hi> 88. So if ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surde, <hi>Dyer</hi> 314. 27 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>tit. Annuity</hi> 41. <hi>Insiitutes</hi> 2. 198. <hi>Dyer</hi> 234. 43 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 22. It is ordained that Commissioners Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall shall punish abuses against the book of common Prayer, yet the Ordinaries ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction is not taken away. See <hi>Institutes</hi> 1. 96. to this bene. The words of a later Statute by Construction or Interpretation onely shall not abrogate a former statute,<note place="margin">4 E. 4. 3. 7 Report <hi>Ken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> case.</note> yet costs were due in a <hi>quare impedit,</hi> by the Common Law, and damages are given by statute <hi>W.</hi> 2. in this action. Costs are by construction taken away. So the statute of <hi>Marlb. cap.</hi> 6. is repealed by the affirmative statute of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. of <hi>Wills.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 Report <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> case.</note> See by mee if it is not because these are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious in reason, which equall as if in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse words.</p>
            <p n="78">78 <hi>Lex non cogit ad vana per agenda.</hi> But rather in some cases will allow the thing as done whch should be in vaine to do. Lessor Covenants upon Surrender to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:205088:48"/> make a new lease, he grants the reversion away for yeers in this case, the lessee need not make any surrender,<note place="margin">5 Report Case Sir <hi>Ant. Maine.</hi>
               </note> but shall have his action so soon as he pleaseth, because it is vain to make a surrender when the Lessor hath himself disabled, &amp;c. by his new lease. Covenant to sing Masse in such a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which falls down,<note place="margin">11 H. 7. 10.</note> the Covenantor needs not goe thither and proffer to sing Masse there, &amp;c. Goods are delivered to re-deliver upon request,<note place="margin">7 H. 6. 31.</note> the Bailer delivers them to a third person, I may take them without request, Protection is cast in a cause where two are sued as husband and wife,<note place="margin">17 E. 3. 16.</note> and shee comes and pleads she is not his wife, she shall not be admitted, and for this cause though shee desire it not, yet she shall not be estopped to say she was a Fem sole. The Lord covenants upon surrender of the old Copy to make a new one, now because the making of a new Copy is a sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render in law of the old,<note place="margin">Michael. 11. <hi>Car. Rot.</hi> 310. B. <hi>Roy.</hi>
               </note> therefore an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of covenant lyes against the Lord if he doe it not without such surrender which was idle to make. Exception is to this rule. In case the thing may be of some va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity, and is not absolutely vain, though <hi>revera</hi> it is idle. As where I.S. is bound to present I. D. to the Church of Sale
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205088:48"/> when this shall next be void. In this case though the obligee is married, &amp;c. by which hee was disabled, &amp;c. yet hee must be presented if hee will save his bond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he may have a dispensation from the Ordinary.<note place="margin">20 Ass. 1. <hi>Perkins</hi> 157.</note> So where <hi>Vtlary</hi> in felony is to be reversed, a <hi>Scire facias</hi> shall go to the Lords, &amp;c. though he hath no land, &amp;c. untill the Court shall be apprised thereof by return of the Sheriffe,<note place="margin">7 H. 7. 5.</note> or the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney. See 39 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 22. 23. 21. <hi>E.</hi> 4. 40. 47.</p>
            <p n="79">79 <hi>Lex non haeret in syllabis vel literis modo de substantia constat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16 E. 4. 3. 39 H. 6. 43. ib. fol. 39.</note> A Writ is that such a one <hi>fuit non compos mentis,</hi> and the traverse to this was that <hi>absque hoc quod fuit extra sanam memoriam &amp; bene.</hi> So <hi>Iturus</hi> is put for <hi>profecturus,</hi> its well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. <hi>Avowrie</hi> is because a 100 pound <hi>pro redditu praedicto,</hi> was behind, and suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient though <hi>de reditu</hi> had beene more apt. The King brings an action of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and the Writ is,<note place="margin">25 E. 3. placi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o 21.</note>
               <hi>quod reddat Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potum nostrum.</hi> Where it should be <hi>suum,</hi> and yet holden good. The Mesne grants to the Tenant to acquit him against the Lord Paramount and his heires, hee shall acquit him against his wife, &amp;c.<note place="margin">1 Institu. 241. 14 H. 4. 18.</note> A bond is to resigne to the obligee, yet it shall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:205088:49"/> bee done to the Ordinary.</p>
            <p>So <hi>The Law is somtimes stricter then the words of the party in force.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Report case <hi>Frances.</hi>
               </note> The Lessor grants if the Lessee is disturbed, he shall have fee, every disturbance wil not do it, but shal be of the lessor himself to raise this Contingent fee. A remaynder is limited to children unprofered, this shall be such as are not preferred when this remaynder happens to fall, and not unpreferred at the time of his death, who made such will for if they be preferred afterward before the remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fall it is sufficient.<note place="margin">Ibid. case <hi>Alice Fulhurst.</hi>
               </note> A statute is that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of Gaol-delivery, or Oyre and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner or any two of them shall heare and determine, &amp;c. in this case though there be but one, hee shall execute this well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.<note place="margin">Institutes 3. 130.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="81">81 <hi>Lex non est curiosa.</hi> Winks at small faults, one brought a Writ of Conspiracy for indicting of him the fourth of <hi>August,</hi> the Defendant makes a Justification for executing the office of Justice of Peace, without that he was guilty of any conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy before the said day or after and ruled good though he doth not precisely answer the very day laid.<note place="margin">12 E. 4. 18.</note> An action <hi>quare fossa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros fregit,</hi> where it is more proper to say,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:205088:49"/>
               <hi>prosternavit,</hi> yet ruled good.<note place="margin">12 Ass. 28. Plo. 192. case <hi>Adams.</hi>
               </note> A lease is made to B. and his wife, she survives and marries W. and in pleading of a new lease, It is said to begin after the end of the lease made to W. and yet held good.<note place="margin">Hill. 11. <hi>Car.</hi> case <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> 10 E. 3. <hi>F.</hi> Release 38.</note> Assumpsit was in consideration hee should surcease <hi>quaerelam pro</hi> 7 <hi>li.</hi> and it was an action upon the case which is not for a summe certain, but dammages seven pounds, yet holden good by the better opinion. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt is brought of a resceet <hi>per autor Mains,</hi> and a release pleaded of accompt by himself, and admitted good.<note place="margin">27 Ass. 5.</note>
               <hi>Champerty quod cepit mainutenere &amp; adhuc mainute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret;</hi> in a plea which is adjudged and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and <hi>adjudge</hi> good, yet it cannot be good in the present tense, <hi>Misrecitall</hi> is of the very ancestor, as a man says himself heir to the grandfather;<note place="margin">10 Eliz. Dyer 359. 360.</note> whereby the office it was to the father, yet good. A conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to lease as, A. thinks meet and in the record its pleaded <hi>non demizavit, nec appunctuavit</hi> and good; so not curious in the translation of the English into Latine.<note place="margin">5 Report 23.</note> In case of waste <hi>de hominibus,</hi> it is proper to say <hi>in exilio hominum,</hi> but if he said <hi>fecit vastum in hominibus,</hi> it is good enough. <hi>Vient lassie supra titulo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 H. 6. 11.</note> where it appeares
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:205088:50"/> before there were many titles, and yet good, <hi>Vide</hi> 38 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 20. 27 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Ultimo. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity circa horam dici.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 326.</note> Upon this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it is that <hi>fuit</hi> is oftentimes admitted for <hi>est, pertinent</hi> for usually occupied, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient office <hi>for petie continuance</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ante verbo Idem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 Report of B. <hi>Salisbury.</hi> 10 H. 7. 27. Plo. Hill. &amp; G. Case. 9 Report 52.</note> The obligee says to the Obligor, that he himself is discharged of all bonds, this is a good release being by deed, albeit it is improperly spoken.</p>
            <p n="82">82 <hi>De minimis non curat lex.</hi> A quill full of gold or silver oare shall not cause a copper or tin myne to be to the King as a myne royall.<note place="margin">Plo. 339.</note>
               <hi>Nota,</hi> Amercement is so small a thing a man shall not be restored to it, though there be a lawfull cause to to discharge it,<note place="margin">8 E. 4. 25.</note> so where a judgment is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versed, I shall not have restitution of an amercement given against mee, cutting of trees to the value of two pence is no waste.<note place="margin">F.n.b. 60. Plo. 329.</note> See <hi>Plo.</hi> 85. where it is said that a lease for an houre of a pretensed title or right is within the statute of 32 of <hi>H.</hi> 8 of buying tirles.</p>
            <p n="83">83 <hi>Law presumes more then the partie himselfe sayes.</hi> An Ordnary returns for cause of divorce that the parties are <hi>infra annos nubiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Report Case <hi>Kens.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Law sayes there
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205088:50"/> are more causes. A man is bound to infesse me of Lands worth ten pounds by year, &amp;c. pleads that he infeoft me of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of D. and S. which are worth ten pounds by year,<note place="margin">14 H. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it is no good reply to say he infeoft me of the Mannor of D. onely, without saying what it's worth, for it may be worth ten pound <hi>per annum</hi> of it selfe, though hee said both were but of that value: a man covenāts with I.S. that if he do not warrant the Land to him he will save him harmelesse upon suit, he enters into the Warrantie,<note place="margin">46 E. 3. 28.</note> though this satisfies the words of the Covenant, yet not the Law, for hee shall render to him in value, otherwise, he doth not performe the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p n="84">84 <hi>Lex intendit optima perfecta &amp; effectualia &amp; legalia.</hi> A man hath esto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in a wood, and he comes with force and armes, and cuts down trees,<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 7.</note> it shall be intended for his estovers, and not other wise, for where the thing stands indifferent right or wrong, the Law always judges the best: Where it's said such a thing to be done, it shall be intended <hi>prima facie</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done, as where one pleads that hee was possessed of a Hawk,<note place="margin">Dyer 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>ut de bonis proprio
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:205088:51"/> is,</hi> it was intended lawfully, where speech is of time indefinitely, it shall bee inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the present time.<note place="margin">42 Ass. 21. 6 Report Case <hi>Colliers.</hi> 10 Report 3 Report Case <hi>Fines.</hi> Plo. Case. <hi>Willowby.</hi> 11 Report Case <hi>Metcalf.</hi> 5 H. 7. 25.</note> A man is bound to apprar, it shall be in person. Where it's agreed a fine shall be levied, it shall be a fine upon the stat. of 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. A challenge is, because such a one was sistet to the Sheriff, ir shall be intended of the whole bloud. Where speech is of a judgement to bee given, it shall bee intended finall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A Lease is made to an Abbot for life, it shall be intended his naturall life, and if he be deposed,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 18. 35 H. 6. 54.</note> his successor shall have it during his life. Hee that claimes conuses of plea in his own case, the Law supposes he will doe right and be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.<note place="margin">Institutes 3. 214. 185. 5 Report 112. Plo. 220. 20 H. 6. 23.</note> A Statute which speaks of attein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of treason, intends legall attendors, and not erronious: so of an office, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of an assigne intend it a complete assigne, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="85">85 <hi>Lex omnia suaviter, &amp; ad melius disponit.</hi> A Writ is, <hi>reperare &amp; munda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fossatum &amp; ripariam.</hi> The Law will apply the most apt Substantive to his verbe,<note place="margin">46 E. 3. 38.</note>
               <hi>mundare</hi> to <hi>fossatum, reparare</hi> to the bankes, &amp;c. The <hi>solvendum</hi> was to the Obligor,<note place="margin">4 E. 4. 29.</note> the Law will alter it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205088:51"/> and make it to the Obligee, and so the Plaintiffe shall declare <hi>quod nota.</hi> A Writ of entre is upon the Statute of <hi>W.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">4 E. 4. 29.</note>
               <hi>quare ingressi sunt manerium de</hi> A. <hi>&amp;</hi> B. <hi>ac u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num messuagium,</hi> ten Acres of pasture, ten of medow, in the Town of P. &amp;c. and the case was that no such Town of P. is without addition, and so in strictnesse of Law the writ was to be abated, but now to save this the Town shall be referred to messuage and lands,<note place="margin">19 E. 4. 6.</note> and not to the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor which is good without any vill layed and the writ abated, as to those and stood good as to the Mannor by this fair and handsome disposition of things. Trespasse <hi>quare clausum</hi> of husband and wife, <hi>&amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na sua cepit,</hi> and declare of a taking before marriage,<note place="margin">7 H. 7. 2. 3.</note> and the Court said that this word <hi>sua</hi> being indifferent shall refer unto the wife onely, and so good by this orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that word, Trespasse <hi>contra pacem, R.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Regis nunc</hi> where part of it was in the one Kings reign, and part in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so declared, though the Writ is joynt <hi>contra pacem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 H. 4. 15. 37 H. 6. 2. 17.</note> the trespasse shall be so marshalled to make it good. <hi>Cessavit</hi> is of divers services, it shall be referred to such services onely in which the Law says
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:205088:52"/> a cessor may be and not to others, as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, &amp;c. <hi>In a Quo warranto prescripton,</hi> is alleaged for wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and possession of the Abbot, and the Act of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. of <hi>Reviver pro catellis follonum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Report Case <hi>Abbot Strata Mercella.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>&amp; eo waranto cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat omnia ut spectant</hi> to the Mannor and good, though <hi>catalla felonum</hi> cannot in Law be spectant to a Mannor, the Law will refer this word to other things before mentioned, which may be appertenent to a Mannour, or else make that word as void, rather then overthrow all. A man grants a rent <hi>de molendino suo percipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum de se &amp; haeredibus.</hi> The Law will marshall it thus that he grants the rent for him and his heires,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 66.</note>
               <hi>percipiendum,</hi> out of the Mill, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="86">86 <hi>Lex semper dabit remedium.</hi> A man leases land excepting the trees, hee shall by law have free egresse and regresse for to come and cut them down and carry them away.<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 1. 11 Report <hi>Lifords</hi> Case. 1 Report 98.</note> Where the statute gives a third part to him who discovers an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any statute, he shall have an action for this,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 4.</note> albeit it is not expresly given,</p>
            <p n="87">87 <hi>Lex judicat de insufficienter vel vane factis quasi omnino infectis.</hi> A Baily of a Franchise makes an insufficient return, it
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205088:52"/> is as if <hi>nullum dedit responsum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Institutes 2. 453. 5 H. 7. 28. 3 H. 7. 11. Plo. 19.</note> and a <hi>non omittas</hi> shall be awarded, and hee shall lose the franchise, <hi>hac vice,</hi> no office and an insufficient office all one. Sommons by one Sommonour, is as if none at all had bin:<note place="margin">Stamford 51. 50 E. 3. 17. 14 H. 8. 21. 26 E. 3. 69.</note> if a rent is granted but no atornment it is as no grant. Presentment to a Church ful before, though the presentee hath accepted of it, will not determine his annuity gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him till he should be presented.<note place="margin">Fitz Coron. 444.</note> A man is acquitted upon an insufficient Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or appeal, no damages shall be given, but is as if no acquitall had been.<note place="margin">27 Ass. 25. 8 Report Case <hi>Vinior.</hi>
               </note> The power of an arbitratour is repealed, but it is imperfect because notice was not, &amp;c. he may well plead, <hi>non revocavit.</hi> An ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal is brought upon an Indictment, but because the Indictment was insufficient it shal be taken as no Indictment had bin,<note place="margin">20 E. 4. 6. 10 H. 7. 24. 26 E. 3. 4.</note> &amp; abettors shall be enquired off. <hi>The same law is where a thing is done in part onely, as where debt is payed in part. Vide</hi> 5 <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, Case Lord Mountjoy. Institutes</hi> 1. 25 4 <hi>Report, Case Vernon.</hi> The same law is where a thing is <hi>vane factum,</hi> and so accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of a vaine thing is as none, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of the Peace is direct to two, which are dead,<note place="margin">P. Brook <hi>50<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> this will not repeale a former
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:205088:53"/> Commission. One makes an Indenture o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Writing under seale of receit of goods,<note place="margin">27 H. 8. 22. 49 E. 3. 3.</note> this works nothing more then if no deed at all had been, but a deed of receit of money shall conclude for to say <hi>unques son Receiver.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 E. 3. 32.</note> A <hi>Metropolitan</hi> doth commit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration where there were not any <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na not abilia, &amp;c.</hi> it is as none. An Infant grants a rent,<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 21. 24 H. 8. 2.</note> or no attournment is to such grant by the tenant in case of a man of full age these may plead ne <hi>grant a pass</hi> for the insufficiency of them.</p>
            <p n="88">88 <hi>The law will accept of that is good in grants or pleadings, and reject the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 E. 4. 56.</note> I infeoffe <hi>A.</hi> and grant to <hi>B.</hi> by the same deed that I shall warrant for me and my heires to <hi>A.</hi> that is a good warranty to <hi>A.</hi> and the words to <hi>B.</hi> are void, A man grants 20 load of buche to <hi>Io. Rosset</hi> and his heires, <hi>quorum</hi> 16 <hi>praedictus Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes habuit ex dono Richardi patris mei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 Ass. 14.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> albeit <hi>Io.</hi> never had any such grant before of the Father, &amp;c. the grant is good for the whole loads. A Bishop cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies bastardy,<note place="margin">4 Institute 48.</note> and endorses the reason be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Father was absent seven yeeres. The Law will reiect this later part, and restrein the former of Basterdy A Writ<note place="margin">11 Ass. 24.</note>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:205088:53"/> goes to chuse a Burgesse of Parliament, no Lawyer, the Law rejects this last.</p>
            <p n="89">89 <hi>The Law is more agile in working then the act of the party.</hi> This the reason that where lands are devised to him, that is heir at law, he shall be in by discent, and not by the will. Tenant by the curtesie is the reversion to the wife of I.S. he infeoffs the huband and wife,<note place="margin">11 Ass. 24.</note> it shall be a surrender to her, and the <hi>husband and takes nothing.</hi> See 20 <hi>Ass.</hi> 16. 35 <hi>Ass.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="90">90 <hi>The Law where it enjoyns an Act to be done will provide he shall not be hurt, à latere that doth it.</hi> And for this, where I have annuity and many arrears are, and then it's due at <hi>Mich. subsequent,</hi> and I do receive it then and give an acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, now because he is not bound to pay it me without acquittance, therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I could not receive it without this acquittance,<note place="margin">3 Report 65.</note> it shall not bar me of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears due before, <hi>aliter,</hi> in case of rent.</p>
            <p n="91">91 <hi>The Law regards the principall thing, and not additionals.</hi> As in case of a Mill, which is in demand, it's no matter whether Corn-mill, Paper-mill,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Luttrell.</hi>
               </note> or Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-mill. A. grants me the yearly annuity of a robe with furs, when I come to sue
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:205088:54"/> for this,<note place="margin">17 E. 3. 73.</note> I shall onely mention a grant of such a robe yearly, without mentioning furs.</p>
            <p n="92">92 <hi>The Law adjudges the deniall to doe a thing as the not doing it or breach of Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> A. delivers B. ten pounds for certain woad, if hee like it when hee sees it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 E. 4. 15.</note> and if hee like it not, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliver the money, if when he sees them he deny to have them, the bargain is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and no agreement after will make it good.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5 E. 4. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4 H. 8. 23.</note> A man is bound to doe an act when I request him, and he sayes hee will not doe it, hee hath forfeited his bond.</p>
            <p n="93">93 <hi>The Law is not satisfied with sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows but substances.</hi> It is not sufficient for a labourer to be retained in service, if he doe not actually serve.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 H 6. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 Eliz. Dyer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>56.</note> If one accept of a thing in satisfaction of another which is of no value it is not good. See <hi>Wades Case,</hi> 5 <hi>Report, to this purpose:</hi> 46 <hi>E.</hi> 3, 26 <hi>&amp;</hi> 33. 46 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 28 <hi>Case of Warranty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="94">94 <hi>The Law hath an eye to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Acts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plo. 260.</note> A Lunatike smites himselfe with a <hi>knife,</hi> and after becomes of sane memory, and dies, hee shall not forfeit his goods.<note place="margin">13 H. 7. 14.</note> I have an intent to strike I. S.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:205088:54"/> and it happeneth upon I. N. it is a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem, &amp;c. If presentment be in time of war, all done upon that is void.<note place="margin">6 E. 3. 41. 2 Report Case <hi>Bingham.</hi>
               </note> A servant kills his Master after he is departed upon malice conceived before in time of his service, this is pettie treason.<note place="margin">Fitz Coron. 210. 16 Ass. 3.</note> A man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates parcell of a gorse, by which all is broken in time shortly after hee shall bee charged of repairs of all and shall answer damages of all.</p>
            <p n="95">95 <hi>Loquendum ut nulgus.</hi> A. sels to me ten Acres of corne,<note place="margin">17 E. 4. 1. Plo. 29.</note> it is good onely for the corne, and upon this reason shall the construction of a deed be made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul the sense of the Law.</p>
            <p n="96">96 <hi>A lawfull act by matter, ex post facto, may become unlawfull.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16 H. 7. 14. 2 E. 4. 5. 22 E. 4 47. 13 E. 4. 9. 9. 9 H. 6. 29. 11 Report 11.</note> So whore a distresse is taken well, and killed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, so if it be sold, or hee claime profit in it. A man hath a house boot, and takes this every yeere, as he may doe though he use it not of 20 years after, for it is not good to build with before it be seasoned,<note place="margin">10 E. 4. 3.</note> if now he sell it or convert it to other uses, he is a trespasser. The same law is where an act is well done by authority of the partie,<note place="margin">M. 2 H. 8. <hi>Kell.</hi>
               </note> as I deliver a chest to one who breaks it, trespasse lies, he which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:205088:55"/> payeth his rent, and afterwards is denyed to have his goods delivered,<note place="margin">22 H. 7. <hi>Kell.</hi>
               </note> hee shall have an action of trespasse or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>E.</hi> 4. 17. 16 H. 7. 14. 11 H. 4. 58.</note> So in many cases by not doing some <hi>act subsequent,</hi> a former lawfull act shall become unlawfull, as where the Sheriffe makes an arrest, and returns not the <hi>Capias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>E.</hi> 4. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 H. 7. 23.</note> or if it be done by his Bailiff or servant, and no return, it will make the Sheriffe himselfe a trespasser though not the servant who is to be quit in such a case, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>E.</hi> 4. 4. 8 H. 6. 8.</note> An Executour commands the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of goods of the testator,, and after refuseth to prove the Will, he is a trespas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 H. 7. 23.</note> but not the servant, the Sheriff seises the goods of one out-lawed and after doth not charge himselfe in his account with them when the partie is pardoned or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary reversed, hee shall have an action of trespasse against the Sheriffe, The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary refuseth a Clarke for lawfull cause, as insufficiencie, if he examine him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and accept him, he makes himself punishable for the disturbance before. A Writ well purchased by matter subsequent as death of one of the demandants may become in apt or false,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 Report 134</note> and so abate. A man is arrested by command of the Justices
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:205088:55"/> in <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall, this is justifiable, the <hi>same Term,</hi> without record therof, but in another terme not,<note place="margin">10 H. 7. 17.</note> unlesse a Record bee of it, and by negligence herein he may be punished by false imprisonment.</p>
            <p n="97">97 <hi>Malitia mutat l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gem. A</hi> is bound to inclose against a close of mine called White Acre, if my beasts go into his for lack of his fence, it is excusable, but if my Close be sown with Corn, &amp;c. by which hee was secure and made not his fence, if I should now put beasts into my Close so sowne of purpose they may escape, &amp;c.<note place="margin">39 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 3.</note> there he is not to be excused. So an Infant in case of Murder shall be tryed for his life where malice and subtlety appears,<note place="margin">3 H. 7.</note>
               <hi>aliter non.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="98">98 <hi>Melior dabit nomen rei.</hi> Husband and wife joynt executors,<note place="margin">22 H. 6. 30.</note> the Writ shall be <hi>executoribus</hi> and not <hi>executrici,</hi> some convenient proportion of gold or silver oare shall <hi>give the name</hi> to a myne to be a myne Royall,<note place="margin">Plo. 323.</note> though a great bulk of Tin is. Lether of a sho shal give the ownership of the threed of I. S.<note place="margin">5 H. 5. 16.</note> used in the making to the owner of the leather, and so he shall have all the property.</p>
            <p n="99">99 <hi>Magis dignum trahit ad se minus.</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:205088:56"/> Charters are put in a box,<note place="margin">14 H. 4. 30. 10 E. 4. 14. 40 H. 6. 18.</note> this alters the nature of the box from a chattel, and now it shall goe to the heir, and it is no felony to steale this box, nor lies a <hi>Capias</hi> of it in detinue.<note place="margin">42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 13. 29 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 19.</note> See 30. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Fitz. tit. bar. simile</hi> Where the realtie shall prevail, issue is, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> such an one was instituted and inducted,<note place="margin">43 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 13. 22 H. 6. 27.</note> the tryall in this case shall be by jury by reason of the Induction. A man reteins a servant to serve in all occupations,<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 14.</note> now because wager of law doth not lye in case of service in husbandry if debt is brought for wages,<note place="margin">18. H. 6. 35. 20 H. 6. 32.</note> hee shall wage law in none of them. An action against two, and the one ought to have priviledge of Chancery, he shall be outed of this and all shall be at the Common Law. A Lease is of a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; a bed rendring rent,<note place="margin">21 E. 4. 34. 46 E. 3. 8.</note> in debt for this rent, the defendant shall not wage his law for the bed, because the other is <hi>Magis dignum,</hi> and shall rule the other. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change is of Greene Mede for blacke acre, and twenty shillings rent in this case all shall be by deed, not that the land is lesse worthy, but because if it be not by deed it will be void for the rent, and so o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the exchange for all, See 11 <hi>Report Case Auditor Curle</hi> 46 <hi>E:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> 50.</note> 3. 8.</p>
            <p n="100">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:205088:56"/>100 <hi>Magis continet in se minus.</hi> Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number comprises the singular, &amp;c. If a man is bound to pay twenty pound and tender is of that and more it is good. Commons grant tonage and poundage for four yeers the Lords agree for two yeeres, they need not send backe this bill to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouse of Commons for their assent.<note place="margin">33 H. 6. 17.</note> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome was to grant Copyhold estate <hi>in feodo,</hi> this implyes that hee may grant for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife, &amp;c. <hi>Quare impedit,</hi> in the Register is,<note place="margin">4 Report Case Coppyhold. 10 Report 136.</note>
               <hi>praesentare ad Ecclesiam,</hi> by this hee may have <hi>pro tertia parte, &amp;c. Procedendo,</hi> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose an Assise before <hi>Stoufe</hi> &amp; <hi>Burton,</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and it was also before <hi>Shard,</hi> &amp; good because three implyes two. An a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of battery is brought &amp; the evidence for this proves it a <hi>Maihem &amp; bene</hi> because it is battry &amp; more.<note place="margin">31 Ass. 1.</note> A man is restored to all lands forfeited by his father in fee or tayle, that he hath but for life, shall be restored.<note place="margin">39 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 20. Plo. 86. 7. 7 H. 7. 13.</note> Exception. Traverse is of a feofmēt by two pleaded, and its found that the Feoffment was by three, It is against him who pleads this. <hi>Vide</hi> 9 <hi>Report</hi> 52.3.<note place="margin">14 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 1. 6 Report Case <hi>Fitzwilliams.</hi>
               </note> Power is given to make leases for yeeres, &amp;c. Yet he may make one lease onely.</p>
            <p n="101">101 <hi>Modus &amp; Conventio vincant
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:205088:57"/> legem &amp; Regem &amp; contra.</hi> This rule is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed <hi>in Magna Charta. Conventio le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi deroget,</hi>
               <note place="margin">W. 2. 50.</note> Barreth the Law as the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator hath it. The Law says <hi>Dyer</hi> will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> determine contrary to the agreement o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the parties,<note place="margin">Dyer 181. 312.</note> and for this cause where a gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in tayle is, the law says its to the use of the Donee, yet by the deed it may be to the use of the Donor. A rent is granted to one and his assignees <hi>pro consilio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Report <hi>Maunds</hi> Case.</note> this may now be assigned which without this agreement in the deed could not. And note by this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement a man may tye himself to things out of his power to do, and which, <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">40 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 6. &amp; 2. Dyer 33.</note> are impossible &amp; which the law frees a man of by common right. As where a man tyes himself to repaire, banks which are subverted by a floud, yet hee is bound to repair them. So to repair a house blowne downe by tempest, which was a good plea in an action of waste. So where the Lessee tyes himselfe to leave a house in so good plight as hee found it, if it was feeble at the time of leasing and falls down, he shall make a new one, which by law he was excused of.<note place="margin">8 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 9.</note> Sheep are letten, &amp; the lessee covenants to render the polls at the end of the terme, he shall do so though
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:205088:57"/> they dye of the Murrain, &amp;c. The banks may be repaired, the house built, new sheepe bought,<note place="margin">40 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 2.</note> for to render the poles is the number not the very same. A man undertakes by covenant to get the good will of such a woman, or that a beggar shall pay 1000 pounds that such a field of corne shall grow, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> A. 146.</note> that such a woman shall have a childe, that I. S. shall make a feoffment of his Land, the Law says these are possible, but if the Law say it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, I am not bound by my Covenant, as where it is to leave a Wood in as good plight at the end of the Term &amp; its blown down, so to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> on a day:<note place="margin">Vide Dyer 33.</note> So of the case where it's covenanted, such a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow shall not be surrounded, or that such a house shall not bee burnt, and it is by lightning, &amp;c. it seems in neither he shall be bound because impossible: So also where the matter agreed is against the Law.<note place="margin">Poulton de Pace Regni, &amp;c. 11. See <hi>Heyburns</hi> Case. 14 E. 2. cited in the Case of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money. 5 Report 64.</note> A man agrees with I. S. that if hee pay him not 20 pounds, he shall imprison him, &amp;c. though he payes not the money at the time agreed, hee cannot imprison him. So a man agrees to a By-law made to imprison for the penalties, &amp;c. this shall not binde him, Justices of assise held plea of Land in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:205088:58"/> another Countie, then their warrant was, and the parties did agree to it, this shall not binde them,<note place="margin">8 Ass: 16.</note> but if either is put out by execution, <hi>inde, &amp;c.</hi> hee shall have an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sise.<note place="margin">Institute 1. 146.</note> If parties agree the distresse shall be irreplegiable, this is void, as against Law. The Defendant would render the dower at the day in the writ,<note place="margin">18 E. 3. 39.</note> but did forbeare by consent of the Plaintiffe, yet hee shall bee amerced. The King reserves a rent, and a condition to reenter, if it is demanded and not paid,<note place="margin">7 <hi>E</hi> 6. Dyer 87</note> but because the law is, the King need not make any demand, he shall enter without demand, this speciall agreement notwithstanding. So in case of incidents which are inseparable by Law, no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of parties will separate them,<note place="margin">5 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 8. Case <hi>Garter.</hi>
               </note> as where an Annuity is granted for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of an Office, and there is a proviso, if the Office bee taken away, yet the annuity shall continue, if the office is taken away, it shall cease. See 44 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 36. <hi>bene,</hi> to this purpose.<note place="margin">F. n. b. 264. D.</note>
               <hi>Ligat Regem in casu.</hi> The King makes liverie to his Ward, without excepting that the dower shall be assigned to the wife by him: the King is bound by this and she shal liue the heire in a Writ of dower. The Kings Tenant alieneth part
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:205088:58"/> of the Land holden, the King may distrein this alienee for the whole rent, and is not bound by the Statute <hi>Quia emptores terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">F. n. b. 235.</note> but if the alience make a fine with the King for this alienation, then hee shall onely pay his part of the rent.</p>
            <p n="102">102 <hi>Nihil dat, quod non habet.</hi> A Tenant for years cannot give seisin of rent issuing out of free hold to maintaine an assise, because himselfe hath not free-hold.<note place="margin">6 Report Case <hi>Brediman.</hi>
               </note> Conusee by fine of a Reversion bargain, this to I. S. hee cannot distraine, because his barganer could not.<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Knotford</hi> in Case <hi>Malory.</hi> Plo. 281.</note> Reversion is granted by fine, the grantee disseise the tenant and infeoff, the lessee enters, this is no attornment here, because hee shall not be in better plight then his feoffor: An administrator cannot have greater proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in goods of the Intestate, then the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie</hi> himselfe had before, yet by words in the Statute he hath. Issue in tayl being bound by the Statute to pay debts of the Kings when the estate by alienation shall be disposed unto anothet, hee shall bee in better case,<note place="margin">7 Report Case</note> and is not bound to pay these debts, for the Statute extends not to him, &amp; so is at the cōmon law, in which case by death of tenant in tayl the issue &amp; al under
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:205088:59"/> him were discharged, so where a custome inlarges the power of a Grantee. A Lessee of a Mannor is, excepting the trees, in which Mannor are Copyholds now hee himself cannot cut trees they are excepted,<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Swain.</hi>
               </note> but if he grants a Copyhold, the granted may cut trees by the custome which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strips that Lease. Upon the same reason it is that <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the person of a Grantee will adde power,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Knight.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. which the Grantor himselfe had not, as where a reversion in part is granted to the King he may <hi>enter for condition</hi> broken in this part,<note place="margin">5 Reporr Case <hi>Mallory.</hi>
               </note> which the Grantor could not do. The like law is when a man comes in by act in law, as by Escheat, &amp;c. hee may distreine though he who dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heire could not do so.<note place="margin">19 E. 4. 6.</note> A subject of the King of <hi>England,</hi> enters bond to a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> enemy to the King,<note place="margin">22 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 23.</note> it is void to the party, yet the King shall have it and recover the debt which the obligee himself could not do. The King grants Conusants of plea in the Mannor of D.<note place="margin">7 H. 4. 1. Fitzh. Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition. 10.</note> then a new action is given by Statute which was not before, the Grantee shall hold plea of this though it was not in the Grantor. <hi>Vide</hi> 4 <hi>Report</hi> 23.</p>
            <p n="103">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:205088:59"/>103 <hi>Nemo bis punietur pro uno deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto.</hi> An Ecclesiasticall person recovers damages in trespasse,<note place="margin">7 H. 41. Fitzh. prob. ibid. 10.</note> hee shall not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished again in the Ecclesiasticall Court, but this seems <hi>quo ad partem ipsam,</hi> but by suit <hi>ex officio</hi> he may, so the partie against whom damages are recovered in trespass may bee fined at the Kings suit upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, &amp;c. and so in many cases, where the wrong trenches upon severall persons, as a servant beaten, so in case Baylor and Baylee they shall have severall actions. So Dissessor and Dissessee renant for life,<note place="margin">10 H. 7. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15 E. 4. 25.</note> and he in the remaynder shall punish the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of false deeds. See 40 <hi>E.</hi> 3.11.43. <hi>Ass.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="104">104 <hi>Negativum nihil implicat, in a precipe quod reddat.</hi> The tenant wages his law of non-sommons,<note place="margin">22 H. 6. 41. 33 H. 6. 25.</note> this doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that he was tenant, nor shall conclude him, others <hi>contra,</hi> one pleads, <hi>ne chasa pas,</hi> in Frank chase of the Plaintiffe, this is no granting that hee hath a free chase, but hee must prove it. One prayes to be received the demandant sayes that hee hath nothing in reversion day of Writt purchased,<note place="margin">10 E. 3. 20.</note> this doth not inferre that hee had after the writ purchased, but if he hath
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:205088:60"/> hee ought to have mentioned it upon his Prayer.<note place="margin">48 E. 3. 13. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="104">104 <hi>Nemo tenetur seipsum prodere.</hi> And for this in Cases criminall he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to answer to matters which tend to prove evidence in this, and if hee deny the matter, it seems no perjurie to be punished though hee answer otherwise then the truth is, and so Sir <hi>John Walter</hi> held in ease of an answer of a defendant in Star-Chamber, hee should not be charged in this for perjury. Exception. There was a man examined upon oath of goods of the Kings which were devised to him,<note place="margin">40 Ass. 35.</note> and come to the possession of the defend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt: and a juror may be examined upon oath if he have sufficient free hold,<note place="margin">12 H. 7. 29.</note> this is no crime, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="105">105 <hi>Negatio duplex est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffirmatio. A distresse was pro servitio inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cto.</hi> The defendant sayes,<note place="margin">9 H. 7. 13. Vide Litt. 220.</note>
               <hi>Quod non fuit inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctum,</hi> and ruled as good a plea, as if hee said it was done, though <hi>Conisby</hi> said it was but an argument in case of a grant, but it seems such Logicall curiosity shall not hold to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void a grant.<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 146.</note> It is said such a thing <hi>Non oportet fieri, nec non</hi> such a thing, though
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:205088:60"/> such expressions are <hi>duplex negatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 H. 7. 21.</note> yet its holden a good negation in Law, and no affirmation.</p>
            <p n="106">106 <hi>Ovune est a defeter chose ceo ne serra object alue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">42 E. 3. 14. 8 E. 4. 6.</note> One brings a Writt of conspiracie to defeate a villenage <hi>cony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onus perfraud</hi> it is no plea that hee is his villaine, so in <hi>libertate probanda.</hi> In er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror outlarie <hi>pro fine Regis</hi> is pleaded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, and holden no plea,<note place="margin">7 H. 6. 44.</note> for hee is to defeate all by this Writ,<note place="margin">6 E. 4. 9. 10.</note> in error for to adnul an outlary, if he is twenty times out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed, it shall not stop him, but hee may go on with his Writ of error. The hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band makes a Lease for life,<note place="margin">7 H. 4. 40.</note> of the land of the wife, rendering rent, and dyeth, the heire of the wife brings a <hi>sur cui in vita,</hi> the Tenant shall not alledge the reversion, and assets in the heire for that that he is to defeite this warrantie,<note place="margin">38 E. 3.</note> but note where the colaterall thing to be defeated is a legall bar of the principall right, there it will stay him, as where a writ of errour is brought to reverse a recoverie,<note place="margin">3 Rep. lin. <hi>Col.</hi> Case 61. 14. 6 H. 6. 3.</note> and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall warrantie is pleaded, this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantie will bar him of his Writ of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p n="107">107 <hi>Ou chose fait per implication serra
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:205088:61"/> bone &amp; contra.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Institutes 1.180.</note> A Letter of Attourney is to two to make liverie and seizin, and the one of them makes liverie the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing present, and nothing saying that is not good, but authority to three bayliffes, and to every of them, and two executes it, this is good because it is for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of justice. A record is <hi>Jurati. ex acti comperuerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 R. 3. 4.</note>
               <hi>quorum duodecum super sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum suum dicunt, &amp;c.</hi> and doth not say, <hi>electi, triati &amp; jurati</hi> this is errour though those words are implied in these words, <hi>super sacrum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 H. 7. 2.</note> Aid is prayed of the patron and ordinary, which are returned, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and doe not come,<note place="margin">7 H. 7. 11.</note> it is as much in Law as if he had come pleaded, and assen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A former doth not come to save his default, it is as much in Law as if he had come into Court and said, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee would not save his default. In an Assise the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe returns the Baliffe was attached,<note place="margin">48 Ass. 40.</note> and exception taken because the Sheriffe did not say, the partie could not be found and ruled that it is included, and is well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p n="108">108 <hi>Ou chose serra, rule per le greinder part de le state. Disseisee Releise</hi> to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasor,<note place="margin">Lit.</note> after he had made an estate for life,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:205088:61"/> his right to this free hold is gone also.<note place="margin">25 Ass. 7.</note> A Cognisee dischargeth the reversioner, or purchase, the neversion, the particular estate is freed also: Lessee of a Mannour,<note place="margin">14 E. 4. 6.</note> to which a villain regardant (is) the Lord in rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion manumits the villain, it seems this shall binde the Tenants for years, Tenant in dower releases her right to him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version upon a lease for life,<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Althams</hi> 151. 9 Report Case <hi>Ascough.</hi>
               </note> her right is gone even during the <hi>life of the Tenant</hi> for life. A menaltie is granted for life, the remainder in fee to the Tenant, it is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished in all: 9. <hi>Report Case, Ascough &amp; Quiks Case ibid.</hi> Land is given in taile, the remainder to the King, the tenant in taile shall hold of none. <hi>Fallit haec regula aliquando.</hi> A. is impleaded who hath nothing in the free hold, fee discends, this shall not make the writ good,<note place="margin">1 H. 6. 2.</note> but if the reversion of the fee discends to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold which he hath purschased, <hi>this makes</hi> the Writ good. A Parson makes a lease, the Patron who hath the fee simple confirmed, this shall not make this good against him,<note place="margin">Dyer 133. 7 Report <hi>Com. Bedfords</hi> case.</note> hath a grant of the Parsonage for yeers, &amp;c. See 2 <hi>Report Beckwiths Case, Instit.</hi> 1. 298.</p>
            <p n="109">109 <hi>Ouvneserra soujudg, demesne, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:205088:62"/> carver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12 H. 8. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lessor covenants to repaire the house, if he doe not the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see may pay himselfe of the tent. Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of a Church, at his own cost repairs the Church, and for amends deteined ten lodes of stones of the parishioners for which the successors Gardians bring an action of accompt,<note place="margin">37 Eliz. Case. <hi>Methold</hi> and <hi>Wing.</hi>
               </note> and adjudge that hee may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deteine them, <hi>aliter</hi> of a servant Baly, &amp;c. who doe disburse money, &amp;c. See the cases of Tailors, Hostlers, &amp;c. who may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine Robe,<note place="margin">8 Report case.</note> Horse, &amp;c. till reasonable sa-satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="110">110 <hi>Ou Chose in lieu serra de mesme le nature.</hi> Land escheat to the Lord who is in of the Signiory by discent,<note place="margin">6 H. 4. placito p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imo &amp; Kell 104.</note> so shall hee be of the land, and shall have his age, and if the Signiory was in tayle, so shall the land it self be, and the Donor of the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory shall have a <hi>forn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>don in revertor</hi> if hee dyes without issue. A fine is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of a Signiory and tenancy escheate,<note place="margin">46 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 4.</note> a <hi>Scire facias</hi> shall be of this land, and he shall not say nient comprise, for it shall be said parcell of the Mannor which comes <hi>in loco.</hi>
               <note place="margin">48 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="111">111 <hi>Parum differunt quae re concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi> A declaration was to have a Faire
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:205088:62"/> three days,<note place="margin">16 <hi>E.</hi> 2. action of Case 47.</note> and ruled that two dayes and two halt days will mayntain this declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. An assise was brought against <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> and <hi>Comminalty,</hi> and found that the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Bailiffs</hi> did the disseisin, but because no more was of the Comminalty then the Bailiffs it was held good.<note place="margin">31 Ass. 39.</note> But note where there is an apt form in the Register, there a man shall not differ from it. A <hi>Precipe quod redd at</hi> is forty and ten acres of land, &amp;c. and the Writ abated,<note place="margin">14 <hi>E.</hi> 2. F. Bre. 816.</note>
               <hi>quia non fuit quinqu aginta.</hi> The moity of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shillings and ten shillings is not all one, See <hi>Institute</hi> 3. 131.<note place="margin">Institut. 1. 197.</note> simile in point of pleading. See 17 <hi>E.</hi> 4 3. <hi>Testamentum &amp; literas testament arias</hi> all one.</p>
            <p n="112">112 <hi>Parols ou voilent amount al act &amp; contra.</hi> A condition of a bond was to permit I. S. to remove his goods, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal by word to remove them is no breach of this condition, without averring of bolting or locking the doore against him,<note place="margin">8 Report case <hi>Frances.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c But note where its said generally that such a one <hi>impedivit,</hi> interrupt or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbe, &amp;c. it is good without more as it seems and shall be intended actuall distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, yet see 47 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 24. <hi>Contra</hi> that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:205088:63"/> he ought to shew some cause or act done in his pleading.<note place="margin">5 Report 76. 22 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 17. 45 E. 3. 3.</note> A Commoner said to the Lord of the soyle that the soyle was his and commanded him to cut no trees, this will not amount to a disseisin.<note place="margin">26 Ass. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="113">113 <hi>Parols subsequent bounded or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by the precedent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dyer 240.</note>
               <hi>&amp; è converso.</hi> A termor covenants that for any act by him done, the assignee shall enjoy against every man, this is no <hi>absolute Covenant</hi> that he shall enjoy. A bond to make suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent estate as <hi>A</hi> shall devise, these last words take off the vigour of the former for the condition is well performed though the estate he makes be insufficient,<note place="margin">5 Report 23.</note> if <hi>A</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise this.<note place="margin">Pasc. 4. <hi>Car.</hi> Lady <hi>Smiths</hi> Case.</note> A Covenant is to surrender upon request, and to permit <hi>A</hi> to take the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, the <hi>word request</hi> doth not goe to the latter clause,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enill.</hi>
               </note> and he may take them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out request. Actuall seisin and possession spoken of the word actuall goes to the first onely. <hi>Soillicet Seisin, vide</hi> 49 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 16. 4 <hi>Report, Case Palmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="114">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 H. 6. 9.</note>114 <hi>Parolx font plea.</hi> The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a bond is if the Obligor <hi>do not pay,</hi> that then the bond shall be void, so it is that the Obligee shall pay, &amp;c. both are
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:205088:63"/> good and shall stand, and it is his folly, &amp;c. And not like the case where the <hi>solvendum</hi> was <hi>to the Obligor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 E. 4. 29.</note> for this may be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and is void, <hi>Ergo</hi> it shall not hurt. A Bond was made T. T. Sheriffe of W. in <hi>Com. perdict. pro praedict.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trin. 21. Iac. Case <hi>Nowel.</hi> in <hi>B.</hi> Roy.</note> &amp; ruled nought for the senslesnesse of the word <hi>perdict.</hi> but for <hi>parolls font</hi> plea, <hi>Vide placit hic</hi> 151.</p>
            <p n="115">115 <hi>Poena aptabitur damno.</hi> If a stranger commit waste in my land by which I lose treble damages,<note place="margin">44 E. 3. 27.</note> In trespasse against him damages shall be recovered treble.<note place="margin">9 Report Case <hi>Hussie.</hi>
               </note> Offence against a statute shall be punished as that says, and so at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law as that directs.</p>
            <p n="116">116 <hi>Poena sine culpa.</hi> Assise is against husband and wife,<note place="margin">7 H. 7. 2.</note> and shee sole did the wrong, and there is no <hi>other forme,</hi> Yet the plaintiffe shall be amerced as to the husband for naming him that did nothing and yet he cannot help it.</p>
            <p n="117">117 <hi>Poena delictum super abit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">40 E. 3. 6.</note> A man lets houses in decay at the time of letting and they are burnt by his negligence, hee is bound to make them new. <hi>A.</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orty shillings if the Sheriffe had made his returne by a legall officer, in an action upon the case for this,<note place="margin">38 As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.</note> he shall reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:205088:64"/> against the Sheriff twenty Marks.</p>
            <p n="118">118 <hi>Particeps criminis &amp; non poena.</hi> Tenant by entire service ceaseth, the Lord recovers in this part the cessor was,<note place="margin">6 Report Case <hi>Bruerton.</hi>
               </note> by this he shall lose his entire Signiory, and the tenant shall have benefit by it. Husband seised of land in right of his wife sowes the land,<note place="margin">5 Report <hi>Olands</hi> case.</note> and after he himselfe sues a divorce, <hi>Causa praecontractus,</hi> yet he shall have the Crop.</p>
            <p n="119">119 <hi>Poena tollitur cum culpa, vel se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur culpam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">14 H. 6. 26.</note> The King pardons all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienations, the fine due by this is also pardoned,<note place="margin">5 Report 49.</note> if a contempt is pardoned, the amercement also is.</p>
            <p n="120">120 <hi>Propositio hypothetica taken Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorice.</hi> I say to I. S. if hee will beat mee I will beat him,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 20. aut co circiter.</note> and this without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking words, this is a menace and an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 28.</note> and the if is idle. Administration is committed to two, and the one being present says, that he will take the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration upon him (if the other will agree) hee is administrator presently till the other disagree. One says to I. S. if thou go to <hi>London,</hi> thou art an arrant T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iefe, it seems these words are actionable, and shall be taken absolute. The defendant in action
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:205088:64"/> of batterie and menace, &amp;c. justifies thus, he saith that if the tenants of such lands will kill or maime him,<note place="margin">10 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 6.</note> hee will himselfe defend, and will rather beat or maime them then they shall him,<note place="margin">3 Car. in b. Roy <hi>Corbols</hi> case.</note> and this holden a good justification. I will prove him perjured if hee will justifie his answer in Chancery an action lies.</p>
            <p n="121">121 <hi>Principio non valens tractu tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris non convalescit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 Ass. 2.</note> A high way is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mee, to B. acre where I have no free hold in it, albeit after this grant I purchase B. acre, this shall not make the grant good. A suit is begun in <hi>London</hi> for the same matter,<note place="margin">14 H. 7. 7. 39 H. 6. 12.</note> for which a suit is depending in the common place, this is ill begun in <hi>London,</hi> now a nonsuit after in that in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place shall not amend that in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or make it of any validity.<note place="margin">10 Report 62.</note> A Bishop makes a Lease for foure lives, and one of the men for whose life, dies in the life of the Bishop,<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 46. 4 Report Case <hi>Herla:</hi>
               </note> this shall not make it a lease for three lives within the Statutes, 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. and 1 <hi>Eliz. vide ad idem</hi> 11 <hi>Report Case,</hi> Auditor <hi>Curle,</hi> &amp; 4 <hi>Report Druries Case.</hi> A man leases land for life, and then grants the trees which grow there, this shall not be a good grant after the Lessee dies. I sell
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:205088:65"/> a horse to I. S. upon condition to pay 40. shillings at Michaelmas next, and before this day I sell him to another, the first ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee failes of payment,<note place="margin">Plo. 432.</note> by which I reseise the horse, this will not make the second sale to be of force. Debt in the Stanneries is brought against an heire, which is not maintainable there by Law, now though he pleade a false plea,<note place="margin">9 <hi>Car.</hi> in b. Roy <hi>Smiths</hi> cale:</note> by which his goods are chargable there, this will not affirme their jurisdiction.<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Rowlins.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Exception</hi> this rule fails in things which have <hi>operation by estoppel,</hi> as if I let B. acre by deed indented, in which I have nothing if I purchase this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it is a good Lease.<note place="margin">9 H. 4. 1. Vide 8 E. 3. 24</note> So in case of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, one makes a return w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is no Sheriffe but afterward the Sheriffe avowes it was done by his Officer, this is good now. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caption lies not upon a reptisall of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse in case a Replevin was sued in a Mannor or Liberty,<note place="margin">F. N. B. 73.</note> and not in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet if it be removed this writ now is maintainable. The same Law is where the impediment is removed, tenant in taile is the remainder in taile of the grant of the King. Tenant in taile acknowledges a fine,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Report Case Lord <hi>Stafford.</hi>
               </note> or suffers a recovery it shall not binde but if after the reversion is put out of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:205088:65"/> Crown it will binde. Tenant for life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feffs him in remainder, in taile and his wife,<note place="margin">41 Ass. 2.</note> this is no forfeiture or discontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, because if shee die first it will bee a surrender, but if shee survive a forfeiture. This rule failes also by long continuance of time, as where a man prescribes to have a rent by distresse, &amp;c.<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E. 4. 4.</note> It is no plea to say it was always payed by cohersion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, albeit it was begun by wrong, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="122">122 <hi>Principio valens tractu temporis non devalescit.</hi> A man says to me see you I. S. I will kill him I may him hold,<note place="margin">9 E. 4. 16.</note> and I shall be excused of this imprisonment, though hee repent him, one makes a lease which is good, now by alteration, &amp;c. it shall never come to be forgery.</p>
            <p n="123">123 <hi>Principio dato sequitur concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, &amp; sit sublato.</hi> I have a Mannor in which is a Park and Fish-pond,<note place="margin">11 Report <hi>Lifords</hi> Case.</note> I lease this excepting the game, &amp;c. And after I grant the Reversion, the Deere and Fish shall passe as attendants. If a statute now made gives an action in case none lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the same Processe Judgement, and Execution shall be,<note place="margin">10 H. 7. 10.</note> as in the same action was in other Cases, where it lay before at
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:205088:66"/> the Common Law, albeit this statute doe not say any such thing. He which takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to grant a Rent,<note place="margin">5 Report 21.</note> it shal be by deed, and hee shall tender a Deed for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose without any agreement for it. A bond is to a Sheriffe to discharge him of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of an Exigent, he shall discharge him of all. Concomitants and therefore though he return him <hi>languidus in prisona,</hi> which discharges him.<note place="margin">18 E. 4. 21.</note> If after distresse <hi>ad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum corpus,</hi> goe forth to the new She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, and the old Sheriffe is distreined to the value of twenty pence, which is forfeit, now the Obligor hath failed of his promise. Cause of appeal is pardoned, and after an Exigent goes out, now the goods shall be saved which otherwise by award of the Exigent were forfeited,<note place="margin">45 Ass. 9.</note> because the principall was pardoned.</p>
            <p n="124">124 <hi>Praesumptioni stabitur donec probe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in contrarium.</hi> Unity at the time of the dissolution discharges tythes upon the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,<note place="margin">Michel. 40. &amp; 41 Eliz.</note> but this is upō presumptiō of prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. Now if it appeare upon evidence, that part of the Mānor was in leas &amp; paid tythes, this disproves the presumption, yet the residue of the Mānor shal be discharged of tithes. A man purchaseth land of I. S.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:205088:66"/> who is impleaded in a <hi>precipe quod reddat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">50 Ass. 3.</note> the law presumes him to be a Champerror without shewing hee was so till he may prove it otherwise.</p>
            <p n="125">125 <hi>Qui tacet consentire videtur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">27 Ass. 3. Vide placito 4</note> He which is present at the actuall killing of a man, and puts not debate shall be adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed assenting. A Writ is against foure, two wage their Laws of non summons,<note place="margin">8 H. 6. 36.</note> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two say nothing, it is so strong an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of jointenancie that they cannot deny it afterward, The Ordinary makes an appropriation to the Patron,<note place="margin">Plo. case. <hi>Grendon.</hi>
               </note> it shall be said made by his assent, <hi>vide Dyer</hi> 62.</p>
            <p n="126">126 <hi>Quisentit commodum sentire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet &amp; onus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">37. Ass. 10. F. Bar. 305.</note> He which hath any benefit of a river shall be charged with the scowring of it,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Dean.</hi> of <hi>W.</hi>
               </note> upon this reason it is that the assignee is chargeable in covenant to repair, though he is not named. A man grants a rent which is behinde, after he grants the land to another,<note place="margin">11 H. 4. <hi>ultimo</hi> 4 Report <hi>Og<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels</hi> case.</note> the grantee dies he which took the profits when the rent Became arreare shall pay it, See 20 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 10. 12, 18. 26 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 64, 30. I reteine Counsell for one,<note place="margin">30 H. 6. 9.</note> he shall pay the fee and not I.</p>
            <p n="127">127 <hi>Qui sentit onus sentire debet &amp; commodum.</hi> This the reason if a feffment is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:205088:67"/> upon conditiō▪<note place="margin">1 Report case <hi>Shelley</hi> 99. 9 H. 7. 25.</note> if the feffor or his heirs pay ten pounds before Michaelmas that they shal re-enter the father hath issue a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and dies, his wife being with childe of a sonne, the daughter paies the money, she shall hold the land. The husband and wife suffer a recoverie of land of the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,<note place="margin">Plo. case, <hi>Eare</hi> and <hi>Snowe.</hi>
               </note> and they vouch and have judgement to recover in value, the husband dies, the wife shall have nothing of the intended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence in this case, for shee lost no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p n="128">128 <hi>Qui per aliud facit per se ipsum facere videtur.</hi> An annuity is granted till he is promoted to a benefice by the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and his heirs in a Writ of annuity,<note place="margin">33 E. 1. anty 51</note> he shews the plantiffe was promoted by his mother at his request and <hi>bene.</hi>
               <note place="margin">19 H. 6. 8.</note> In tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe against A. and the evidence is that B struck me by his incitation and <hi>bene.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Report Case <hi>Frost.</hi>
               </note> A Baily arests mee, he may shew the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe did the arrest.<note place="margin">39 H. 6. 42. Dyer 241.</note> A Rescoufe is made to the servant of an officer, he may return the rescouse made to himselfe. An Abbot prescribes to hold land discharged of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tithes <hi>dum propriis manibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 Eliz. Dyer. 277.</note>
               <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colitur</hi> if it be tilled by his servants, it is within the prescription, outre with my
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:205088:67"/> beasts is my entre, and so he shall declare, <hi>Quare clausum fregit, vide</hi> 15 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 24.<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 5.</note> 21 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 16. 44 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 44. 12 <hi>H,</hi> 7. <hi>Kellow, Placito</hi> 7.<note place="margin">42 E. 3. 23.</note> But note this exception where it is matter of authority, it is otherwise, he must doe it himselfe.</p>
            <p n="129">129 <hi>Qui remedio destituitur reipsa va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, siculpa absit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 Report 63.</note> Upon this reason it is that he who hath a reversion by way of use which is executed by 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. shall a vow, have wast, &amp;c. without attorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Upon the same reason tenancie by curtesie, shall be of a rent before seism,<note place="margin">3 H. 7.</note> To make the obligor executor,<note place="margin">8 E. 4. 3.</note> is a release in law because he cannot release to himselfe, <hi>vide</hi> 7 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 11. <hi>fallit regula.</hi> A parson pays an annuity, and takes an acquittance, the successor shall not have this, &amp; yet his plea of payment is not good without it.<note place="margin">44 E. 3. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="130">130 <hi>Qui magis Scit &amp; potest de eo magis requiritur.</hi> If a stranger is to plead that such a one hath to name <hi>John Abbot</hi> of <hi>Ramsey,</hi> it is sufficient,<note place="margin">1 E. 4. 7.</note> but if the Abbot himselfe was to plead such a plea, he shall shew how his name is so, &amp;c. See 13 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 19.</p>
            <p n="131">131 <hi>Quicquid solo superstruitur solo cedet.</hi> And therefore if one build upon
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:205088:68"/> my land or plant trees they are mine. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception if my water by long continuance of time by little and little imperceptibly wear,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 93.</note> and so run upon your ground, yet it is mine and not his upon whose ground it runs.</p>
            <p n="132">132 <hi>Quicquid remittitur fieri aequat facto.</hi> A deed is delivered into equall hands, to be delivered to I. S. upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain conditions,<note place="margin">14 H. 6. 11.</note> the conditions are broken, but he that was party to the delivery doth release the conditions, now it's all one as if they had been performed,</p>
            <p n="133">133 <hi>Quae non prosunt singula juncta juvant.</hi> Tenant for life in remainder shall not punish wast nor have a Writ of right,<note place="margin">F. N. B. 30.</note> but if he joyne with him hath the fee, hee shall have both. Lessee for years grants part of his terme, and both joyne in a sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render,<note place="margin">14 H. 7. 4.</note> this is a good surrender, which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally was not good.</p>
            <p n="134">134 <hi>Quod necessario intelligitur non deest.</hi> A fine with proclamation is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and he shews that <hi>termino pasche,</hi> 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8. So many proclamations were and <hi>termino. Trin.</hi> 4. proclam: and Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas term 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">7 Eliz. Dyer 234.</note> other foure, and excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was taken that no terme was added
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:205088:68"/> to trinity, but ruled sufficient because it is added <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Easter and Michaelmas <hi>&amp; neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sario sub intelligitur</hi> to the other</p>
            <p n="135">135 <hi>Quod non capit discus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apit fiscus.</hi> The appellee in robbery disclaims in the goods, and after is acquitted,<note place="margin">12 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 5.</note> the King shall have them, money is to be paid to I. S. who dies without heirs or extor,<note place="margin">48 E. 3. 31. The Earle of <hi>Marches</hi> case.</note> and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questration was, &amp;c. It is said the King shall have this money.</p>
            <p n="136">136 <hi>Ratio dicti minus valet quam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ubi differunt.</hi> A Bishop certifies ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stardie, and indorces the reason of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the husband was beyond the Seas seven years,<note place="margin">38 Ass. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the certificate is good of the bastardie, and the reason of it reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <p n="137">137 <hi>Relations.</hi> It is a fiction in Law used to severall necessary purposes, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to make a nullity of a thing <hi>ab initio,</hi> which had an <hi>esse</hi> to certain purposes, and for other necessary uses in the Law.</p>
            <p n="138">138 <hi>Relatio &amp; non ad ultimum.</hi> A Writ is brought of rescuing his goods, and denying to pay toll, <hi>contra pacem, &amp;c.</hi> This shall refer to the Rescouse and not to the toll.<note place="margin">30 E. 3. 17.</note> Note where the thing is vain to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:205088:69"/> which the relation should be, as place &amp;c. there reference shall not be ad <hi>ultimum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">30 H. 6. 32 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 17.</note> in that kinde, where the place was not put <hi>pro loco,</hi> but for another purpose. A carve of land is in demand, medow, wood, and rent, &amp; an exception comes after all,<note place="margin">6 <hi>E.</hi> 3 42.</note>
               <hi>forstries</hi> to Acres▪ this exception goes to the Land, A demand is by Writ <hi>quod reddat manerium de W.</hi> &amp; two acres of land, <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m pertinentiis in</hi> Cliderow, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>cum pertinentiis</hi> shal be referred to the Mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r,<note place="margin">6 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 12. Sir <hi>Adam de Cliderows</hi> case. 17 <hi>E.</hi> 3 26 77. 1 Ast. 15.</note> bough it is in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Town then Cliderowes the same Law is where severall Lands in severall Towns are in demand <hi>precip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. &amp; interim mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suagia illa torras pratareditus, &amp;c: illa</hi> refer to all,<note place="margin">1 H. 6. 23. Plo <hi>Crofts</hi> case.</note> A bond is made to A, B, and C, Yeomen, this goes to all three <hi>destrirgas</hi> M.<note place="margin">4 H. 6. 3. Dyer 45.</note>
               <hi>quae fuit uxor</hi> T. S. <hi>de Marton Davie,</hi> this addition of place refers to M. A declaration was of a thing done at M. <hi>juxta Ston in Com. Northampton,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the defendant at <hi>Ston, in Com. predict.</hi> assume &amp;c. <hi>Warwick</hi> was in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and <hi>Ven. fac.</hi> went to the Sheriff of <hi>War:</hi> and tried there, and judgement was stayed for that <hi>Northampton</hi> was the last Town and County named, and the rule
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:205088:69"/> given that reference for the most part is to be <hi>ad proximum antecedens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. 35 Eliz. Case <hi>Child</hi> and <hi>Towers.</hi>
               </note> though it is absurd, or will orethrow a verdict, &amp;c. See <hi>Plo. Adams case.</hi> 6. exception. 9 <hi>Rep.</hi> 27 5 <hi>E</hi> 4. 126. <hi>F N. B.</hi> 2 <hi>D.</hi> 18 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 1. 6. <hi>Rep.</hi> Sir <hi>H. Finches case.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="139">139 <hi>Relation will rectifie incertainties in place time, measure, &amp;c.</hi> A condition of a bond was to discharge him of such a rent against R.<note place="margin">18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. ff. harr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 247.</note> &amp; also to pay his area<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s incurred before Michaelmas next both shall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Michael. by relation to this subsequent word Michaelmas. A Lease is of W. acre &amp; rent to be paid at D. upon the feast of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Michael,</hi> and if it is behinde by 40 daies to reenter,<note place="margin">Plo. 70. <hi>Kidwallies</hi> case.</note> though no pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce is appointed where it sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be paid at the 40 dayes end, it shall be referred to D. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition of a bond is to make a lease before Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas to the Obligee for 31 years, if A will assent, and if not, then for 21 years,<note place="margin">18 Eliz. Dyet 347.</note> A will not assent the lease for 21 years ought to be made before Michaelmas. Affise of the moitie of a house, a carve of Land, and 40 shillings rent, and ruled onely a moity of all is in demand.<note place="margin">24 Ass. 7.</note> A man grants ten acres of his land in D. <hi>simul cum commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:205088:70"/> posture in omnibus terris suis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 Ass. 3</note> This shall be in D. onely, and not charge his lands elsewhere.</p>
            <p n="140">140 <hi>Relation shall make things have been,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H. 7. 16.</note>
               <hi>as if they never had been.</hi> The hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band disagrees to a feffment made by his wife, it is void <hi>ab initio,</hi> so that he may plead <hi>ne infeffa pas,</hi> A devise is that execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors may sell land, &amp;c. when they sell all mean charges made by the heire in the interim shall be avoided by relation to the time of the death of the testator.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H. 7. 1 H. 8. 10.</note> I dissese A. to the use of B. the disseisee releas to me, and then B. agrees, this agreement by rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall be as if he had agreed before the release,<note place="margin">14 H. 8. 18.</note> and so shall defeate it. Jurors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien their Land away between the teste of the writ of attaint and judgement, yet they shall be charged to the King for the estrepment by relation.<note place="margin">12 E. 3. 26.</note> Cause of assise brought was for rescuing a distresse taken for rent, and then an office is found which intitles the King, who seises the Land, and then an <hi>ouster le main</hi> is sued, the assise is gone for ever, because the King shall bee said in possession at the time of the rescous by relation of this office,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 Ass. 1.</note> upon whose pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:205088:70"/> no distresse could be made. <hi>See Plo.</hi> 281. 10 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 18.</p>
            <p n="141">141 <hi>Relation to defeat a thing, shall be intent a ad unum</hi> Husband and wife te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in tail,<note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>B.</hi>
               </note> shee brings dower after his death, this unsetleth the estate was joynt in them two, but shall not have relation to defeat a Reversion granted by the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner Atournament makes the services past <hi>ab initio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">48 E. 3. 16. 11 H. 7. 8.</note> yet nothing of the arrears shall be paid in prejudice of the tenants which are third persons. The Lord is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled to the marriage of an heire of the disseisee, the heire release to the dissessor, hee is in now from the time of the first disseisen of a good estate,<note place="margin">7 H. 6. 12.</note> but this shall not hurt the Lord of his Wardship, &amp;c. An infant is infeoffed and disagree, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feats it <hi>ab initio,</hi> as to himselfe to avoid all dammages,<note place="margin">3 Report Cas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>B.</hi>
               </note> but not to make a void gift by his feffor good: a remainder is limited to the King, and before inrolment of the deed he grants this over,<note place="margin">Ibib.</note> and then the deed is inrolled, this will not make the grant good.</p>
            <p n="142">142 <hi>Relation will yeeld to necessity.</hi> The husband is essoyned, and at the day
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:205088:71"/> fails to bring in his warrant, or doth not appear, the judgement shall relate to the time of the protection,<note place="margin">2 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 17. 21 Ass. 17.</note> or essoign cast, &amp;c. yet his wife may bee received for no time covenable was before to pray to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved untill default, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="143">143 <hi>Relation shall not be to take away things collaterall, &amp;c.</hi> Trespasse is made to A. and after his estate is defeated by condition performed or Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">4 H. 7. 11.</note> this shall not relate to take away his action vested,<note place="margin">3 Report Case <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. A bond is delivered to my use, I disagree this shall now loose his force from the time of the disagreement onely.</p>
            <p n="144">144 <hi>Relatio ad principium, &amp;c.</hi> Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see for yeers is bound to I. S. to make to him the best estate he can,<note place="margin">12 H. 8. 5.</note> and afterward the reversion, or releases to him, the les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see shall be discharged of the bond if hee grant the estate he had at the bond make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Estranger abates, after the death of the father,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 60.</note> the son dyes his wife shall not have dower for this abatement shall relate to the death of the father.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E. 4. 33. 8 H. 6. 22.</note> Administratour <hi>de son tort</hi> takes letters of administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this shall relate to the death of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:205088:71"/> Intestate. An Escrow is delivered by a feme sole,<note place="margin">14 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 2. 21 H. 6. 3 Report case. <hi>Ionnings</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> 33 H. 6. 17. 1 Report 199.</note> if she marry or dye yet by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation it shall be good. An Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath relation to the first day of the Session. Presentment <hi>tempore belli</hi> is not good to gain possession, though ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction was <hi>in tempore pacis,</hi> a blow given in time of <hi>in sane memory,</hi> though he dye when of sane memory it is not capitall. Sale of goods is out of the market, and after they are brought into the market and delivered there, yet it relates to the first sale, &amp;c.<note place="margin">1 Mar. Dyer. 99.</note> and so takes away no property of an Estran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p n="145">145 <hi>Relation to time▪ place, &amp;c.</hi> In case of atteindor by verdict in felony, It shall relate to the time of the fact done,<note place="margin">30 H. 6. 5.</note> of outlary it is otherwise, but in case of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son outlary shall relate to the fact done. Atteindor by Act of Parliament shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the first day of the Parlia.<note place="margin">35 H. 8. <hi>B.</hi> Crom p. 77. Dyer 50.</note> one shall not be accessary to a felony by relation, but onely from the death not blow given. Arbitrement was pleaded at D. <hi>scilicet</hi> that such an one shal grant an Annuity out of the Mannour of S. &amp; in conclusion says, <hi>quod loco supradicto, &amp;c.</hi> this shall relate
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:205088:72"/> to D.<note place="margin">12 H. 6. 17.</note> and the <hi>Venire facias</hi> shal be thence a <hi>Venire facias</hi> was <hi>ad recognoscendū,</hi> if an Executor did administer <hi>aliqua bona</hi> that were the Testators after his death, these words after his death, shall relate to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minister and not to goods,<note place="margin">7 H. 4. 37.</note> to examine whether they came after the death or not.</p>
            <p n="148">148 <hi>Relatio sit ad accommodatiora.</hi> A man leases for the life of I. S.<note place="margin">Hill. 19. Elia. <hi>Gowers</hi> case.</note> &amp; after gives all his lands &amp; reversion of this parcell <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum</hi> all his lands and parcell <hi>cum acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit proxime post mortem</hi> I. S. these last words shall relate to the reversion onely. The Obligee doth acknowledge he is sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied,<note place="margin">9 Report Case <hi>Hickman.</hi>
               </note> all bonds, and promiseth to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in all bonds (except one of ten pound, this exception-goes to the <hi>word satisfied,</hi> and restreins this and not onely to the words deliver in,<note place="margin">11 Report 32.</note> see the word <hi>(such)</hi> is to equalls in the mischiefe and not to any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the statute there named. See 22 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 4. Condition of a bond was, if the Defendant enter peaceably, so that the Plaintiffe may bring his action before <hi>Michaelmasse,</hi> in this case, these words before <hi>Michaelmasse</hi> shal relate to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre<note place="margin">27 H. 6. 18.</note>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:205088:72"/> onely, and not to the bringing of the action.</p>
            <p n="149">149 <hi>Relation to avoid thing or a vaine thing will destroy that was good in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises.</hi> As a grant is by me of my lands in D. which I had by descent, or of the gift of I. S. if this he false it will destroy my grant, A bond to performe all Covenants between A. B. and C,<note place="margin">37 H. 6. 18.</note> in such an Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and there is not any such, the bond is not good, one makes an acquittance of debt, which was recovered by a judgment, &amp;c. and there is no such it is <hi>void,</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 H. 7. 6.</note> hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife are seised of land, and a grant is made of the reversion of the land which the husband holds, this is void to passe this reversion. <hi>Contra sepius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">33 H. 8. Dyer. 50.</note> A bond is of thirty pound and the Obligee upon receit of twenty pound, &amp;c. makes an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance thus,<note place="margin">11ff. Grants 63</note> received in part of twenty eight pound, &amp;c. the summe of twenty pound, this shall not make frustrate the acquittance if not that averment is that twenty eight pound was for another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. A reversion of lands in D. <hi>quae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia sunt,</hi> in lease to I. S.<note place="margin">48 E. 3. 18.</note> for life is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though no such lease is, it is good. See
<pb facs="tcp:205088:73"/>
               <hi>Plou.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plo. Case <hi>Throgmorton.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Adams case,</hi> 5. <hi>exception,</hi> 10 <hi>Rep. Legats case,</hi> an indēture of defesanes refers to a Statute made <hi>primo Maii, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 35. Sir <hi>Iohn Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shals</hi> Case.</note> and it was ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her day, yet it is good because an agreement was in the summe of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and name of the parties. See 20 <hi>Ass.</hi> 8. 26 <hi>Ass.</hi> 38. 31 <hi>Ass.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="148">148 <hi>Semel malus semper presumitur malus &amp; contra.</hi> A Jury was challenged <hi>cum panello,</hi>
               <note place="margin">33 Ass. placito ultimo.</note> for being made favourably by an Officer of the Sheriffes, and upon a new <hi>Ven. fac.</hi> part of the same jurors are returned by the Sheriffe himselfe, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led bene, and the suspition shall not be said to continue.</p>
            <p n="149">149 <hi>Similitude non currit quatuor pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus</hi> Resommons is <hi>ita quod sit (in eodem statu.)</hi> Yet a default saved, which was before discontinuance,<note place="margin">5 <hi>H.</hi> 7. 39. 40.</note> so essoigne lies which did not before.</p>
            <p n="150">150 <hi>Sic utere tuo ut non laedas alieno.</hi> Lessee for years shall so take his hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bote,<note place="margin">46 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 17.</note> that he doe not destroy common of estouers which another man hath there, he which hath common in Land not inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,<note place="margin">20 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 11.</note> shall keep his cattle out of an estran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers land. If beasts are driven by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:205088:73"/> he ought at his perill keep them out of the Lands adjacent to the way, &amp;c.<note place="margin">20 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 11. 10 E. 4. 7.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in case where the owner is bound to inclose &amp;c. but note, prejudice may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue by my act upon my own land without danger, as where a man erects a wall, part upon my land,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pasch. 34.</hi> Eliz. <hi>C.</hi> Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford vers. Gill.</note> and I destroy this upon my land, and the rest by that means falls down this is excusable.</p>
            <p n="151">151 <hi>Singulare distributive sumpta aequat plurali.</hi> Tenant in assise makes se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall bars, &amp; the plantiffe makes severall titles,<note place="margin">Dyer 325.</note> and the tenant pleads <hi>veigne l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssise supra titulo,</hi> this goes to all the titles. A lease is <hi>pro uno anno,</hi> and if they agree that he shall have the land for threee years <hi>reddendo durante termino praedict.</hi> ten pounds annuatim this reservation goes to both termes.<note place="margin">10 Report Case. <hi>Loefeild.</hi>
               </note> In debt the plantiffe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that the defendant and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were bound in an obligation <hi>sigello suo sigillat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 33 <hi>Eliz-</hi> Case <hi>Briton</hi> &amp; <hi>Bolton.</hi>
               </note> this extends <hi>distributive</hi> to both.</p>
            <p n="152">152 <hi>Synonyma will not serve in our Law.</hi> The Statute <hi>W.</hi> 2. forbids entre, <hi>ubi ingressus non datur per legem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 19.</note> now if in an indictment, &amp;c. it is layed, <hi>quod
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:205088:74"/> ingressus est illicite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Long.</hi>
               </note> this is not good, so an indictment for murther by thes words, <hi>ex malitia precogitata necavit, &amp;c.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not good without the word, <hi>murdraivi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="153">153 <hi>Surplusage, what power and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence this shall have in Grants &amp;c.</hi> And note some use may be made of it, as where a contract is to deliver a horse &amp;c. and a bond is to deliver it,<note place="margin">8 E. 4. 22. <hi>Perkins.</hi> 784.</note> now albeit by the contract the property be vested in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligee, yet in this case if the horse is tendred to him, and he refuse, he hath lost the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, because this bond which was more then needed hath determined the contract, <hi>nota.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="152">152 <hi>Totum continet suas partes &amp; è converso.</hi>
               <note place="margin">30 E. 3. 13. 7 Report Case <hi>Bulwar.</hi>
               </note> The Statute <hi>W.</hi> 2, which gives a writ <hi>ad petendum advocationem decima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> implies he shall have this writ for a fourth part of Tithes.<note place="margin">2 Eliz. Dyer 186.</note> A statute is made that the adjournment of Michaelmas Terme shall not hinder fines, &amp;c. This im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies that though part of the Terme onely is adjourned, that shall not let, but fines are well levied. A Statute is if a man is redissessed of land,<note place="margin">Institut. 1. 154.</note> hee hath recovered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, such a penaltie shall bee, if he is redis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seised
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:205088:74"/> but of part of that Land, it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that statute. A man hath a way for foot, horses and waynes, if this is made so strait that wayns cannot passe, which is onely part of that he hath way for, yet the writ shall be, <hi>quod obstruxit viam</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
            <p n="155">155 <hi>Totius &amp; partis eadem ratio.</hi> Aid was granted for part of the Land charged with rent, it shall stand for all.<note place="margin">22 H. 6. 2. 24.</note> He which diverts part of a water shall be said in law to divert it all, <hi>fallit regula aliquoties.</hi> A liberate comes to an Officer to pay a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, if he <hi>have it all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Institut. 4. 116.</note>
               <hi>he ought to pay it,</hi> but if he want part thereof, hee is not bound to pay that part &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="156">156 <hi>Totum qui concedit partes negare non potest.</hi>
               <note place="margin">23 Ass. 12.</note> It is alledged in Assise that all the lands within the fee of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Yorke</hi> were departible between the males, and that the ten acres in question were within that fee, and the tenant would have said that these ten acres were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partible, but was not suffered. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exception. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>This doth not hold where the matter affirmed of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell tends onely to alter the jurisdiction.</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 E. 3. 18.</note> As where a Mannor is alledged to be anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:205088:75"/> Demesne, hee may say that Black acre parcell of the Mannor is Frankfee. <hi>Fallit regula,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exception. </seg>2</label> also in case of time that which may be said of a moneth of time, cannot of a week, &amp;c. As the statute 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> gives a penalty against him trades by the space of a moneth, not being an apprentice, &amp;c. if he trade but a weeke or fortnight hee shall forfeit nothing at all within this Law.</p>
            <p n="157">157 <hi>Tort, of his own wrong, a man shall not take advantage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 18. 5 Report Case <hi>Wimarke.</hi>
               </note> I.S. takes from me the release he had made, now I shall plead it without shewing it. Lessee for years cut trees,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Harlakenden.</hi>
               </note> he shall not have avail of this to keepe it toward reparations, &amp;c, Husband and wife are impleaded, and the demandant holds the wife of the tenant that shee cannot appear,<note place="margin">10 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 40.</note> this shall not turn to a default in the tenant. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exception. </seg>3</label> See 4 <hi>Report Case</hi> Sir <hi>Andrew Corbet, &amp;</hi> 34 <hi>H</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Regula, fallit,</hi> in case hee to whom the wrong is done had it in his power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy it, there it shall prejudice him if he doe not remedy it, and it shall be to the availe of the wrong dore, as I am bound to infeffe I. S. before Michaelmas of B.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:205088:75"/> acre, and the obligee,<note place="margin">8 Report 92. <hi>Frances</hi> Case.</note> disseise mee of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cre, here because I may enter and regain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Land and make the feff, if I doe not I have forfeited my bond: So where Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is to build a house by the lessee before the end of the Terme, and lessor enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and outs him, yet hee is bound to doe it, or else the Covenant lies,<note place="margin">36 Eliz. Case. <hi>Farewell</hi> and <hi>Barker.</hi>
               </note> unlesse there be speciall matter to excuse it, as if the other hold him out by force.</p>
            <p n="158">158 <hi>Utile per inutile non vitiatur, nec emendatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Report 93.</note> Of this nature is all <hi>Surplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage</hi> in grants, deeds, &amp;c. It doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor ill. A. release to B. <hi>ad primum diem Maii quod esset.</hi>
               <note place="margin">35 H. 8. Dyer 57.</note> All Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, &amp;c. this is a present release, and the subsequent words <hi>ad primum diem Maii quod esset</hi> are idle. A deed is that such a thing shall be done before Whit-Sunday next, being the first day of June,<note place="margin">Pasch. 1. Car. Case Bishop of <hi>Norwich.</hi> Vid. 41. Ass. 21</note> though Whit-Sunday is the fourth of June, this shall not frustrate the agreement, but shall be made on Whit-Sunday. Uses are decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in an indenture in taile, in which is power of revocation,<note place="margin">8 Report Case <hi>Frances.</hi>
               </note> and upon recitall of this deed he declares that <hi>praedicti usus,</hi> to him and his heirs shall be void, yet this
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:205088:76"/> a good revocation, and the other word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> idle, <hi>scil.</hi> to him and his heirs. A rent is granted for legality of partition,<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 146. 147. Vid. 30. H. 6. 14</note> this is good without deed, now annuity doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lie though a deed is in this case made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause surplus,<note place="margin">14 E. 4. 2.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Exception,</hi> Sometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> idle and vain words will have operation as A.<note place="margin">2 Report Case <hi>Buckler.</hi>
               </note> release to B. <hi>omni modas</hi> (which the said B. hath against A.) this was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged a void release. Lessee for life make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a lease for three years, &amp; then grants <hi>tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a praedict a habendum</hi> after Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masse,<note place="margin">4 Report Case <hi>Palmer.</hi>
               </note> all this is void. The Sheriffe in executing a <hi>Fiere facias</hi> takes upon him upon the sale of a Terme, to nominate the beginning of the terme, and saies it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Maii,</hi> where it was another day: this surplus makes the whole execution null. An union was pleaded to be <hi>concurrenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus his quae jure debent, &amp;c.</hi> and by as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Ordinary, this surplusage ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly contradicts that was implyed in the <hi>concurrentibus his,</hi> &amp;c. in which the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary might well have been intended also which now appears that he is not,<note place="margin">10 H. 7. 19.</note> and so vitiates all the rest, &amp;c. for surplusage in cases of pleading, the Law varies upon se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:205088:76"/> distinctions, in one case it shall hurt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad not in another, where surplusage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes a contradiction there it will doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urt;<note place="margin">22 Ass.</note> so in case of a Writ where there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot substance to maintain the action,<note place="margin">39 H. 6. 38.</note> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or to increase damages, it shall doe no harme. <hi>Plo.</hi> 85. 46 <hi>E.</hi> 3, 3. 1 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 7.<note place="margin">37 H. 8. 3.</note>
               <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> 6. 6. 12 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Kell.</hi> 10 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 10. 8 <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> 159 <hi>Dyer</hi> 235, 236. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 6 34 <hi>H.</hi> 6. 48.</p>
            <p n="159">159 <hi>Void, in a Statute where it is said what sense it hath, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">28 H. 8. Dye 28.</note> Obseeve first where a Statute saies such a thing shall be void,<note place="margin">3 Report 59. Plo. 107.</note> yet the ordinary circumstances are to be observed, which by law are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to avoid such a thing as entre, and the like.<note place="margin">Institutes 1. 273.</note> The Cannon saith that a second shall Benefice void, see if before sentence, <hi>vide Statut.</hi> 21. <hi>H.</hi> 8. by that it is void pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently and lapse shall incurre, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theine avoidance is not grantable by a Patron because it's void. If it be inacted that a bond made by I.S. shall be void, as upon the Statute of 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. of Sheriffes, such a clause is for a bond taken by a She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe otherwise then is there directed,<note place="margin">5 Report 119</note> yet he shall not plead <hi>non est factum,</hi> but
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:205088:77"/> the speciall matter and demand.<note place="margin">Plo. 169.</note> judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, See action Stat. <hi>W.</hi> 2. <hi>Case</hi> 1. whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sayes,<note place="margin">Plo. 137.</note>
               <hi>quod finis sit nullus,</hi> yet it is not ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solutely void, but avoidable by errour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not otherwise, the Stat. of 3 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grants of Deanes, &amp;c. shall be void, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not so in all respects,<note place="margin">11 Report 73.</note> for it's good agains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him that made it, but void as to the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor.</p>
            <p n="160">160 <hi>Void, where a thing shall be for part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 E. 4. 7, 8.</note>
               <hi>or for a certain time onely.</hi> A man contracts for wages beyond that the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute alows, this is void as to the wages, but shall charge him in an action upon the Statute.<note place="margin">Abridg. assis. 87.</note> A man enters into Religion, and his wife aliens the Land, of which they were seised, and then he is darreined, he shall avoid this for his life, but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lience shall hold it against the wife, so a terme may be avoided by tenant in dower &amp; revived afterward,<note place="margin">7 Report <hi>Com. Bedfords</hi> Case.</note> and it shall be good against the heire.</p>
            <p n="161">161 <hi>Void act as to that was intended, may yet be good and effectuall to a colate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall purpose.</hi> An appeale is void being brought by the youngest son,<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 29.</note> yet this shall him excuse to be indicted, if the party is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:205088:77"/> acquitted upon this, but otherwise it is in case a woman brings an appeal of the death of another, then her husband because it is apparently ill within the record it selfe. A release of a feme covert is pleaded, this is void to make a barr,<note place="margin">18 H. 6. 29.</note> yet it will amount to a waiver of a good plea pleaded before to the writ. An issue joyned in waste was a <hi>jeofale,</hi> the same plea notwithstanding may bee a confession of the wast.<note place="margin">10 Eliz. Dyer 272.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne is by one Coronor of a Rescous upon a writ made to more Coronors, it is a voide returne,<note place="margin">39 H. 6. 42.</note> yet it will be a good sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion upon which a processe shall issue for the Rescous: But <hi>nota,</hi> such a void act shall never bee good or avaleable in the same kinde it was void.<note place="margin">Pasch. 11. <hi>Car.</hi> Cafe. <hi>Baker</hi> and <hi>Hagget.</hi>
               </note> Tenant in taile is, the remainder to himselfe in fee, he makes a feofment by deed, and a letrer of Atourney, &amp;c. if this livery is not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the remainder shall not passe by the deed: Bargain and saile is of a mannor,<note place="margin">11 Report 48.</note> and all the trees the deed is not inrolled, this shall not work as a grant of the trees being of no effect for the Land. A man leases a mannor,<note place="margin">16 H. 7. 3.</note> and hath nothing in demesne at the time, but in services these
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:205088:78"/> shall not passe, but <hi>this exception hath its exception,</hi> as where the thing is <hi>void, quoad modum onely</hi> as a fine,<note place="margin">4 Eliz. Dyer 215</note> upon 4 <hi>H.</hi> 7. is not good for lack of proclamations, yet it's a good fine at the Common Law.<note place="margin">1 H. 6. 4. 7.</note> A Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is acknowledged which is not good, for some failers, &amp;c. yet it is a good bond.</p>
            <p n="162">162 <hi>Volenti non fit injuria.</hi> A man shoots giving warning to all,<note place="margin">18 E. 4. 8. 19 E. 4. 2.</note> &amp;c. and one will go to the mark and is hurt he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy. I am bound to make a house if you prohibit me to come upon the land I may plead this in bar, <hi>exception</hi> is where the fault and injury is essential to the thing and vitiates it, and is not personall, the law is otherwise, as where I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change with one hath a bad <hi>title</hi> and its knowne to me. So if I know of fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent conveyance and you buy the land,<note place="margin">5 Report Case <hi>Gooche.</hi>
               </note> in both these cases the party shall have the remedy though hee was willing to the wrong, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="163">163 <hi>Verba discretiva, shall not extend to joynt words &amp; contra.</hi> The Amercements of my tenants are granted,<note place="margin">22 Ass. 49.</note> this shall not extend to those <hi>hold of mee and of others.</hi> where its spoken of an act to be made by
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:205088:78"/> A.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins.</hi> 158. &amp; 310.</note> it shall be by him sole and not joyntly with others, but a surrender of all his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, is good of those hee holds joyntly as of others. Statute 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6. is if one enter with force or peaceably and hold with force an action lyes,<note place="margin">Plo. 8. 6. 3 E. 4. 19.</note> yet if both are done the action lyes.</p>
            <p n="164">164 <hi>Verba conjuncta non capiantur discretive &amp; contra.</hi> A <hi>Recordare</hi> is to remove a plea betweene <hi>A</hi> and <hi>B.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 H. 7. 14.</note> Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs, and <hi>C.</hi> and <hi>D.</hi> Defendants, and every Plaintiffe would have counted severally and not permitted, for it shall be intended joynt plaint onely.<note place="margin">29 E. 3. 20.</note> A statute speaks of an act to be done by two parties, this shall be intended joynt act. 5 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 14, 15. <hi>Contra</hi> where they shall be taken discretive,<note place="margin">2 R. 3. 18.</note> three men then submit of all matters betweene them and <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 H. 7. 29.</note> this extends to matters se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall among them, as well as joynt. Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Demises and Rents are in one Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">No. lib. Entry 115.</note> and in conclusion hee covenants to pay <hi>reditum praedictum,</hi> this goes to all the Rents. Two joyn in a grant of <hi>omnia bona sua,</hi> so a release to <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">19 H. 6. 4.</note> this extends to their severall goods and severall actions to have operation to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:205088:79"/> the most advantage against him made the deed or grant. Three severall men covenant separatim by Indenture and in this, one is bound to perform the covenants made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>A.B.</hi> &amp; <hi>C.</hi> &amp;c. he shall be bound to performe any covenant made betwixt them seperatim.<note place="margin">11 H. 7. 6.</note> Severall rents are behind by a Prior and his Predecessour, and in his Count he concludes, <hi>non dum rediderunt,</hi> And this holden good though part was due in the time of the Predecessor,<note place="margin">17 E. 3. 2.</note> and part since.</p>
            <p n="165">165 <hi>Una hirundo non facit ver.</hi> A Lord hath allowance one time to have <hi>Conusans of plea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 E. 3. 2.</note>
               <hi>ubi ipse pars fuit,</hi> this will not serve at another time to hold such plea.</p>
            <p n="166">166 <hi>Universale non comprehendit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne particulare. A</hi> man is reteined to serve in all occupations.<note place="margin">38 H. 6. 13.</note> In debt for wages the defendant may wage his law, which yet hee cannot do in <hi>case of husbandry, Ergo. In decies tantum,</hi> it is no plea for the defendants to say that they tooke not any mony for saying their verdict,<note place="margin">21 H. 6. 20.</note> but they shall say, <hi>nec aliquis eorum, &amp;c.</hi> See 3 <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> Marquesse of <hi>Winchesters</hi> Case, where all rights in a statute did not extend
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:205088:79"/> to right of action.<note place="margin">4 H. 7. 8. 6 Report 56.</note> So where an exigent is returned against three; <hi>quod non compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruerunt,</hi> it must be <hi>nec aliquis eorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruit, &amp;c.</hi> else its not good.</p>
            <p n="166">166 <hi>Ubi duo jura in una concurrunt persona aeque est ac in diversis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Institut. 1. 194. 195. Institute 3. 134 <hi>Holcroft</hi> Case.</note>
               <hi>Articuli super chartas ordaneth.</hi> That in case of death of one within the Verge, the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the County, and of the houshold of the King shall joyne in the Inquire, and holden if <hi>one is Coroner</hi> of both he shall well executeth is authority.</p>
            <p n="167">167 <hi>Vigilantibus &amp; non dormientibus subveniunt leges.</hi> This the reason of lapse incurring for lack of presentment. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty barring for lack of entry, discents barr entryes for lack of clayme, title to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy by curtesie is lost for lack of entry. statutes of limitations barr actions,<note place="margin">Litt. 551.</note> the first Grantee that its attornment shall have the Reversion or Signiory, &amp;c. and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Cases more are ruled upon this ground.<note place="margin">36 H. 6. 1.</note> A man is outlawed and error is in the Record this may be reversed, the same terme by plea, but after not. A trespasse is committed to two joynttenants, and each of them releases, and after brings trespasse,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:205088:80"/> and the defendant pleads the release of one of them which is found against him hee shall not be afterward admitted to plead the other release, because he hath surceased his time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finis Topicorum legum</hi> Angliae. Which was allowed to the Presse two yeers since <hi>in furore belli,</hi> but the Booksellers were unwilling to Print it then because it was in French and few in town.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205088:80"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>